<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-04T10:57:21+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">KITAB</title><subtitle>The Website for the KITAB project</subtitle><author><name>KITAB</name></author><entry><title type="html">Post 1: Al-Tabari’s Direct Informants: Work on a New Data Set</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Post-1-Al-Tabari-s-Direct-Informants-W3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post 1: Al-Tabari’s Direct Informants: Work on a New Data Set" /><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Post-1--Al-Tabari%E2%80%99s-Direct-Informants--W3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Post-1-Al-Tabari-s-Direct-Informants-W3/">&lt;p&gt;In a series of eight blog posts, we share some results of experimental work on citations in three works by Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari (d. 310/923). These are his universal history, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;; his Quran commentary, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt;, an incomplete work on traditions, arranged according to the last transmitter of the Hadiths and also according to the Prophet’s Companions. All three are important works in their own fields and contain numerous citation chains (&lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s). These &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s provide a fascinating and previously untried opportunity for historians to understand his working methods.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What We Want&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three works, al-Tabari refers repeatedly to people who gave him information directly with the phrase ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Our goal was to use these citations to build up a picture of his working methods relevant to Arabic book history. Our specific questions were the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari’s books are full of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and give the general impression of a man on the move, gathering information from many corners. How big was his source base? In particular, how many people gave him information directly on a significant scale (we call these people ‘direct informants’)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What form might the material he obtained from these people have taken? The field generally now accepts the idea that notebooks played a major role in knowledge transmission, especially before al-Tabari’s lifetime. Al-Tabari rarely cites books – that is, works that circulated under specific titles. Do his books provide evidence of the use of notebooks?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To what extent do all three works rely on a common source base? Did al-Tabari reuse his own material, copying, for example, parts of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; into the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, or vice versa?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions address a larger set of issues in book history relating to the idea of the book and the form and evolution of the written Arabic tradition in the third/ninth century and beyond. A major argument running through these posts is that al-Tabari worked efficiently. The total word count of the three works considered here is 4.72 million words. But despite the size of his works and the number of citations in them, he relied heavily on a surprisingly small number of people as his sources. Another major argument is that he relied specifically on notes, collated into notebooks whose structure and content we can imagine in some detail, if not reconstruct precisely. His ability to recall information from these notebooks was critical to his compositional method. He compiled the notebooks in his youth using information he obtained from people with whom he spent significant periods of time. The material that found its way into his writing was (metaphorically) indexed to these people, his experiences with them and the writings that he carried with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book historians working on the third/ninth century struggle to make sense of what can seem a bewildering situation. We find references to works and authors from this period in, among others, the &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; of the bio-bibliographer Ibn al-Nadim (d. 385/995). But when we try to match a book to an author, we often find that the book took its final form only much later – perhaps after decades or more. Or we discover that when Ibn al-Nadīm refers to a person’s writings, he had in mind something smaller, or less permanent, than what we would today recognise as a book. The most frequently encountered situation is that a work mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; no longer survives, at least independently. More perplexingly, we find citations of authors in works that post-date the authors’ lifetimes, but with no references to actual books written by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we as historians describe the working habits of authors in this period, we may feel like the proverbial blind men, each trying to describe an elephant but able only to name a feature or two of it – be it ears, tail or skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than thirty years ago, Gregor Schoeler prompted us to think harder about the meaning of ‘book’, especially in the second/eighth and third/ninth centuries (Schoeler had predecessors, but his impact on the cohort of current historians has been unique). He distinguished an essentially private note set or notebook (&lt;em&gt;hypomnēma&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;hypomnēmata&lt;/em&gt;) from ‘actual books’, purposely crafted for publication to an audience of readers (&lt;em&gt;syngramma&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;syngrammata&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This important distinction supplanted the earlier perceived binary between the written and the oral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historians adopted Schoeler’s model and have used it particularly to describe the emergence and development of what for him were ‘actual books’. The third/ninth century is now frequently considered the period that witnessed the ‘rise of the Arabic book’ (as Beatrice Gruendler’s 2020 monograph is titled). Letizia Osti and James Weaver have made the important observation that from the second half of the third/ninth century onwards, books come to possess features that make them ‘increasingly usable for independent reading and study’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Division into topical chapters, hierarchical structuring, the use of section- and chapter-headings, detailed tables of contents within programmatic introductions, and alphabetically ordered lemmata, as well as regular cross-referencing, all enable the autonomous reader to navigate unfamiliar material with greater ease, to some extent perhaps facilitating consultation in addition to linear reading.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the third/ninth century no doubt witnessed changes towards the ‘well-organised book’, we would like to add a further layer of complexity by giving greater consideration to the personal side of writing. We believe that citations and text reuse data reveal that authors’ approaches to their writing were more diverse than we recognise today and that the types of authority that these approaches carried were also more varied than we currently imagine. We can perceive these features by examining al-Tabari’s citations and reading Ibn al-Nadim’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; alongside them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are convinced that further questions can productively be asked about the written Arabic tradition. The question we wish to pose is not whether a piece of writing constituted a published, redacted book but rather what forms did writing take, what evidence do we have of these forms in works that do survive and how might ideas about writing itself have contributed to the evolution of the tradition as it survives – including the loss and oblivion of many of its layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari was working with bounteous written materials – including, prominently, Quranic exegesis, historiography and Hadith – and these materials took many different forms. Many of them represented second- and third-generation offshoots of earlier writings, bundled together, as, for example, in the case of al-Tabari’s access to al-Madaʾini’s (d. ca. 224/839 or 228/842–3) historical material, studied by Ilkka Lindstedt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important question concerns the extent to which the situation in al-Tabari’s lifetime resembles that in later eras. Our data points to continuities in practice across the third/ninth century and indeed beyond, with later scholars citing al-Tabari personally, rather than his books, surprisingly often. The Arabic book thus seems to show continued reliance on earlier forms of written transmission, including those supported by aurality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the advancement of the field, we should seek to discern such continuities in writerly practice in later periods, in which writers relied on notes and blends of writing and aurality (as described, for example, by Konrad Hirschler).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This type of blended transmission was clearly critical for Hadith and the disciplines that supported it, but it appears that history writing, and perhaps other genres, too, shared these practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first blog post, we introduce our method; in the second, we present our data. Over the subsequent posts, we then consider each of the above questions as we demonstrate what al-Tabari’s citation practices reveal about the working habits of a major author in the late third/ninth and early fourth/tenth centuries and the shape of the material on which he relied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari uses several terms to denote transmission of information from other people, but only a few of these terms indicate direct, personal contact. The phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;) at the beginning of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (citation chain) are by far the most common markers of such contact. We are most interested in the name that introduces the &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;, representing the transmitter closest to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd told me (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;) that Jarīr said that he was told by Mughira, from al-Musayyib b. Rafiʿ, that Abu Hurayra said: Abraham never lied, except on three occasions…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; with whom al-Tabari implies having had direct contact is Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862). That al-Tabari indeed had direct contact with Muhammad b. Humayd and the other individuals for whom he uses the ‘he told me’ phrases is supported by biographical works that discuss al-Tabari’s life. For example, al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (d. 463/1071) wrote that al-Tabari&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;heard (&lt;em&gt;samiʿa&lt;/em&gt;) Muhammad b. ʿAbd al-Malik b. Abi al-Shawarib, Ishaq b. Abi Israʾil, Ahmad b. Maniʿ al-Baghawi, Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi, Abu Hammam al-Walid b. Shujaʿ, Abu Kurayb Muhammad b. al-ʿAlaʾ, Yaʿqub b. Ibrahim al-Dawraqi, Abu Saʿid al-Ashajja, ʿAmr b. ʿAli, Muhammad b. Bashshar, Muhammad b. al-Muthanna, and a circle comprising many people like them from Iraq, Syria and Egypt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari cites all but one (Abu Saʿid al-Ashajja) of these people in his works using the ‘he told me’ phrases. However, although al-Khaṭīb mentioned only ten names, al-Tabari seems to identify hundreds of direct contacts. Further, al-Khatib may well have been relying on the very same evidence as we are for identifying al-Tabari’s direct informants. But even if he was, it would still be noteworthy that he interpreted the ‘he told me’ phrases in the same way as we do – as indicators of direct contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph 1: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; across al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. Graph designed by Peter Verkinderen and Masoumeh Seydi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frequency of this formula can be represented graphically. In Graph 1, the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; has been broken down into chunks of 1,513 characters – the average number of characters in a set of 300 word tokens in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (all books within the OpenITI corpus are divided into chunks of 300 word tokens, each marked by a numbered ‘milestone’ tag). The graph is thus like a great scroll on which the text is written with 1,513 characters per line. The top of the scroll is the graph’s left edge, and its bottom is the right edge. The location of each &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt; that starts with &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; is marked with a blue dot. Uses of the effectively synonymous expressions &lt;em&gt;akhbaranī&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;akhbaranā&lt;/em&gt; are marked with black dots. The red dots, meanwhile, indicate &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;s beginning with the passive-voice phrase &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;, ‘it is reported from’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of phrases that might point to direct transmission, the formula &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; is by far the most common. Al-Tabari does not use the phrase &lt;em&gt;samiʿtu&lt;/em&gt; (‘I heard’), for example, and the phrases &lt;em&gt;akhbarana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;akhbarani&lt;/em&gt; appear only rarely. Al-Tabari’s use of the passive ‘it is reported from’, which does not reveal his direct informant, is concentrated in the final part of the work, a phenomenon discussed in detail elsewhere.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Graph 2: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph 3: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We describe our data and the way we generated it in much more detail in our next blog post, but the following is a summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We went through each work and extracted &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;s that start with the &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula. The formula occurs 32,115 times across the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s are presented in a table entitled ‘Transmission Chains’ in our data set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The style of writing and citation in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; differs from that in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. Generally speaking, al-Tabari’s more narrative style in the former invokes &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, but often refers back to them in oblique ways. Consequently, &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and other citations appear relatively less frequently in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, as the graphs above show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We extracted the names of transmitters from the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and put each in a separate cell in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;’s row. To identify and separate the names, we relied on a list of transmissive terms, first prepared by R. Kevin Jaques, plus a further list of words, such as ‘by him’ (&lt;em&gt;bi-hi&lt;/em&gt;), that appear in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s but are not part of names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We created a unified list of authorities by normalising variants of each Arabic name to a single Latin-script version and listing the normalised names in a ‘Name Normalisation’ table. We also entered the normalised names into the Transmission Chains table.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We calculated the frequency of the name of each direct informant in each position within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and presented them as a ‘Direct Informants Position Frequencies’ table. This step helped us to diagnose data challenges involving names. Theoretically, these names should only appear in position 1. But that is not the case. For example, cases in which our extraction method failed to distinguish two &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, with the result that the same name occurred in two positions in the putative &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;. Or cases where the same name refers to two different people, only one of whom is a direct informant.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the above table, we created a ‘Direct Informants Overview’ table, which ranks al-Tabari’s direct informants by the frequency of his citation of them. It includes, for each informant, the normalised name, the total number of times the informant’s name appears across al-Tabari’s works, and the number of times it appears in each work. It also contains a cumulative count of citations and the cumulative percentage they represent of the total, which indicates the degree of al-Tabari’s reliance on his top informants. Finally, the table includes the informants’ death dates and the places in which each met al-Tabari according to secondary literature (which is also cited in the table).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we compiled a ‘Texts Name Counts’ table, which shows how many direct informants al-Tabari cites in each of his works and also how many are cited in two or all three of the works. This table is especially important for our final question, concerning the extent to which he relied on a common source base.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We analysed this data alongside text reuse data on overlaps between al-Tabari’s various writings and between his works and other, earlier and later works. Evidence of such alignments was particularly helpful for showing that al-Tabari was working with written materials, sometimes in precise ways but other times quite liberally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project is experimental and unfinished. We are able to obtain a lot of data relatively efficiently, but we know there is further evidence that can be harvested at a later point in time with refinements to our method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Previous Work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data we have examined opens a window on al-Tabari’s participation in a system involving students and teachers, speaking and note-taking, and the storage of material over decades. Our approach aims for the big picture. We want to determine how al-Tabari worked, to get a sense of the scale and likely form of his source base and to judge whether he used a common source base or relied on different direct informants for each of his works. Our overall goal is to expand and add nuance to our current understanding of book history in the third/ninth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ours is a picture of the forest rather than the trees. But our digital effort is part of a long tradition of tracing al-Tabari’s sources (who are often called his ‘teachers’, a blanket term that, we believe, overspecifies the relationship between al-Tabari and many of his direct informants, only some of whom fit the description of this role, whatever respect was owed to them because of their age in al-Tabari’s day). Attempts to identify the people with whom he had direct contact began in the centuries after his death, undertaken, for example, by al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (463/1071), Yaqut al-Hamawi (d. 626/1229), al-Dhahabi (d. 748/1348) and Ibn Hajar al-ʿAsqalani (d. 852/1449). According to Yaqut, al-Tabari wrote about the teachers with whom he studied (&lt;em&gt;samiʿa&lt;/em&gt;) in his &lt;em&gt;Kitab Dhayl al-mudhayyal&lt;/em&gt;. However, this section is not preserved in the ‘skimpy’ selection from the work that survives as &lt;em&gt;Muntakhab min Dhayl al-mudhayyal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The efforts at identification continued into the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, most recently with Ahmad Muhammad Shakir (d. 1958), Franz Rosenthal (d. 2003), Claude Gilliot, ʿAbd Allah b. ʿAbd al-Muhsin al-Turki, Scott Lucas and, most exhaustively, Akram b. Muhammad Athari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would be no forest without trees. We rely especially on Athari’s &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; for our Name Normalisation table. Athari’s work contains 475 numbered entries for names listed first in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. The book runs to more than 800 pages and features entries such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;129. Saʿid b. Numayr. From the tenth [generation]. I did not identify him, nor did I find a biographical entry (&lt;em&gt;tarjama&lt;/em&gt;) on him. Before me, Shaykh [Ahmad Muhammad] Shakir [also] passed over him. In his edition of the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt;, Shaykh [ʿAbdAllah] al-Turki named him, specifying that one of the manuscripts had [the name as] Saʿid b. ʿUmar. But he did not attempt to go further in his entry.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athari includes in his entries, to the best of his ability, the informants’ birth and death dates, the people from and to whom each informant transmitted and information on the informants’ reliability. He also specifies the generation (from the ninth to the eleventh) to which the informant belonged according to a &lt;em&gt;tabaqat&lt;/em&gt; schema, and he cites the sources of his information. It is important to note that he is not claiming to have found 475 &lt;em&gt;shuyukh&lt;/em&gt; for al-Tabari. Rather, his list comprises the ‘surface forms’ of the names that al-Tabari identifies as his sources as they appear in the text, regardless of whether these names can be connected to actual historical persons. The tenor of the above paragraph on Saʿid b. Numayr is common. The last fifty or so of Athari’s entries are on especially problematic surface forms and identities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athari has made considerable efforts to determine the identity of the people named by al-Tabari. Thanks to his investigation, for example, we know that two different names can refer to the same person, or that an apparent reference to a particular individual may in fact denote someone else when the ostensible referent lived before al-Tabari’s time, or that a name appears in the wrong form (such as ‘Yunus b. Sulayman al-Basri’ instead of the correct ‘Yusuf b. Salman al-Basri’). Atharī also notes variations between editions of the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital methods that we currently use cannot identify all of the named persons either, especially in cases in which we know nothing of an individual’s biography. Over these works’ long history, there have been plenty of chances for scribal errors and other changes to obscure identities and mix up the order of names in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a fuller discussion of the data, please read our second blog post, ‘Show Me the Data!’ Otherwise, stay tuned for Post 3, ‘How Many People Did al-Tabari Talk To?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the data set, see https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5533889. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gregor Schoeler, &lt;em&gt;The Genesis of Literature in Islam: From the Aural to the Read&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Shawkat M. Toorawa (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2009), 63. Schoeler’s distinction goes back to his 1985 &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; article, ‘Die Frage der schriftlichen oder mündlichen Überlieferung der Wissenschaften im frühen Islam’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 62 (1985), 201–30. For the phrase ‘actual books’, see his &lt;em&gt;The Oral and the Written in Early Islam&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Uwe Vagelpohl (London: Routledge, 2010). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Letizia Osti and James Weaver, ‘Organizing the Fourth/Tenth Century: Knowledge, Information, Tools’, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Abbasid Studies&lt;/em&gt; 7 (2020), 103–20, at 108. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lindstedt, ‘The Transmission of al-Madāʿinī’s Historical Material to al-Balādhurī and al-Ṭabarī: A Comparison and Analysis of Two &lt;em&gt;Khabar&lt;/em&gt;s’, in Sylvia Akar, Jaakko Hämeen-Anttila and Inka Nokso-Koivisto, eds, &lt;em&gt;Travelling Through Time: Essays in honour of Kaj Öhrnberg&lt;/em&gt; (Helsinki: Finnish Oriental Society, 2013), 41–63 and Lindstedt, ‘Al-Madāʾinī’, &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt;, 3rd ed. In the &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt; article, Lindstedt has also pointed out that in the two surviving works of al-Madāʾinī, ‘every narrative item is preceded by a chain of transmission mentioning his students and his students’ students’. This method of citation ‘arguably signifies that the works were redacted, and perhaps compiled into manuscript form, by students of al-Madāʾinī’. See also Lindstedt, ‘The Life and Deeds of ʿAlī b. Muḥammad al-Madāʾinī’, &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift für Geschichte der arabisch-islamischen Wissenschaften&lt;/em&gt; 20–21 (2012–14), 235–70; Lindstedt, ‘The Role of al-Madāʾinī’s Students in the Transmission of His Material’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 91/2 (2014): 295–340. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Konrad Hirschler, &lt;em&gt;The Written Word in the Medieval Arabic Lands: A Social and Cultural History of Reading Practices&lt;/em&gt; (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2012); Hirschler, &lt;em&gt;A Monument to Medieval Syrian Book Culture: The Library of Ibn ʿAbd al-Hādī&lt;/em&gt; (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2020). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh Baghdad&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, 0463KhatibBaghdadi.TarikhBaghdad.Shamela0000736-ara2.mARkdown, milestone (ms.) 0545. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the more technically minded: To produce this graph we defined regular expression patterns to find the transmissive terms &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;akhbarani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;akhbarana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;. We then searched for the terms in the text of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; to determine the character positions of those terms. We scaled the positions to the x- and y-axes of the graph, which represent the length of the text and the approximate length of the 300–word token chunks, respectively. To identify the beginnings of sections, we searched for the section headers (annotated through OpenITI mARkdown) and marked these with vertical lines. The script for doing this is available at https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5118900. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 89–90. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Akram Athari, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; (Amman and Cairo: n.p., 2005), 258, no. 129. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Bowen Savant</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="mARkdown" /><summary type="html">In a series of eight blog posts, we share some results of experimental work on citations in three works by Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari (d. 310/923). These are his universal history, Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk; his Quran commentary, Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan (Tafsir) and the Tahdhib al-athar, an incomplete work on traditions, arranged according to the last transmitter of the Hadiths and also according to the Prophet’s Companions. All three are important works in their own fields and contain numerous citation chains (isnads). These isnads provide a fascinating and previously untried opportunity for historians to understand his working methods.1 For the data set, see https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5533889. &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-01/sarah_savant/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Token Frequency Counter For OpenITI Texts</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Token Frequency Counter For OpenITI Texts" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts/">&lt;p&gt;One of the participants in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2020/07/24/call-for-participation/&quot;&gt;KITAB user group&lt;/a&gt; asked for an easy way to find out which are the most frequently used words in a text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are quite a lot of online tools that allow you to upload a file (or provide a link to a web page) and will produce a nice table with word counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this specific user group participant works with the largest text in the KITAB corpus, Ibn al-ʿAsakir’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenITI/0575AH/master/data/0571IbnCasakir/0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq/0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq.JK000916-ara1.mARkdown&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which weighs in at about 75 MB in the OpenITI version, and none of the sites I tried out was willing to accept such a large file. Others failed to produce a frequency list even with smaller books, probably because they don’t deal well with Arabic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of other options to create frequency lists from a text, but most involve using a programming language such as Python or R. Since most of our user group participants do not have any background in programming, we thought about using this question as an opportunity to show the user group how to install Python or R and run a simple script to create the frequency list (for example, using the fantastic R stylo library).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even demonstrating something simple like this to people who do not have Python or R installed and are working on different platforms always takes quite some time, time we didn’t have during our user group meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, after getting frustrated with a number of websites that promise to convert a text into a frequency list, I decided to build such an online tool for OpenITI myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was quite straightforward because I could build on work we have done for our &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/openiti/&quot;&gt;OpenITI Python library&lt;/a&gt; and other subprojects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://openiti.github.io/tokenFrequency/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, you upload a text and get a table with token frequency counts in return. You can browse through the table online or download it as a csv file (by clicking ‘Download table as csv file’ at the top of the table) that you can import into a spreadsheet program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An additional advantage of building such a tool yourself is that you can customise it to your own wishes. I added a number of options I would personally find useful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a minimum limit for the number of times a token needs to be in the text for it to be included in the table&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a list of ‘stop words’ – that is, tokens to be excluded from the count&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an option to define what the tool must consider a token. By default, it considers any sequence of Arabic-script characters a token (see below for a full list of these characters). You can also provide your own definition of what characters should be considered a token by providing a regular expression of your own. (Note for those who know about this type of stuff: Javascript’s regular-expression engine is used for the tokenisation, so &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MARKDOWN_HASHa9611d04392ad1acb0cd7642a0e405dfMARKDOWN_HASH&lt;/code&gt; refers only to ASCII word characters.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an option to split off a metadata header, so that words that are not really part of the text are not counted in. By default, the OpenITI metadata header is split off from the main body of the text, but you can also provide a regular expression of your own to split off headers that are delimited in another way.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a really quick build; if you would find more options useful, don’t hesitate to contact me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A cautionary note about tokens&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool extracts ‘tokens’ from the text and counts them. The word ‘token’ is frequently used as a synonym for ‘word’, but they are not exactly the same. A token is nothing more than a sequence of characters, in our case defined by default as an unbroken sequence of Arabic-script characters, bounded on either side by characters that do not belong to that list of characters (there are other ways to define tokens as well). The tool does not try to analyse this sequence of characters as a word with a specific meaning, a specific form of a specific verb or the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the token &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ولكتابه&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;em&gt;wa-li-kitabi-hi&lt;/em&gt;, ‘and for his book’) could be considered four separate words, but the tool considers it one token. The opposite is also true: the name ʿAbd Allah is written in Arabic using two separate tokens (in our definition), ʿAbd and Allah, and both are thus counted separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the plural of &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتاب&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;kitab&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;kutub&lt;/em&gt;, and both are considered (and counted as) separate tokens by the tool, although they are arguably the same word. This problem is compounded with verbs, since Arabic expresses their number, gender, tense and so on using prefixes and suffixes. Each form of the same verb is thus considered a separate token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that if you’re interested in how many times an author used a specific ‘word’ in the text, you may have to sum up a large number of different versions of the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if we want to know how many times Ibn ʿAsakir uses the word &lt;em&gt;kitab&lt;/em&gt; in his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;, we could try to sum up the counts for these tokens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;count&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;token&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3560&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2585&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1805&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1320&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1204&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1111&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;492&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;278&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;276&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;263&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;196&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابيهما&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;108&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;103&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;96&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بالكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ولكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابهما&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;للكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;للكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابة&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبهما&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أفبكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبهن&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتابان&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابان&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;قرأالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتباه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بالكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابى&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتبات&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;قرأكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتابان&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أقرألكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ككتابكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;تصنيفكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بهذاالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابنه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;واكتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فقرأكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ولكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وإنماالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even that approach is not always successful. For example, the word &lt;em&gt;kataba&lt;/em&gt; (‘he wrote’) and the word &lt;em&gt;kutub&lt;/em&gt; (‘books’) are clearly separate words, but they are written in exactly the same way in unvocalised Arabic (&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt;) and are thus considered to be one token, and counted as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to know from the frequency list how often the token &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt; refers to a book and how often to the act of writing. By way of illustration, I have marked in bold the cases in the table where there is uncertainty over whether the verb or the noun is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example also shows another use case for such frequency lists: it shows a number of tokens that are clearly errors in the text, often due to the omission of a space (marked in bold and italics in the table); these all appear only once or twice in the text. Combining such frequency information for all texts in the corpus could give us an idea of what tokens in our texts are likely to be errors and should be flagged as such. We are currently experimenting with the use of such frequency lists of single tokens (and of token bigrams – combinations of two adjacent tokens) extracted from the entire OpenITI corpus for identifying possible OCR mistakes in texts produced by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@openiti/openiti-aocp-9802865a6586&quot;&gt;OCR&lt;/a&gt; pipeline we are setting up to get additional texts into the corpus. More about this in a later blog post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix: list of Unicode characters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the tool considers any sequence of the following unicode characters a token:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ء&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER HAMZA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;آ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH MADDA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH HAMZA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ؤ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER WAW WITH HAMZA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;إ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH HAMZA BELOW&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ئ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER YEH WITH HAMZA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ا&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ب&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER BEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ة&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TEH MARBUTA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ت&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ث&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER THEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ج&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER JEEM&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ح&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER HAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;خ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER KHAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;د&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER DAL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ذ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER THAL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ر&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER REH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ز&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ZAIN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;س&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SEEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ش&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SHEEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ص&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SAD&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ض&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER DAD&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ط&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ظ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ZAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ع&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER AIN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;غ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER GHAIN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ف&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER FEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ق&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER QAF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ك&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER KAF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ل&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER LAM&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;م&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER MEEM&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ن&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER NOON&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ه&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER HEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;و&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER WAW&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ى&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF MAKSURA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ي&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER YEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ً&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC FATHATAN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٌ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC DAMMATAN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٍ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC KASRATAN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;َ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC FATHA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ُ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC DAMMA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ِ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC KASRA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ّ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC SHADDA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ْ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC SUKUN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٰ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SUPERSCRIPT ALEF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ـ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC TATWEEL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٠&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ZERO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;١&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ONE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٢&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT TWO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٣&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT THREE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٤&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FOUR&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٥&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FIVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٦&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SIX&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٧&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٨&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٩&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT NINE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٮ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER DOTLESS BEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٹ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TTEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;پ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER PEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;چ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TCHEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ژ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER JEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ک&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER KEHEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;گ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER GAF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ی&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER FARSI YEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ے&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER YEH BARREE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۱&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ONE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۲&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT TWO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۳&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT THREE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۴&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FOUR&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۵&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FIVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۶&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SIX&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۷&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۸&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۹&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT NINE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۰&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ZERO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Verkinderen</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="viz" /><summary type="html">One of the participants in our KITAB user group asked for an easy way to find out which are the most frequently used words in a text.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Using the Many to Spot the Few</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/d/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using the Many to Spot the Few" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/d</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/d/">&lt;p&gt;At present, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-corpus-metadata.azurewebsites.net/&quot;&gt;OpenITI/KITAB corpus&lt;/a&gt; comprises 10,243 text files, 6,268 of which are unique titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a large, and growing, number of texts makes quality control challenging. But at the same time, it is precisely this large number of texts that can be the basis for quantitative methods of quality control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I would like to briefly explore how we can make use of a large number of annotated lines of poetry for a simple quality check of such lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the texts in the OpenITI/KITAB corpus contain poetic verses. Many of these verses are found in texts that carry the word &lt;em&gt;diwan&lt;/em&gt; in the title; others are not. Some of these verses are annotated and tagged as verses; others are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of where verses are found, if they are annotated according to the OpenITI mARkdown system used by OpenITI/KITAB, the tag %~% is inserted either between two of the hemistichs of a verse or before or after a verse in case there are not two hemistichs (see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://alraqmiyyat.github.io/mARkdown/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; under ‘Verses of poetry’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many instances, the tag is inserted manually in the course of the annotation work carried out by KITAB team members. In the vast majority of cases, however, the tag is inserted automatically by KITAB when new text files are converted to the OpenITI mARkdown format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However the tag %~% has been inserted, the number of lines containing it is substantial, and if we search our corpus for lines containing %~%, we get tens of thousands of results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give a sense of the scale, for the following exploration, I have limited myself to texts attributed to authors whose date of death falls between the years 1 and 799 of the Hijri calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we limit ourselves to texts from within the said chronological window, there are far more than 300,000 lines that contain the tag %~%!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a large number should tell us something rather solid about lines of poetry in our corpus. Not least, it should tell us pretty accurately how long they typically are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The length of each string tagged as a line of poetry in our corpus can easily be determined computationally, and the resulting hundreds of thousands of values indeed give us a relatively good idea of what to expect from verses in terms of length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, outliers are of considerable interest when it comes to flagging strings that seem to be either too long or too short. The many can be used to spot the few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of these outliers are problematic, but the chance that they actually are is more than just a remote one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worthwhile plotting the relevant data to get a better sense and overview of how the lengths of strings which contain the tag %~% are distributed across the OpenITI/KITAB corpus (as has been said, for this exploration, the texts used fall within the chronological window 0001–0799 AH). The following figure shows a distribution in which the x-axis shows the AH death dates and the y-axis the lengths of the strings containing the tag %~%:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two facts are readily palpable: First, the bulk of the strings in our corpus which have been tagged as poetic verses are somewhere between thirty and eighty characters long (which in this exploration also includes non-Arabic characters). Second, not only are there outliers, but many of these outliers seem to accumulate around a few text files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we zoom in on strings whose length is between 80 and 300 characters, this can be seen more clearly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For example, the values eye-catchingly stacked at 0283 AH all belong to the text file containing Ibn al-Rumi’s &lt;em&gt;diwan&lt;/em&gt;. The highest character count value here is 278, which is considerably longer than expected from a line of poetry. Indeed, if we go into the text file and check up on this particular string, there are issues with the text file (see the image below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The reasons some of the strings that contain the tag %~% are too long differ. At the end of the day, it will be up to a human annotator to make a judgement call and fix what caused the problem (should there be any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, already at this point, the data that we can generate from our corpus allows us to identify files with ‘odd’ lines of poetry and directs us to the affected text files relatively efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, from the more than 300,000 lines that contain the tag %~%, fewer than 1,000 are longer than eighty characters, and fewer than 300 exceed 100 characters. The latter are scattered across only about thirty-five texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KITAB will automatically flag these cases in our yml version metadata files.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lorenz Nigst</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="viz" /><summary type="html">At present, the OpenITI/KITAB corpus comprises 10,243 text files, 6,268 of which are unique titles.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From Networks to Named Entities and Back Again: Exploring Isnad Networks</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/c/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Networks to Named Entities and Back Again: Exploring Isnad Networks" /><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/c</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/c/">&lt;p&gt;From Networks to Named Entities and Back Again: Exploring Isnad Networks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2020/02/03/tracking-traditions-identifying-isnads-in-the-openiti-corpus/&quot;&gt;previously written&lt;/a&gt; for the project blog about detecting &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, Arabic citations which give a chain of individuals involved in the transmission of information rather than the single source common in other forms of citation, in the OpenITI corpus using machine learning. In this post, I will focus on one of the problems that arise when trying to analyse &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s computationally and one potential way of solving it: the issue of name ambiguity when trying to discern who is who in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; networks. I also offer an application of these methods to a case study determining the number of direct transmitters of Ibn Saʿd to Ibn ʿAsakir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a quick refresher, in the example &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; below, there are five transmitters involved in the chain, each underlined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;حدثنا &lt;u&gt;أبو داود&lt;/u&gt; قال: حدثنا &lt;u&gt;هشام،&lt;/u&gt; عن &lt;u&gt;قتادة،&lt;/u&gt; عن &lt;u&gt;الحسن&lt;/u&gt; عن &lt;u&gt;سمرة&lt;/u&gt;، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Abu Dawud&lt;/u&gt; told us, saying, ‘&lt;u&gt;Hisham&lt;/u&gt; told us, from &lt;u&gt;Qatada&lt;/u&gt;, from &lt;u&gt;al-Hasan&lt;/u&gt;, from &lt;u&gt;Samura&lt;/u&gt;, that the Prophet, may the peace and blessing of God be on him … (al-Tayalisi, 204 AH)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than just thinking of this &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; as text alone, we can think of it as representing a chain of individuals involved in the transmission of information, or a simple linear network with five nodes. These networks from &lt;em&gt;isnads&lt;/em&gt;, when taken collectively, can be a valuable resource for solving many problems in book history surrounding the sources a particular writer was drawing upon when composing a text. While understanding such a network is something that a reader can do (and indeed does) quite easily while reading a text for a reasonable number of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s at once, working with a collection as large as the number of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s even in just a single text becomes very difficult for a human reader in terms of the effort involved, particularly if the text is long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the common issues involved in understanding &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s is that even within one work, an author will often refer to the same transmitter by a variety of different names. We collected a data set of 2,379 &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s from Ibn ʿAsakir’s sixth/twelfth-century historical work &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;. all involving the third/ninth-century scholar Muhammad b. Saʿd. The data set contains 14,454 names, of which 90% have been manually assigned to the individuals to whom they refer. Our annotation process found that the annotated names refer to forty-four distinct individuals. We found that of the forty-four individuals involved in transmission, around half were referred to by multiple different surface forms of their names, with one individual having as many as twenty-five surface forms, as can be seen in Figure 1 below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: Frequencies of surface form counts for individuals in the Ibn ʿAsakir data set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; data itself is also the source of a potential solution to this issue of name ambiguity, since the context a name appears in can help us determine who the individual is. Consider the following &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; fragments taken from the Ibn ʿAsakir data, with transmitters underlined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أخبرنا أ&lt;u&gt;بو بكر الحاسب&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أنا &lt;u&gt;أبو محمد الشيرازي&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أنا &lt;u&gt;أبو عمر بن حيوية&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أخبرنا &lt;u&gt;أبو بكر الحاسب&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أنا &lt;u&gt;أبو محمد الجوهري&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أنا &lt;u&gt;أبو عمر بن حيوية&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both contain the transmitters Abu Bakr al-Hasib, Abu Muhammad al-Shirazi and Abu ʿUmar b. Hayawayya. One will note that Ibn ʿAsakir used two different names to refer to the second transmitter, Abu Muhammad (al-Shirazi and al-Jawhari). However, the two names are not only internally very similar to each other but also occur in similar contexts, with identical names on either side of the ambiguous name. Thus, if we had a way to represent names that let us account for contextual similarity of potentially ambiguous names, we could try to find groups of similar names that are likely to refer to the same individual. The problem then becomes figuring out how to represent names and how to find clusters of similar names. We will tackle each of those in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For representing the names, it would be useful to have representations that are similar when either the names or their contexts are similar. Helpfully, this property is central to a lot of work in natural language processing focused on learning good contextual representations of text, called word embeddings, which are essentially long vectors which encode the meaning of a word in its context. These can be used to accomplish a wide variety of tasks, which we can take advantage of when trying to represent names. Using one such model, a multilingual English-Arabic BERT model trained on modern Arabic,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as a base, in conjunction with some additional work to improve the model’s ability to understand classical Arabic and how names in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s are constructed, we can represent names using their word embeddings from that model. For multiword names, we can average the embeddings of each word to obtain a representation of the full name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the name representations in hand, we can then turn our attention to clustering them to determine which names refer to the same individual. To that end, we apply the social network analysis tool of community detection. To do this, we first need to construct a network using the collection of name embeddings as nodes. We experiment with two different methods of constructing the network, using different methods for deciding which mentions should be connected to which other mentions. As an aside, it is important to note that since each vector represents a point, we can calculate distances between names using Euclidean distance, which allows us to talk about embeddings as being closer or further away from each other. Additionally, in both cases, the cosine similarity (a measure of the angle between two vectors that ranges from 1 to -1, with higher values denoting greater similarity and perpendicular vectors having 0 similarity) between the two embeddings is used as the weight for any edge added to the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first method is more straightforward, with each embedding being connected to its &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; nearest neighbours, as demonstrated in Figure 2 below with a simple two-dimensional example where &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 2. While this is a sensible starting point, it has the undesirable property of forcing all mentions to be connected to at least &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; neighbours. As such, names that are close to fewer than &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; names will be forced to have at least &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; neighbours in the network regardless of how similar the names in question are. The second method, which we call the surface-form heuristic and demonstrate in Figure 3, takes a more fine-grained approach to remedy this. For each name, we calculate the distance, &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;, from that name to the most-distant identical name and connect it to all names at most that distant in embedding space. That way, more isolated regions of the embedding space can have more sparse networks, rather than being subsumed into a larger cluster with a large number of lower-weight edges. One could add a multiplier, &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;, to look beyond that radius, linking to any mentions within the distance &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; * &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;, but we demonstrate the method with &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; = 1 in Figure 3 below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: A demonstration of the kNN network creation method. Beginning with the fully unconnected points (top left), each name is in turn connected to its two nearest neighbours (as in the top right and bottom left), until the final network (bottom right) is constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image9.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3: A demonstration of the surface-form heuristic network creation method. Beginning with the fully unconnected points (top left, coloured according to their surface forms for ease of understanding), each name is connected to any name at most as distant as the most-distant identical name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the network is constructed, the only remaining step is to detect communities in it. We experiment with both simple label propagation, which uses only the structure of the network to detect communities, largely ignoring the edge weights, and the Leiden algorithm proposed by Traang et al.,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which iteratively refines the communities, starting from a network in which every node is in its own cluster and combining similar clusters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To review, we are trying to assign the names to clusters so that the names that refer to the same individual are all in the same cluster. Evaluating our success at this task is somewhat difficult, as clustering problems like this have many evaluation metrics due to the inherent difficulty of quantifying how good a clustering is. We use several metrics, each with their own advantages and disadvantages. For brevity, we will present only the final scores we use to compare models to each other, which is itself the average of three other metrics. A perfect assignment of names to individuals would receive a score of 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link Method&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Algorithm&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Score&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kNN, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leiden&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.727&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kNN, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;LP&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.591&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Surface form&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leiden&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.790&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Surface form&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;LP&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.790&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: A comparison of different methods of constructing networks from names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Table 1 above, it is clear that the surface form method does significantly better than constructing the network using &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; nearest neighbours, especially when using the more advanced Leiden community detection algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While being able to describe how we solve this process in the abstract is useful, it is perhaps more informative to present a case study in which counting the number of individuals a collection of names refers to solves an actual problem of historical interest. As a case study, we are going to attempt to determine the number of direct transmitters of Ibn Saʿd’s material to Ibn Asakir. In the language of networks, this means that rather than working with the complete data set of all names in all &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, we will consider only the first name in each &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;. In addition to that selection process, we set aside half of the data to select the values of &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; which maximise the scoring metric we use above, and evaluate how well that optimised model performs on the other half of the data. The test set consists of 1,070 names with a total of sixty-three surface forms for twenty-five individuals. The results are shown in Table 2 below. For comparison, we also show the results of a naive clustering algorithm in which each surface form is used to create its own cluster and which makes no effort to resolve ambiguity across variation in surface forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Model&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Score&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;# of Transmitters&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Naive clustering&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.741&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kNN, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 135, Leiden&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.661&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kNN, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; = 135, LP&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.618&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Surface form, &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; =1.15, Leiden&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.791&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Surface form, &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; = 1.05, LP&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;.779&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 2: Results of clustering first names in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s to count the number of direct transmitters to Ibn ʿAsakir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these results, it is clear that the kNN models tend to vastly over-aggregate the names, resulting in too few clusters, while the reverse problem occurs with the surface-form heuristic, albeit to a lesser degree. In other words, the kNN models claim there are fewer transmitters than there actually are, while the surface form–based model does the reverse and finds too many transmitters. The latter method does, however, outperform the naive method regardless of the choice of community detection algorithm, which implies that these results on new data would serve as a good starting point for human disambiguation rather than starting from scratch as was done to create this data in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with my earlier work on identifying &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, this research would not be possible without close collaboration with other members of the KITAB team. In particular, much of the work to create labelled data for this research was done by Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lan, W., Chen, Y., Xu, W., &amp;amp; Ritter, A. (2020). “An Empirical Study of Pre-trained Transformers for Arabic Information Extraction.” In &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of The 2020 Conference on Empirical Methods on Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Traag, V.A., Waltman, L. and van Eck, N.J. “From Louvain to Leiden: guaranteeing well-connected communities.” &lt;em&gt;Sci Rep&lt;/em&gt; 9, 5233 (2019). &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-41695-z&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-41695-z&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ryan Muther</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="machine-learning" /><category term="citation" /><category term="book-history" /><summary type="html">From Networks to Named Entities and Back Again: Exploring Isnad Networks</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-05-31//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Digital Humanities Be Informed by Bioinformatics? Visualising Passim Data for Multiple-Book Relationships</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/a/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Digital Humanities Be Informed by Bioinformatics? Visualising Passim Data for Multiple-Book Relationships" /><published>2021-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/a</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/a/">&lt;p&gt;As KITAB’s research has shown, passim is an incredibly powerful tool for answering a variety of questions about book history and history in general. The algorithm produces a huge amount of data, which we can utilise in our research in many ways. At present, we typically investigate text reuse in the corpus at the level of relationships between pairs of books. That is, we look at statistics that tell us what percentage of one book is reused in another and we visualise alignments between two books. This approach is great for understanding how two books are related, but once we start comparing multiple books these approaches become quite cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To note a couple of examples: What if we wanted to investigate how one particular book was disseminated across tens or even hundreds of later works? Or what if we wanted to know about how one particular unit of information (perhaps a narrative about a major event) circulated throughout our corpus? To help deal with these kinds of questions the team has been developing new applications for understanding multiple-book relationships. In this blog post, I will take the opportunity to introduce some of the applications under development. To do so, however, requires a short tangent on bioinformatics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computational analysis of text reuse has developed and advanced alongside that of genomics. This is a fact noted explicitly by David Smith, when he acknowledges that passim utilises the Smith-Waterman alignment algorithm, which is also used in the analysis of genes.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Text reuse and genetics are both concerned with problems in sequencing. Put simply, when biologists wish to analyse genes, they convert genetic material into a sequence of letters (A, C, G, T), each of which represents a chemical nucleotide base (adenine, cytosine, guanine, thymine). Three-letter words termed ‘codons’ specify the amino acids that are used by the body to build proteins.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There are also ‘stop codons’ that mark the end of the sequence. Similarities in sequences of letters between parts of a chromosome or with other chromosomes, or even similarities between the genomes of different animals, might indicate (for example) similar biological functionality. In short, important biological questions can be resolved by identifying similar sequences of letters, and alignment algorithms such as Smith-Waterman are used to undertake this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computational processes used to identify genetic alignments and textual alignments are, therefore, shared. It is natural, then, that we should look to the field of genomics for inspiration when thinking about and visualising text reuse, too. We could, for example, think of books as analogous to genomes and chapters or volumes as analogous to chromosomes. Just as biologists annotate particular parts of DNA that correspond to a particular biological function and then look for alignments in other, unexplored parts of DNA, we might annotate part of a text (for example, information corresponding to a particular topic) and look for alignments in other texts. Therefore, to explore text reuse data, we do not need to necessarily build applications from scratch. Whole suites of applications have already been developed to aid biologists in reading and annotating genetic alignments. Although not all of these tools are immediately useful for the study of text reuse, there are parts that we could adapt, particularly for comparing relationships between multiple books.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team’s first foray into visualising relationships between multiple books uses Microsoft’s Power BI and was developed to investigate the multiple texts used in one book, al-Nuwayri’s &lt;em&gt;Nihayat al-arab&lt;/em&gt;, in a collaboration between Sohail Merchant and Sarah Savant. In particular, Sarah was interested in prising apart overlapping sources. For multiple milestones – that is, the 300-word chunks into which we divide our texts – al-Nuwayri’s text aligns with al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and Ibn al-Athir’s &lt;em&gt;Kamil&lt;/em&gt;. As Ibn al-Athir also reused al-Tabari’s text, it is necessary to separate his quotations of the text from al-Nuwayri’s. To investigate these questions, the application gives a scatter plot with the milestones of the main text (in this case the &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt;) on the x axis. We then plot onto the graph a dot for every case in which passim found text reuse for a milestone on the x-axis, giving the number of words matched on the y-axis. For example, if milestone 2711 in the &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; had text reuse with al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; with eighty-four words matched between the two milestones, then a dot would be plotted for that text at location 2711 on the x-axis and at 84 words on the y-axis. Filters allow the user to set thresholds for how closely the milestones should align (by number of words matched and percentage of alignment matched). It is also possible to filter by author or title to explore how particular books are reused in comparison to others. For an example, see Figure 1 below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: Al-Nuwayri’s &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; as shown in the Power BI application, filtered to show only al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (in orange) and Ibn al-Athir’s &lt;em&gt;Kamil&lt;/em&gt; (in blue). One can clearly see a few cases in which the &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; aligns uniquely with the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. However, in many cases in which a milestone is shared by both the &lt;em&gt;Kamil&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, more words match with the former, suggesting that the &lt;em&gt;Kamil&lt;/em&gt; is being used in preference to the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: The Power BI application using the same filters as in Figure 1, but focusing only on milestones 2700–20 of the &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt;. Notice that some milestones have more than one alignment with al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. This might indicate that al-Nuwayri has amalgamated material from two different parts of al-Tabari’s text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application effectively allows one to explore the ‘DNA’ of one book and to see how it is made up of reused segments of other, earlier books.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The app can also be used to explore questions of dissemination by investigating how parts of a work are reused in the centuries after the author’s death. The team members are now collectively experimenting with a series of apps with different books on the x-axis on the basis of this al-Nuwayri prototype, and we hope to iteratively develop a template app that can then be adapted by researchers to address their own research questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application described above is great for investigating how one book is constructed or disseminated. It does not, however, provide any information about how the reusers of a text are themselves organising the reused text. At present we use a book-to-book visualisation that shows the reuse of milestones between a book pair, as shown in Figure 3 (this visualisation can be seen in many KITAB blog posts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3: Al-Nuwayri’s &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; (on the top) compared with Ibn al-Athir’s &lt;em&gt;Kamil&lt;/em&gt; (on the bottom) in the KITAB pairwise visualisation. Notice how this visualisation, unlike the Power BI app, allows us to compare the locations of reused milestones in the two texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be immensely powerful to be able to take a similar approach to relationships among multiple books. Fortunately, researchers in genetics have already developed a solution for visualising these kinds of alignments (in the field, this kind of comparative practice is called synteny). As noted above, biologists are interested in tracing alignments of sequences between chromosomes and species. One popular approach is to use a circular representation (sometimes called Circos&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;), a donut-shaped visualisation in which the outer ring is broken into segments representing individual chromosomes or genomes and lines (chords) are drawn between segments of the outer ring to represent alignments. If one replaces the chromosome alignment data with book alignments, the result is a visualisation of multiple books that takes account of the location of reuse in all of the compared texts. An example is given in Figures 4 and 5, created using the bioinformatics visualisation library Dash Bio in Python.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 4: A Dash Bio Circos diagram showing text reuse between al-Nuwayri’s &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; and three chronicles (Ibn al-Jawzi’s &lt;em&gt;Muntazam&lt;/em&gt;, Ibn al-Athir’s &lt;em&gt;Kamil&lt;/em&gt; and Sibt Ibn al-Jawzi’s &lt;em&gt;Mirʾat al-zaman&lt;/em&gt;). On each segment of the ring, 0 represents the start of the work, that is, word 0. Chords represent reuse (using the aggregated data set) between all of the chosen texts, with line thickness corresponding to the size of the reuse instance. The green bars on the outside show the parts of the compared texts that are reusing al-Nuwayri’s &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; (the user’s chosen primary text). One can clearly see that all of the text is reused in more or less the same order – that is, following a chronological schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the quantity of reuse between the texts (in particular, the large amount of text shared between Ibn al-Jawzi and Sibt Ibn al-Jawzi), the exact relationships of the three chronicles with al-Nuwayri’s &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; are difficult to distinguish in Figure 4. For this reason, we have added the ability to show only chords between the primary text and the other selected texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 5: A Circos visualisation comparing the same selection of books as in Figure 4 but displaying chords only for reuse between al-Nuwayri’s &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; (the user’s chosen primary text) and the other selected texts. In this case, one can more easily see that the &lt;em&gt;Nihaya&lt;/em&gt; shares text most heavily with the &lt;em&gt;Kamil&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This circular representation of the data allows for significant customisation. One can colour individual chords to represent different types of data. It is also possible to add other data ‘tracks’ to the visualisation to show different types – bars on the outside of the circle or line graphs on the inside. We will be experimenting with different approaches and hope to share more soon. For the moment, I hope I have shown the importance of thinking across fields and learning from other approaches. Such an approach will help us avoid reinventing the wheel (or, in this case, circos).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a good explanation, see David A. Smith, Ryan Cordell and Abigail Mullen, ‘Computational Methods for Uncovering Reprinted Texts in Antebellum Newspapers’, &lt;em&gt;American Literary History&lt;/em&gt; 27/3 (2015), &lt;a href=&quot;https://viraltexts.org/2015/05/22/computational-methods-for-uncovering-reprinted-texts-in-antebellum-newspapers/&quot;&gt;https://viraltexts.org/2015/05/22/computational-methods-for-uncovering-reprinted-texts-in-antebellum-newspapers/&lt;/a&gt;. This paper references Dan Gusfield, &lt;em&gt;Algorithms on Strings, Trees, and Sequences: Computer Science and Computational Biology&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge, 1997), which helpfully compares alignment in genomics with other ‘string’ problems in computer science (for the non-computer scientist, the latter is particularly dense and perhaps not that helpful). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a more in-depth explanation and diagram, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/genetics-glossary/Genetic-Code&quot;&gt;https://www.genome.gov/genetics-glossary/Genetic-Code&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a helpful guide to tools for visualising genomics, see Cydney B. Nielsen, Michael Cantor, Inna Dubchak, David Gordon and Ting Wang, ‘Visualizing Genomes: Techniques and Challenges’, &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods Supplement&lt;/em&gt; 7/3 (2010), esp. 7–9. A trawl of the literature indicates that the available tools do not seem to have changed significantly since the date of this publication. See also Pal Subhajit, Sudip Mondal, Gourab Das, Sunirmal Khatua and Zhumur Ghosh, ‘Big Data in Biology: The Hope and Present-Day Challenges in It’, &lt;em&gt;Gene Reports&lt;/em&gt; 21 (2020). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The comparison to DNA is not mine, but Sarah Savant’s. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Named after a popular variant; see Circos.ca. Perhaps the most powerful variant of this visualisation is MizBee, but this application cannot presently be easily adapted for non-genomic applications. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.utah.edu/~miriah/mizbee/Overview.html&quot;&gt;http://www.cs.utah.edu/~miriah/mizbee/Overview.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For more information on the functions and code, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://dash.plotly.com/dash-bio/circos&quot;&gt;https://dash.plotly.com/dash-bio/circos&lt;/a&gt;. When the application has been finalised, we will publish our customised version of the code on GitHub. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mathew Barber</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="viz" /><category term="text-reuse" /><summary type="html">As KITAB’s research has shown, passim is an incredibly powerful tool for answering a variety of questions about book history and history in general. The algorithm produces a huge amount of data, which we can utilise in our research in many ways. At present, we typically investigate text reuse in the corpus at the level of relationships between pairs of books. That is, we look at statistics that tell us what percentage of one book is reused in another and we visualise alignments between two books. This approach is great for understanding how two books are related, but once we start comparing multiple books these approaches become quite cumbersome.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29-2//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">First Five Hundred Years of the Arabic Book: The Native Origin of the Authors</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/b/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Five Hundred Years of the Arabic Book: The Native Origin of the Authors" /><published>2021-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/b</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/b/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quantitative and macroanalytic approaches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we know about the authors of the earliest Arabic books in terms of their native origins and linguistic and cultural backgrounds? Were the majority of them Arabic-speaking Muslims from imperial capitals, or non-Arab converts or even non-Muslims? Could this information be useful in tracing the flow and formation of ideas and culture? To answer these questions computationally, one must begin with creating a corpus of texts – in this case the OpenITI – including robust metadata for the texts and their authors. In this blog post, I will discuss the question of the native origins of scholars and authors of early Islamicate society based on a subcorpus of the OpenITI, which includes all the texts in the corpus written within the first five centuries of Islam, ending in 505/1111, al-Ghazali’s death date. More generally, I hope to show how a combination of quantitative and macroanalytic approaches can be useful for the study of premodern Arabic texts and the history of the Arabic book and its authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usefulness of computer-assisted ‘distant reading’ and analysis has been convincingly defended by literary historians including, recently, Franco Moretti and Matthew L. Jockers, who in turn drew inspiration from the fields of economics, geography and the natural sciences.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Computational methods range from the study of metadata – a set of information about the books and authors in the corpus, the lowest hanging fruits – to more complex text-level analysis. These methods were also adopted and further developed within our own field of Islamic history by Maxim Romanov, as exemplified in his study of al-Dhahabi’s (d. 748/1348) &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alraqmiyyat.github.io/2013/11-02.html&quot;&gt;Taʾrikh al-Islam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and Ismaʿil Pasha al-Baghdadi’s (d. 1338/1919) &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/693970&quot;&gt;Hadiyat al-ʿarifin&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; which offer relatively structured data on premodern authors and their output, reaching tens of thousands of entries (over 30, 000 biographies in &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-Islam&lt;/em&gt; and 40,000 titles in &lt;em&gt;Hadiyat al-ʿarifin&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier generations of Islamicists were, of course, well aware of the potential of quantitative methods for the study of biographical dictionaries. But whereas earlier attempts were typically limited, not least because of the enormous labour involved in data collection, computational reading of biographical dictionaries enables modern scholars to analyse all biographical dictionaries available in machine-readable format by, for instance, analysing the descriptive names (&lt;em&gt;nisba&lt;/em&gt;s) more efficiently or mapping their regional affiliations and travels through the automatic tagging of toponymics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted, a computational study of a modern bibliographical dictionary, the &lt;em&gt;Hadiyat al-ʿarifin,&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/693970&quot;&gt;Maxim Romanov&lt;/a&gt; has already addressed the question of cultural production in the Islamic world up to the early modern period. By focusing on a much smaller sample from the OpenITI corpus, books authored during the first five centuries, I hoped to get an idea about the geographical distribution of the historical texts in Arabic through an analysis of the metadata, corpus statistics and text reuse data produced by the KITAB project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the OpenITI corpus did not have any information about the geographical provenance of its authors and books beyond &lt;em&gt;nisba&lt;/em&gt;s, a part of Arabic personal names that often contains information about a person’s belonging&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; To create metadata I combined manual annotation with automatic attribution of birthplaces based on the authors’ &lt;em&gt;nisba&lt;/em&gt;s&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; But &lt;em&gt;nisba&lt;/em&gt;s, however informative, may not always accurately represent an individual’s cultural background. A Persian client of an Arab tribe may adopt its tribal &lt;em&gt;nisba&lt;/em&gt; without even learning how to speak Arabic, or may keep and pass his Persian family name to his fully Arabised descendants who may settle elsewhere in the world. Likewise, geographic &lt;em&gt;nisba&lt;/em&gt;s are also commonly adopted after immigrating to a new place. With these cautions, and with the aim of understanding the present corpus better, I have manually checked reliable reference works and created author birthplace metadata (regions and cities of birth) for most books in the OpenITI corpus (October 2020 release) and for all of the authors who lived in the first five centuries, with the exception of a small number of anonymous texts and translations from Greek. Eventually, the corpus will include accurate geographical data for the places of birth, death, residence, study and travel for all authors in the corpus, which will allow us to create more informative networks and to map cultural and demographic shifts over periods. At this stage, identifying authors’ birthplaces was prioritised as the most stable indicator of a person’s cultural background, for even though both birth and death can happen at a place of temporary residence, birth presumes stronger socioeconomic and thus cultural ties to a place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, al-Tabari, the ʿAbbasid-era polymath, who studied in Iran, Iraq, Hijaz, Syria and Egypt and then spent half a century in Baghdad, a city with which he is rightly associated. Nonetheless, it is undeniable that his first sense of historical time (which evolved over time) must have been provided by the Iranian world, especially his birthplace, Tabaristan – the town of Amul in the region of Daylam, where he grew up, from where he was supported by his family, and which he visited at least twice – and Rayy, where he studied. Likewise, his native origin may have contributed to suspicions of his Shiʿi leanings, as various forms of Shiʿism, especially Zaydism, dominated the Caspian region. In the same way, all other historians that followed him also demonstrate regional perspectives. The crucial disclaimer that I would like to make, however, is that at this stage my priority is to prepare the data, not to interpret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A note on the geographical division&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geographical division of the Islamic world that I have adopted comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://althurayya.github.io/#home&quot;&gt;al-Thurayya Gazetteer&lt;/a&gt; (Maxim Romanov and Masoumeh Seydi),&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which follows Georgette Cornu’s (1985) &lt;em&gt;Atlas du&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;monde arabo-islamique&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which in turn is based on third–fourth/tenth–eleventh-century Muslim geographical works&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; In most cases, the classical division of regions is useful. When necessary, several regions can be united into one regional cluster. For instance, for some analyses I have merged Khurasan, Ma Waraʾ al-Nahr and Sijistan into one ‘Greater Khurasan’ cluster. This grouping reflects the integration of these three regions following the Arab conquests and the greater cultural connectivity facilitated under the Tahirid, Saffarid, Samanid and Ghaznavid dynasties. Nonetheless, both historical sources (e.g. Ibn Qutayba) and modern studies stress the ambiguity of the boundaries of Khurasan, which could denote much of the territory to the east of Rayy or Hamadhan when viewed from the Sasanian or ʿAbbasid capital in Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I began by creating birthplace metadata (town and region of birth) for the authors in the OpenITI corpus. Currently, native origin has been assigned for all the authors who lived before 505/1111, in most cases down to their town of birth, and this information is now available through our &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-corpus-metadata.azurewebsites.net/&quot;&gt;Corpus Metadata App&lt;/a&gt;. Other KITAB team members are working towards completing the metadata for all texts in the corpus. The subcorpus of texts from the first five centuries contains 1,947 OpenITI texts. This is far from including all the surviving Arabic books from this period. The digital corpus still represents only a fraction of the published and unpublished materials available to modern scholars of Islam. The good news is that the corpus is expanding rapidly, and the new &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2021/02/12/openiti-release-2021-1-4/&quot;&gt;OpenITI release (2021.1.4)&lt;/a&gt; already includes 458 more texts for the early period up to 505/1111 (out of 1,029 new texts for all periods) compared to the previous release, four months earlier in October 2020, that was the basis of my work. The metadata will be updated periodically to reflect these additions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introducing the First Five Centuries Power BI app&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After creating the metadata, I created a Power BI application to explore the regional distribution of authors in the OpenITI. The app relies on the analysis and visualisation tools offered by MS Power BI. Although the app is still being developed, it can already be used for the purpose of exploring the data. Importantly, as discussed above, the present iteration reflects only the authors’ regions of birth. You can access the App below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;373.5&quot; src=&quot;https://app.powerbi.com/view?r=eyJrIjoiYmY0OTU4YTMtYWE1MC00MzI1LThmN2EtN2JiNjAxNmZjZDE4IiwidCI6Ijk1ZjZmYjYyLWI1YzUtNDkwNC04NTZjLTJlYTNiNGNjZTA4MyJ9&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to use the app:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has seven pages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stats:&lt;/strong&gt; an interactive overview of the subcorpus, its size in terms of word count and text reuse according to authors’ native origins. It also visualises the distribution of texts and authors by native regions over the first five centuries. There are sliders for adjusting the time periods according to the Islamic and Gregorian calendars. This feature is repeated on other pages, too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map&lt;/strong&gt;: an interactive map that will be more informative when more geographical metadata is added. On this page, books can be filtered by word count and AH and CE years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rise of Books:&lt;/strong&gt; a diachronic visualisation of the corpus’s distribution by the authors’ native origin and book size (word count). Try using the sliders to filter out shorter works or to select a specific time period.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genre:&lt;/strong&gt; a preliminary attempt to provide insight into the content of the books by region. By selecting regions you can view prominent tags in the word cloud visualisation on the right. This approach has greater potential once tagging and classification systems have been improved. The current OpenITI tags were created on the basis of Carl Brockelmann’s rather broad classification in &lt;em&gt;Geschichte der arabischen Litteratur&lt;/em&gt; (Leiden, 1932–49); in addition, some were introduced by the online digital libraries from which the texts originated or by the individual scholars who added them to the corpus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DeepDive:&lt;/strong&gt; another attempt to visualise the corpus by the regional distribution of prolific scholars in the corpus. You can select one or several regions for comparison during a specific period of time and can filter for extremely long or short works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Word Count:&lt;/strong&gt; a simple grouping of books by region and total word count. Al-Scopus ranking in the bottom right shows the most quoted books. Try the sliders to find most frequently quoted books for each century.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text Reuse:&lt;/strong&gt; text reuse statistics according to the authors’ native regions. Check the Al-Scopus ranking for the top quoted (most reused) authors. The page also includes filters for date and word count and a ranking of authors by reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: Total statistics. Iraq is the birthplace of the most authors, followed by Jazirat al-ʿArab and Khurasan. However, if you include Ma Waraʾ al-Nahr and Sijistan in the Greater Khurasan region, the eastern region is second only to Iraq in the total number of books as well as of authors. It is also worth noting that the majority of the &lt;em&gt;diwan&lt;/em&gt;s – poetry collections – from the first century CE and pre-Islamic times are modern reconstructions. If we discount these, the number of authors from the Jazirat al-ʿArab diminishes significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: DeepDive allows a focus on individual authors and their output within their geographical clusters. This figure tells us that al-Qadi al-Nuʿman was the second most productive author from the Maghreb in the corpus for the first five centuries, slightly behind Ibn Abi Zayd al-Qayrawani, who wins the race with his massive &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Nawadir wa-l-ziyadat.&lt;/em&gt; However, by looking at the works of al-Qadi al-Nuʿman, specialists will notice that fewer than half of his published works are included in the corpus, and this is not to mention books of his that have not reached us, such as the largest Hadith collection of the time, the &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Idah&lt;/em&gt;. Thus we get an immediate quantitative insight into how prolific al-Qadi al-Nuʿman, the chief judge of the Fatimid Empire, was in comparison with his contemporaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3: Text reuse statistics show the proportion of all text reuse across the subcorpus attributable to books from specific regions. Khurasan dominates other regions, including Iraq, in terms of the ranking of its books according to text reuse. It is true that Muslims from all over the Islamic empire had settled in the great cities of Iraq, but according to our criteria here they were counted as Iraqis (Iraq accounts for 33% of authors in the first five centuries corpus). Despite this important early start advantage, during and beyond the first five centuries Iraq lags far behind Khurasan in terms of text reuse by other authors. Ma Waraʾ al-Nahr and al-Andalus are two other regions that can boast disproportionate text reuse despite accounting for fewer texts in the corpus. This is clearly due to the Hadith scholarship that flourished in both regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope these preliminary insights into the regional distribution of early Arabic books will spark some interest and encourage others to contribute to the initiative. The KITAB team values feedback from scholars and students of the Arabic textual heritage and digital humanists. Do get in touch if you have comments or suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franco Moretti, &lt;em&gt;Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for Literary History&lt;/em&gt; (London: Verso, 2007); Moretti, &lt;em&gt;Distant Reading&lt;/em&gt; (London: Verso, 2013); Matthew L. Jockers, &lt;em&gt;Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History&lt;/em&gt; (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2013)&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Maxim Romanov, ‘Algorithmic Analysis of Medieval Arabic Biographical Collections’, &lt;em&gt;Speculum&lt;/em&gt; 92, no. S1 (October 2, 2017), S226–46, doi:10.1086/693970. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Maxim Romanov and Masoumeh Seydi, ‘Al-Ṯurayya, the Gazetteer and the Geospatial Model of the Early Islamic World’, in &lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities 2019 Conference Papers&lt;/em&gt; (9–12 July 2019), Utrecht University, 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.clariah.nl/files/dh2019/boa/0909.html&quot;&gt;clariah.nl/files/dh2019/boa/0909.html&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Georgette Cornu, &lt;em&gt;Atlas du monde arabo-islamique à l’époque classique: IX&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;–X&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; siècles&lt;/em&gt; (Leiden: E. J. Brill, 1985). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Aslisho Qurboniev</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="reg-east" /><category term="book-forms" /><category term="author-practice" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="dispersed-texts" /><category term="scholar-network" /><category term="khurasan" /><category term="iran" /><summary type="html">Quantitative and macroanalytic approaches</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-04-29//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Call for Papers – Arabic Pasts: Histories and Historiographies (Annual Workshop)</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Call-for-Papers-Arabic-Pasts-Histories-and-Historiographies-(Annual-Workshop)/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call for Papers – Arabic Pasts: Histories and Historiographies (Annual Workshop)" /><published>2021-03-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Call-for-Papers-%E2%80%93-Arabic-Pasts--Histories-and-Historiographies-(Annual-Workshop)</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Call-for-Papers-Arabic-Pasts-Histories-and-Historiographies-(Annual-Workshop)/">&lt;p&gt;This annual exploratory and informal workshop offers the opportunity to reflect on history writing in Arabic. We encourage contributions focused on methodologies, research agendas and case studies that investigate history writing in the Middle East and North Africa in any period from the seventh century to the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are interested in papers that consider the practical and conceptual challenges of working on history writing in the region. Papers might explore the following sorts of questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through what practices of writing or otherwise encoding the past, and of remembering and forgetting, have different groups in the Middle East and North Africa viewed their pasts? At different times and places, how have the significant contours, events and actors in their histories been seen? Was the significant past the same for court historians as for literary historians, for bureaucrats as for the military and for Sufis as for Muslim lawyers and traditionists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How did non-Muslims and Muslims, men and women, adherents of different sectarian or juristic traditions, and speakers of different languages within societies that became ‘Islamic’ imagine the shape and meaning of their specific societies’ own pasts and their relation to the universal history of the Islamic community?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How have urban and rural people, workers and peasants and the religiously educated and the technocratic elite developed different ways of writing, remembering or commemorating particular events in, or the broad sweep of, local, national or ‘Islamic’ history?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In what ways do educational institutions, museums, media organisations and proponents of heritage use history writing in Arabic to shape loyalties and senses of belonging in the Middle East, North Africa and Europe?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How can digital methods now enhance or change our understandings of the past? What additional information and perspectives do they offer?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributions are invited from scholars at all career levels, addressing any period and any part of the Middle East and North Africa, broadly defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we anticipate running the workshop from the Aga Khan Centre in London (subject to UK government guidelines on travel), with the possibility of an online component featuring participants who are unable to travel to the UK. As in past years, there is a small budget to provide some travel assistance for scholars outside of London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programme date: &lt;/strong&gt;The workshop will take place on 7 and 8 October 2021. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organisers:&lt;/strong&gt; Arabic Pasts is co-organised by Sarah Bowen Savant (AKU-ISMC), Hugh Kennedy (SOAS, University of London) and James McDougall (University of Oxford).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submission:&lt;/strong&gt; Please submit an abstract of 300 words or less by 19 April to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:ArabicPastsConf@aku.edu&quot;&gt;ArabicPastsConf@aku.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programme venue:&lt;/strong&gt; The Aga Khan Centre in London (subject to UK government guidelines on travel), with the possibility of an online component featuring participants who are unable to travel to the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:ArabicPastsConf@aku.edu&quot;&gt;ArabicPastsConf@aku.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anjum Alam</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="news" /><category term="events" /><summary type="html">This annual exploratory and informal workshop offers the opportunity to reflect on history writing in Arabic. We encourage contributions focused on methodologies, research agendas and case studies that investigate history writing in the Middle East and North Africa in any period from the seventh century to the present.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/kitab/mesa.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/kitab/mesa.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">OpenITI release 2021.1.4</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OpenITI release 2021.1.4" /><published>2021-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021/">&lt;p&gt;The KITAB team has released a new version (2021.1.4) of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI&quot;&gt;OpenITI&lt;/a&gt; corpus at &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/4513723&quot;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;. The release is open access and freely available. It is our fourth release (first release in 2021). You can also access the release through our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release features 10,202 books, including all versions and editions (2,046,728,631 words), representing 6,236 unique books written by 2,582 authors. In the release, 2,506 new identifiers have been added. The new ids reflect either new books, which are assigned a new unique id, or changes to existing ids and corresponding URIs (resulting in new ids). In terms of structural annotation, 180 books have a new status, and of these 73 have a .mARkdown extension, which means they are available in full structural OpenITI mARkdown. This brings to 247 the total number of books in mARkdown. The mARkdown files have been reviewed and vetted by the annotation team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major changes to the URIs as well as statistics on the corpus are given in the release note at the publication &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/4513723&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE/tree/master/release_notes&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;. We have also added a few new fields to the metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cite this version, please use the following (the bibliographical export is also available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3891466&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorenz Nigst, Maxim Romanov, Sarah Bowen Savant, Masoumeh Seydi and Peter Verkinderen, &lt;em&gt;OpenITI: A Machine-Readable Corpus of Islamicate Texts (Version 2021.1.4)&lt;/em&gt; [data set] (February, 2021), Zenodo, http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4513723.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="release" /><category term="news" /><summary type="html">The KITAB team has released a new version (2021.1.4) of the OpenITI corpus at Zenodo. The release is open access and freely available. It is our fourth release (first release in 2021). You can also access the release through our GitHub repository.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/kitab/mesa.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/kitab/mesa.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Diversifying the OpenITI corpus, One Text at a Time</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Diversifying-the-OpenITI-corpus,-One-Text-at-a-Time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diversifying the OpenITI corpus, One Text at a Time" /><published>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Diversifying-the-OpenITI-corpus,-One-Text-at-a-Time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Diversifying-the-OpenITI-corpus,-One-Text-at-a-Time/">&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of texts in the OpenITI corpus were sourced from three major collections of digital texts originally prepared by organisations based in the Middle East (see Peter Verkinderen’s excellent blog post on the largest of them, &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2020/12/03/al-maktaba-al-shamila-a-short-history/&quot;&gt;Shamela&lt;/a&gt;). These collections have proven invaluable to researchers, not least because they have facilitated digital forms of analysis, but they all entailed choices about which textual materials should belong on their platforms and which should not. Shamela, for example, did not originally include any poetry and focused largely on Sunni traditionalism. Another significant omission in each of these collections is the rich corpus of Arabic texts written by and for non-Muslims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it would be naive to think that OpenITI is itself unbiased, we do aim to be as inclusive as possible and try to address several of the issues found in other collections. First, we bring the separate collections together and engage all of them in a continuous dialogue on text reuse. Second, we identify and try to fill gaps in the corpus through digitising texts ourselves or through collaborating with other research teams. This has led to the inclusion of texts digitised by other academic projects in fields that are of only marginal interest to the major text collections. Thanks to the concerted efforts of Peter Verkinderen and Lorenz Nigst, we now have a number of agrarian treatises, Greco-Arabic philosophical materials and texts of ancient wisdom, as well as some materials preserved in the so-called Cairo Geniza. We list all these various collections and individual contributors with their URI identifiers &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/Annotation&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I have also contributed a number of texts I am interested in by using Optical Character Recognition software, typing up manuscript treatises and contacting people who have published texts online. To encourage people to contribute materials they may have to our corpus, I will here briefly describe a small set of texts I have contributed to the OpenITI in this way. If readers of this blog feel inclined to contribute textual materials in exchange for text reuse data, they should get in contact with KITAB team members and we will happily accept their offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-01-21-Diversifying-the-OpenITI-corpus,-One-Text-at-a-Time//media/image1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-01-21-Diversifying-the-OpenITI-corpus,-One-Text-at-a-Time//media/image1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I was researching historical accounts about a Mamluk expedition against the Nusayri-ʿAlawis in the Lebanese Kisrawan region (the rugged mountain terrain north and northeast of Beirut) which took place in 704/1304. To my pleasant surprise, I found a number of Maronite sources that discuss these events. One of these was a type of text I had not encountered before in my readings of Arabic literature: an epic poem in the z&lt;em&gt;ajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; form written by the Maronite bishop Jibraʾil Ibn al-Qilaʿi (d. 921/1516). Ibn al-Qilaʿi had been instrumental in spreading adherence to the Catholic Pope amongst Maronites in the region of present-day Lebanon, thus strengthening the full communion with Rome which the Maronite Church still follows.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The poem is usually referred to as &lt;em&gt;Madiha fi Jabal Lubnan&lt;/em&gt;, and it describes acts of heroic resistance against outsiders by Maronite chiefs from the dawn of time up to the bishop’s own day. It consists of 294 quatrains, of which the first three hemistiches rhyme with each other and the fourth ends on a monorhyme sustained throughout the entire poem. While there are many Arabic poems discussing or commenting on historical events, they do not tend to be narrative in the way an epic poem usually is. Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s work, by contrast, is highly narrative, if not in a linear chronological way. Furthermore, Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s introductory verses express some interesting ideas about time, history and memory which I am hoping to unpack more in further research. Consider, for example, this quatrain, which seems to conceive of an important role for poets in preserving cultural memory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; ما كان يخبر عنه انسان * وكيف العصور بتتغير   *   وفيها العقول بتتحير  *  ولولا توجد في الاسطار  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How the ages change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;while intellects get confused&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;if it weren’t for you finding in the lines of text&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;what informs man about himself&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its relatively short length I decided to digitise this poem by using Google’s OCR engine, which can be used via Google Drive. The added personal benefit is that by post-correcting the digital text I am effectively skim reading it as a whole, familiarising myself with its structure and identifying interesting sections to return to in more detail. Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s text was edited by Bulus Qaraʾli in 1937 as part of his book &lt;em&gt;Hurub al-muqaddamin&lt;/em&gt; (‘The wars of the [Maronite] commanders’), a blend of primary texts and commentary by Qaraʾli on the Maronite community’s vicissitudes in dealing with their surroundings across the ages. Because of this hybrid publication form, digitising this edition posed a number of challenges and obliged me to make some editorial choices. We always record these kinds of decisions in a so-called yml file, a specific format of markup language which we use to record various forms of metadata in a formalised and computer-readable way. We use three forms of such files: one for author metadata (which includes an author’s birth and death date and various geographical locations, as well as personal relationships), one for general book metadata (including, among others, variant titles and relationships to other books) and one for version metadata. Below is an example of my version metadata for Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s &lt;em&gt;Madiha&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00#VERS#CLENGTH##: 20224&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00#VERS#LENGTH###: 4673&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00#VERS#URI######: 0921JibrailIbnQilaci.MadihaFiJabalLubnan.GVDB20200821-ara1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80#VERS#BASED####: http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/784489194&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80#VERS#COLLATED#: http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/784489194&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80#VERS#LINKS####: https://www.noor-book.com/كتاب-حروب-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    المقدمين-1075-1450-pdf-1593183859&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90#VERS#ANNOTATOR: Gowaart Van Den Bossche&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90#VERS#COMMENT##: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;This text was digitised with Google OCR and corrected by Gowaart. I have followed the edition's lack of consistently noting the hamza and using a generic ha instead of ta &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;marbuta&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;. The edition of the text is somewhat complicated. It interlaces the poem included here with a 19th-&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;century anonymous &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mukhtasar&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; (see &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Salibi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;, &quot;Maronite Historians of Medieval Lebanon&quot;, p. 39) as well as a commentary by the editor. For &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OpenITI&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; purposes I felt it was best to separate these three&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;layers, and&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; assign separate URIs to the poem and the &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mukhtasar&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;, while&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;deleting the editorial commentary. I have also deleted the titles, as these seem to be part of the commentary rather than the poem. As a &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;result&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; the pagination looks like the text has gaps, but this is entirely due to my reorganisation of the texts. The poem is a &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; in Lebanese colloquial. This poetic form is in quatrains, as opposed to the&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;usual Arabic two &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hemistiches&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;. Currently &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mARkdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; does not accommodate this form (in which the first three &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hemistiches&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; rhyme with one another, while the last hemistich follows the &lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;endrhyme&lt;/code&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; of each other quatrain in the poem), so I have followed some other editors of other texts by splitting the quatrain into two parts. This way it looks identical to other Arabic poetry, except that the end rhyme only happens every two lines.&lt;/code&gt; 90#VERS#DATE#####: 2020-08-21&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90#VERS#ISSUES###: NO_MAJOR_ISSUES&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See Hamidreza’s blog post for another example of a yml file and some discussion of how it should be used within the &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2020/06/12/tagging-the-structure-of-texts-in-the-openiti-corpus/&quot;&gt;OpenITI annotation process&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having grown interested in Ibn al-Qilaʿi (a more malignant observer might say I fell down a substantial rabbit hole), I did some further research and stumbled upon the Academia page of the Lebanese cleric P. Elie Saade. He has edited a few &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt;s he found in manuscripts across his home country and published them on his page. I contacted him directly to ask whether he would want to contribute his editions to the OpenITI, something he happily agreed to do. Consequently, we were able to add one more poem written by Ibn al-Qilaʿi (a hagiography of the third-century saint Mar Nuhra) to our corpus, as well as a nineteenth-century &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; by a Lebanese priest. Saade had transcribed both of these into Arabic script from the Karshuni (Arabic in Syriac script) originals in which they have been preserved. He has also since then notified me of another &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; he has published which deals with the experience of the First World War in Lebanon. I hope to add this text to the corpus in the near future. You can find the OpenITI versions of the two first texts through the links below. Note the ‘PES + date’ at the end of the URI: this identifies P. Elie Saade as the contributor to the corpus. Note also that in the above-cited yml file the URI bears my initials, GVDB, as I was the one who digitised this text through OCR. In this way we keep track of the diverse origins of text versions in our corpus while harmonising their contents as much as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/0925AH/tree/master/data/0921JibrailIbnQilaci/0921JibrailIbnQilaci.QissatMarNuhra&quot;&gt;0921JibrailIbnQilaci.QissatMarNuhra.PES20201020-ara1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/1350AH/tree/master/data/1337IstifanThani/1337IstifanThani.Zajaliyya&quot;&gt;1337IstifanThani.Zajaliyya.PES20201021-ara1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through such additions our corpus becomes a little more balanced, but these are of course only small steps towards capturing the true diversity of the Arabic written tradition. There is still a lot of work to be done to achieve a more rounded balance in the corpus. Indeed, three new Christian Arabic texts within a corpus of some 5,000 individual texts is but a drop in an Islamic ocean. It will also come as no surprise that neither of these three texts showcases a lot (if any) reuse. The one case of reuse identified by passim for Ibn al-Qilaʿi is from a late nineteenth-century compendium of Christian Arabic texts compiled by the great Jesuit Chaldean Catholic scholar Louis Cheikho (d. 1927), in which a number of verses from the &lt;em&gt;Madiha&lt;/em&gt; are directly quoted. Even fully capturing the relatively minor &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; tradition poses further challenges. Because they are generally seen as of limited literary value (Kamal Salibi called Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s poems ‘dull’) and because of their highly regional character, only very few of these texts have been edited and published. As noted, the majority exist only in manuscripts written in Karshuni, so it requires people fluent in both scripts to properly transcribe and edit them. They are also largely written in colloquial Arabic. This issue of script and language is another aspect we would like our metadata to reflect better, especially as more Geniza materials (much of which are written in Judaeo-Arabic, that is, Arabic written in Hebrew script) will be added to the corpus in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I wanted to highlight more generally is that pooling the various resources of Arabic texts increasingly available online into one harmonised corpus is all well and good, but if we want to really remedy major gaps and issues we also need concerted efforts from scholars to identify gaps in the corpus and to actively curate and contribute materials. Here are a few ways in which you can get involved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you notice that relevant texts/genres/… are missing in our corpus, we can show you how to add these texts yourself (or you can simply notify us that we should include them, especially if you can propose a way to acquire them in digital format).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are a specialist, you could become a curator of texts in your field, identifying gaps, creating lists of texts to be digitised, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inform us about other projects that have digitised texts that may not be in our corpus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photograph used in this blog post was taken by Gowaart in May 2017 in one of the Maronite monasteries in the beautiful Kadisha Valley below Bsharré in North Lebanon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The most comprehensive treatment of Ibn al-Qilaʿi remains K. S. Salibi, &lt;em&gt;Maronite Historians of Medieval Lebanon&lt;/em&gt; (Beirut, 1959). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Gowaart Van Den Bossche</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="book-history" /><category term="reg-syr-arab" /><category term="book-forms" /><summary type="html">The vast majority of texts in the OpenITI corpus were sourced from three major collections of digital texts originally prepared by organisations based in the Middle East (see Peter Verkinderen’s excellent blog post on the largest of them, Shamela). These collections have proven invaluable to researchers, not least because they have facilitated digital forms of analysis, but they all entailed choices about which textual materials should belong on their platforms and which should not. Shamela, for example, did not originally include any poetry and focused largely on Sunni traditionalism. Another significant omission in each of these collections is the rich corpus of Arabic texts written by and for non-Muslims.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-01-21-Diversifying-the-OpenITI-corpus,-One-Text-at-a-Time//media/image1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-01-21-Diversifying-the-OpenITI-corpus,-One-Text-at-a-Time//media/image1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tracing the origins of a historical fragment focused on the Samanids</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Tracing-the-origins-of-a-historical-fragment-focused-on-the-S%C4%81m%C4%81nids/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tracing the origins of a historical fragment focused on the Samanids" /><published>2020-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Tracing-the-origins-of-a-historical-fragment-focused-on-the-S%C4%81m%C4%81nids</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Tracing-the-origins-of-a-historical-fragment-focused-on-the-S%C4%81m%C4%81nids/">&lt;p&gt;At the Arabic Pasts conference this year, Hugh Kennedy and I presented a paper in the panel dedicated to the Invisible East programme, chaired by the programme’s PI Arezou Azad. The paper focused on a fragment from an as-yet-unknown Arabic historical text on the Samanid dynasty of the fourth/tenth century. The fragment is one of the manuscripts from the Bamiyan region of Afghanistan that were recently acquired by the National Library of Israel (the shelfmarks for the bifolios that make up the fragment are Heb. 8333.190=4 and Heb. 8333.191=4). This is among the very few literary texts in Arabic in this corpus; otherwise, it consists mostly of legal documents and letters in Persian. We plan to edit and publish this fragment in full, along with a translation and commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text is written in a book hand typical of the tenth or eleventh century CE, with certain features, most notably its inconsistent number of lines from page to page, that suggest it was a kind of draft. In several places, direct witnesses to the events described are cited, indicating that that the text’s author was not far removed from the events either, in time or space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fragment seems likely to come from a text that is otherwise no longer extant. We illustrated this point through an in-depth look at a passage in the fragment treating the succession dispute that followed the murder of the Samanid amir Ahmad b. Ismaʿil in 301/914 and a comparison with the treatment of these events in the other major sources on the Samanids. The passage in question includes a long speech by the (eventual) Samanid vizier Jayhani, as he exhorts Ahmad’s retinue of slave soldiers to rally behind Ahmad’s young son Nasr b. Ahmad. This Jayhani is also known for his geographical scholarship and for being a bit of a neat freak (relatable in these times). According to Ibn Zafir, writing in the late twelfth or early thirteenth century CE, ‘when he passed a veterinarian treating a dog, he became overwhelmed by disgust and pushed his hand out of his sleeve, keeping it in this position until he reached his home, where he poured pitcher after pitcher of water on it.’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the speech, Jayhani rebukes the men for caring too much about money and not enough about their duties to the son of their murdered lord, but deftly adds that they will also be remunerated very well indeed for their troubles. He tells them they will receive a special bonus, in addition to their regular salaries, when Nasr b. Ahmad formally succeeds his father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the author’s familiarity with the city of Bukhara and his closeness to the events described, it seems possible that what we have comes from the original Arabic text of Narshakhi’s (d. unknown) &lt;em&gt;History of Bukhara&lt;/em&gt;, which otherwise exists only in an abridged Persian translation from 522/1128, but more work is required to say for sure. In any event, we can be fairly sure that the text does not correspond to any known text in Arabic. The KITAB team ran a transcription of the manuscript (made by Kosar Mirrazi) through its text reuse software package and found no matches, which further supports our theory that this text has no surviving precedent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2020-12-11-Tracing-the-origins-of-a-historical-fragment-focused-on-the-Sāmānids//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2020-12-11-Tracing-the-origins-of-a-historical-fragment-focused-on-the-Sāmānids//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A folio from MS Heb. 8333.191=4, housed at the National Library of Israel. The image is from the full catalogue entry, which can be accessed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nli.org.il/en/manuscripts/NNL_ALEPH003924972/NLI&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As translated by Luke Treadwell in ‘The Account of the Samanid Dynasty in Ibn Ẓāfir al-Azdī’s &lt;em&gt;Akhbār al-Duwal al-Munqaṭiʿa&lt;/em&gt;’, &lt;em&gt;Iran&lt;/em&gt; 43 (2005), 135–71, at  156. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Thomas Benfey</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="text-reuse" /><summary type="html">At the Arabic Pasts conference this year, Hugh Kennedy and I presented a paper in the panel dedicated to the Invisible East programme, chaired by the programme’s PI Arezou Azad. The paper focused on a fragment from an as-yet-unknown Arabic historical text on the Samanid dynasty of the fourth/tenth century. The fragment is one of the manuscripts from the Bamiyan region of Afghanistan that were recently acquired by the National Library of Israel (the shelfmarks for the bifolios that make up the fragment are Heb. 8333.190=4 and Heb. 8333.191=4). This is among the very few literary texts in Arabic in this corpus; otherwise, it consists mostly of legal documents and letters in Persian. We plan to edit and publish this fragment in full, along with a translation and commentary.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2020-12-11-Tracing-the-origins-of-a-historical-fragment-focused-on-the-S%C4%81m%C4%81nids//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2020-12-11-Tracing-the-origins-of-a-historical-fragment-focused-on-the-S%C4%81m%C4%81nids//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>