<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-03T10:14:48+00:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">KITAB</title><subtitle>The Website for the KITAB project</subtitle><author><name>KITAB</name></author><entry><title type="html">New KITAB visualizations</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/New-KITAB-visualizations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New KITAB visualizations" /><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/New-KITAB-visualizations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/New-KITAB-visualizations/">&lt;p&gt;Much of our work at KITAB involves comparing books in order to understand their relationships. Our main tool for this is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/methods/text-reuse&quot;&gt;passim&lt;/a&gt; software, which detects passages two texts have in common (here are some of our blogs about passim: &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-7-Text-Reuse/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/a/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/Adventures-in-Alignments-Training-an-Algorithm-to-Recognise-Text-Reuse/&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/A-Tale-of-3-Versions/&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;). passim produces a lot of data about each pair of passages, including where exactly in both books these passages are found, and how many words and characters the shared passage contains in either book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each pair of books, this data is collected in a csv file, which can be loaded into a spreadsheet. In this form, the data is not very human-reader-friendly. In order for us to get an understanding of what all these rows and rows of data mean for the relationship between two books, we use visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common visualization we use to visualize the overall relation between two books, and which is familiar to anyone who has ever read a blog post or attended a lecture on the KITAB project, is what we have started to call our 'scroll' visualization (see Figure 1) - that is scroll in the old-fashioned sense of a rolled-up strip of paper, not the digital-age thing you do with a mouse or on your phone. The team has also been referring to this visualization as the “pairwise visualization”, because it is the visualization we most commonly use to compare pairs of books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: scroll visualization of the text reuse between al-Istakhri’s &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Masalik wa-al-mamalik&lt;/em&gt; (top) and Ibn Hawqal’s &lt;em&gt;Kitab Surat al-ard&lt;/em&gt; (bottom).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how you read this visualization (see Figure 2): imagine that we write out the text of both books we compared on a very large scroll, 300 words per line. We then highlight passages that are in both scrolls in red, and connect the location of the passage in scroll 1 to that in scroll 2 with a yellow line (we considered briefly calling this visualization our 'spaghetti' visualization after these yellow lines). Finally, we zoom out so far that we can only see the highlighted passages and the connecting lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: How to interpret a scroll visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red lines give us an impression of how much of the book is reused in the other book, while the yellow lines help us see whether the common passages occur in the same order in both books. In the example in Figures 1 and 2, the red lines show that much of al-Istakhri’s work is reused in Ibn Hawqal’s, and the absence of red lines in some sections of the book shows that Ibn Hawqal did not reuse some sections but added his own information there. (People who know the books will immediately suspect that the large blank section in the first quarter of Ibn Hawqal’s book must be his description of the Maghrib, which is entirely independent from al-Istakhri’s). Meanwhile, the fact that the yellow lines all run nicely parallel shows us that Ibn Hawqal faithfully followed the structure of al-Istakhri’s book. For examples where this is not the case, see Sarah Savant’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/A-Tale-of-3-Versions/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; on the different versions of Malik’s al-Muwatta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kitab-diffviewer&quot;&gt;KITAB DiffViewer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scroll visualization is very useful for comparing books at a high level. For fine-grained comparisons of the differences and similarities between passages identified by passim as text reuse, we until recently used an online tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diffchecker.com/&quot;&gt;Diffchecker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3: Diffchecker visualization of a passage from Muntajab al-Din’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; (left) and Agha Buzurg Tihrani’s &lt;em&gt;Dhariʿa&lt;/em&gt; (right). Differences are highlighted in darker shade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool highlights words that are different between two passages in a darker shade, but it does not do a very good job with Arabic texts: it does not display right-to-left text correctly, and it cannot deal well with the small differences between tokens caused by prefixes and suffixes. From looking only at the coloured areas, not the text, in the example in Figure 3, we get the impression that there are only two short sections in the passage that are similar in both texts. However, when we look closer at the text, we can see that already the first word is highlighted as different, although it is exactly the same, albeit that the Dhariʿa (the text on the right) adds the suffix &lt;em&gt;-hu&lt;/em&gt; at the end of the word (تصانيف vs تصانيفه). Similarly, the third word in the &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; is identical to the second word in the &lt;em&gt;Dhariʿa&lt;/em&gt;, except for a dot on the last letter (نقص vs نقض).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to blame the tool for this: like many similar tools, it was mostly designed to detect changes in computer code. Such a comparison between two versions of the same code is called a 'diff' in computer speak - hence the tool’s name 'diffchecker'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked into many other online diff tools, hoping to find one that would work better for our texts. Unfortunately, all tools I checked had the same problem. The most promising one seemed to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Cacycle/diff&quot;&gt;wikEd-diff&lt;/a&gt;, a program written to detect and highlight edits in wikipedia articles (see Figure 4). Designed to work with prose written in human languages rather than computer code in mind, it does a better job at catching differences and similarities between two passages of Arabic text, even at a sub-word level. Moreover, it is the only tool I found that can detect blocks of text that were moved rather than added or deleted. Contrary to Diffchecker and other similar tools, however, it displays the two fragments in a single composite (Frankenstein-like) text, with different colours for text that is present only in fragment 1 or fragment 2 (see Figure 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 4: wikEd-diff visualization of the same two passages as Figure 3, generated with the wikEd-diff online demo tool (&lt;a href=&quot;http://cacycle.altervista.org/wikEd-diff-tool.html&quot;&gt;http://cacycle.altervista.org/wikEd-diff-tool.html&lt;/a&gt;). Text that is only in fragment 1 (from Muntajab al-Din’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;) is highlighted in blue, text that is only in fragment 2 (from Agha Buzurg Tihrani’s &lt;em&gt;Dhariʿa&lt;/em&gt;) in orange. Text that is present in both fragments but in a different location is placed where it appears in fragment 2 and highlighted in grey; at its location in fragment 1, an arrow is inserted, and when you hover over the arrow with the mouse, the corresponding text in the other fragment is highlighted in a darker grey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not easy to read: the display looks cluttered and although the tool selected more text as common to both fragments than Diffchecker, the fact that both alternatives are displayed in the same composite text gives the impression there is much more difference than similarity between the two text fragments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After giving up hope for an out-of-the-box solution, I started searching for javascript or Python libraries that can be used for analysing and displaying the difference between two strings of text, and which I could use to build a diff tool for our OpenITI texts myself. Again, there are plenty of those (I tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/diffchecker&quot;&gt;diffchecker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/prettydiff/prettydiff/&quot;&gt;prettydiff&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mergely.com/doc&quot;&gt;mergely&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rtfpessoa/diff2html&quot;&gt;diff2html&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kpdecker/jsdiff&quot;&gt;jsdiff&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/google/diff-match-patch&quot;&gt;diff-match-patch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/liddiard/text-diff&quot;&gt;text-diff&lt;/a&gt;) but almost all of them are focussed on displaying diffs between two versions of the same program code, rather than prose texts in human languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, the best option seemed to be to use the wikEd-diff javascript code to analyse the differences and similarities between the two passages and then to parse and manipulate its html output in order to display both passages in separate fields rather than as one composite text (Figure 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 5: wikEd-diff output, refined and split into two separate texts (colour coding: blue: only in fragment 1; green: only in fragment 2; orange: in both fragments but in different positions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wrote a script to refine the output of the wikEd-diff code to make it handle differences below the word/token level in a better way. Compare, for example, how wikEd-diff marks the first word in the example strings, تصايف / تصانيفه (&lt;em&gt;tasanif / tasanif-hu&lt;/em&gt;), as entirely different (Figure 4), and how the refined output (Figure 5) marks only the suffix &lt;em&gt;-hu&lt;/em&gt; as different. In the appendix, I will go into a bit more technical detail on how this was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result is that the commonalities between the two texts are much clearer with the OpenITI Diff Viewer than with diffchecker or the raw wikEd-diff output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have embedded this code in an online app that is publicly available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/diffViewer/&quot;&gt;https://kitab-project.org/diffViewer/&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image6.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 6: OpenITI Diff Viewer interface after loading two texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app was optimized for use with our OpenITI texts: for example, by default, all OpenITI mARkdown tags (and all punctuation) are stripped away, and all alif-hamza combinations, ta’ marbutas/final ha’s and alif maqsuras/final ya's are normalized. These settings are optional, however, and can be (de)selected in the Options field (see Figure 7).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image7.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image7.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 7: Diff Viewer options&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has more options: the most useful,in my opinion, is that you can divide the output into lines to make it easier to read the passages side by side (Figure 8). It is usually easy enough to read the beginning of an alignment, but after a couple of lines, it becomes hard to follow where you are in the other fragment, especially if there are many additions/deletions on both sides. This option makes sure that after a divergence between both fragments, both start on the same new line from the point onwards where they converge again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image8.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 8: splitting the output into lines for easier reading (compare to Figure 6!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can download the diff as an image file by clicking the ‘Download png’ or ‘Download svg’ buttons. Before downloading the image, you can resize the text fields by dragging the right-most margin of the image, and change the font size in ‘Options’, so that it fits the layout of the publication you want to use it in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, we would also like to provide an option by which you can create a permalink to your diff output, which you can then link to in a publication. This has not yet been implemented, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reuse-heat-map&quot;&gt;Reuse heat map&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, we would sometimes like to be able to visualize all reuse one text has in common with all other texts in the corpus (or a selection).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way I came up with to do this is to use a heat map: a visualization that indicates by the use of colours how intensely each part of a text has been reused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image9.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 9: heat map of the reuse of al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tarikh&lt;/em&gt;. The number of times each character in the text features in a reuse alignment detected by passim is indicated by colours (see the colour scale on the right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, the heat map of text reuse of al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tarikh&lt;/em&gt; (Figure 9). The visualization works in a similar way to the book-to-book scroll visualization (Figure 2): the graph represents a scroll, in which each line represents 300 words. Whereas the book-to-book visualization highlights all passages both books have in common in red, this visualization highlights each character in a colour that reflects the number of times it appears in an alignment with another text in the corpus, as detected by passim: in the example in Figure 9, any sections marked in light yellow feature less than 10 times in a reuse instance, while those marked in dark purple were reused up to 120 times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to see that not all parts of the texts were as intensively reused as others: there is a clear concentration of darker (more reused) passages between (roughly) lines 700 and 1200. We can go back to the text to find out which section is so much more intensively reused than the other sections of the work: each 300-word section that is represented by a line in the scroll is marked in OpenITI texts with a numbered 'milestone' tag within the text (for example, the end of the first 300-word chunk in the text is marked with the tag `ms001`). Using these milestone numbers, we can see the intensively reused section in the heatmap agrees with the section on the life of the Prophet Muḥammad: the section titled &lt;em&gt;al-qawl fi al-sira al-nabawiyya&lt;/em&gt; starts in the milestone 685, while the section on Muḥammad’s death ends in al-Ṭabarī’s text in milestone 1176.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heat maps can also be used to investigate the spread of reuse over time. One useful application is to split the text reuse into reuse of earlier and later works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image10.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 10: text reuse of al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tarikh&lt;/em&gt; in books written by authors who died before and after al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 10 clearly shows that the material al-Tabari used for his &lt;em&gt;Tarikh&lt;/em&gt; is only partially known from older sources in the corpus: especially the sections between the death of the Prophet and the start of the Umayyad period, and the later ʿAbbāsid period are sparsely documented. Of course, this does not mean that al-Ṭabarī uses original material here; rather, that the material he used did not make it into the corpus. Especially interesting in this sense is the tight-knit block of reuse just between lines 4100 and 4200: when we look at where this reuse comes from, we can see that it comes from the only extant part of Ibn Abi Tahir Tayfur’s &lt;em&gt;Kitab Baghdad&lt;/em&gt;. It is therefore very likely that if the rest of that book were extant, passim would detect much more reuse for the Abbasid part of the &lt;em&gt;Tarikh&lt;/em&gt;. Sarah Savant&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has argued for al-Tabari’s heavy reuse of Ibn Abi Tahir’s text (without mentioning the author) based on an analysis of al-Tabari’s citation patterns in the Tarikh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also split up the reuse data of the later sources into smaller periods, to see whether the reuse is more or less evenly spread over time. For example, if we split up the reuse of Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tarikh&lt;/em&gt; in later texts into 200-year periods (Figure 11), we see that the section on the life of Muhammad consistently remains the heaviest reused section, but that the later parts of the work lose their importance after the 10th hijri century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image11.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image11.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 11: Reuse of al-Tabari’s Tarikh in later texts, grouped by 200-year periods&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This visualization is generated using a Python script; the heatmaps it outputs are interactive (you can zoom in, and get a count of the number of times a specific word is reused when you move your mouse over a coloured bar; it could also show the URIs of all texts that reuse those specific words). See an example &lt;a href=&quot;/tabari-heat-map&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming months, we will build a publicly available online app to build such heatmaps, to be released when the KITAB data becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heckel, Paul, ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://documents.scribd.com/docs/10ro9oowpo1h81pgh1as.pdf&quot;&gt;A Technique for Isolating Differences Between Files&lt;/a&gt;’, &lt;em&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/em&gt; 21/4 (1978), 264-268.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savant, Sarah Bowen, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’, forthcoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix&quot;&gt;Appendix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wikEd-diff code is an implementation of an algorithm consisting of six steps, first described by Paul Heckel in his 1978 article ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://documents.scribd.com/docs/10ro9oowpo1h81pgh1as.pdf&quot;&gt;A Technique for Isolating Differences Between Files&lt;/a&gt;’. The algorithm tries to find the most likely steps by which one string (s1) was turned into another string (s2) by three different types of actions: insertion, deletion, moving. The idea is simple: both strings (s1 and s2) are split into tokens, and tokens that appear exactly once in each string are used as anchors. Next, the tokens before and after those anchors are compared in a number of further steps. The end result is that each token in s2 is marked as either common to both strings, or inserted / deleted / moved to another position in s2 as compared to s1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WikEd-diff code outputs a single html string in which the inserted, deleted and moved characters are enclosed in span tags with different classes for each type (see Figure 5):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;inserts: `class=&quot;wikEdDiffInsert&quot;`&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;deletions: `class=&quot;wikEdDiffDelete&quot;`&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;moves: characters in s2 are in a span with `class=&quot;wikEdDiffBlock&quot;`, while the position of these characters in s1 is marked with a placeholder character in a span with class `wikEdDiffMarkRight` or `wikEdDiffMarkLeft` (depending on whether the text was moved to the left or right in s2)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters that both strings have in common are included as plain text (without tags).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image12.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image12.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 12: Simplified and abbreviated extract of the output of the wikEd-diff code. Spans are highlighted in the same colours as in Figure 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote a script that splits this composite html text into two separate html strings (output1 and output2) in order to display them side by side: untagged (shared) text is added to both output strings, `wikEdDiffInsert` and `wikEdDiffBlock` spans only to output2, `wikEdDiffDelete` and `wikEdDiffMarkRight`/`wikEdDiffMarkLeft` spans only to output1 (Figure 13).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image13.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image13.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 13: wikEd-diff output split into two separate texts (blue: only in s1, green: only in s2, orange: in s1 and s2 but in different positions). Generated from the wikEd-diff output in Figure 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works, but I noticed that the output of the wikEd-diff code is not as fine-grained as we’d like: more often than not, it will tag an entire word as insertion/deletion even if the only difference is a prefix or a suffix, or a single character. For example, in the first line of Figures 4, 12 and 13, you can see that like diffchecker, wikEd-diff marks تصايف / تصانيفه (&lt;em&gt;tasanif / tasanif-hu&lt;/em&gt;) as entirely different tokens, although they differ only by one character. The same goes for the words نقص / نقض and التصفح / التصفيح on the same line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 14: wikEd-diff output split into two separate texts (blue: only in s1, green: only in s2, orange: in s1 and s2 but in different positions) and refined using shingled 3-grams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a next step, I wrote my own implementation of (the first five steps) in Heckel’s algorithm in order to finetune the output of the script: each text inside a span is divided into shingled n-grams (default: n = 3 characters; this can be changed under “Options” in the app, see Figure 5), and then these n-grams are used as tokens for Heckel’s algorithm. This significantly improves the output: for example, in the first line of Figure 14, you can see that the refined output correctly identifies the word تصانيف as shared between both strings, with only the suffix &lt;em&gt;-hu&lt;/em&gt; ه tagged as addition in string 2. Similarly, only the last letter in نقص / نقض is tagged as different in both strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’, forthcoming. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Verkinderen</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="viz" /><category term="passim" /><summary type="html">Much of our work at KITAB involves comparing books in order to understand their relationships. Our main tool for this is the passim software, which detects passages two texts have in common (here are some of our blogs about passim: 1, 2, 3, 4). passim produces a lot of data about each pair of passages, including where exactly in both books these passages are found, and how many words and characters the shared passage contains in either book.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-12-03/peter_verkinderen/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Suggestions on Using OpenITI Corpus to Present Enhanced Digital Versions of Large Collections: The Case of al-Dhari‘a Ila Tasanif al-Shi‘a</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Some-Suggestions-on-Using-OpenITI-Corpus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Suggestions on Using OpenITI Corpus to Present Enhanced Digital Versions of Large Collections: The Case of al-Dhari‘a Ila Tasanif al-Shi‘a" /><published>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Some-Suggestions-on-Using-OpenITI-Corpus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Some-Suggestions-on-Using-OpenITI-Corpus/">&lt;p&gt;Tagging the structure of the texts in OpenITI corpus is an important step towards the ultimate goal of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/&quot;&gt;KITAB project&lt;/a&gt;—Studying the Arabic textual tradition using text reuse detection (for a detailed description of the tagging process, see my other blog post &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/Tagging-the-Structure-of-Texts-in-the-OPENITI-Corpus/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). However, its application goes much beyond the aims set for this project. In the first place, it creates a corpus of manually-tagged texts, annotated by human annotators and reviewed by second annotators, to which readers have access, with an interactive space enabling them to suggest corrections for any problem in the tags or in any part of the text itself through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/Annotation/issues&quot;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; reporting mechanism on our GitHub page. Besides, with a touch of creativity, such a corpus developed by spending so much time on preparing each single text can be freely used as a base by specialists who decide to work on specific texts in their area of specialty. In this blog post, I will try to explain how our annotated texts can be used to present enhanced versions of the texts, especially large biographical/bibliographical collections. By enhanced version, I mean a digital (and preferably online) version modified in order to facilitate using the content of the text for readers and also facilitate doing research on the text (or even more broadly on the genre of the text) for specialists. The text I will use here as an example is the famous Shiʿi bibliographical collection &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/1400AH/tree/master/data/1389AghaBuzurgTihrani/1389AghaBuzurgTihrani.DharicaIlaTasanifShica&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a ila tasanif al-shi’a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, the suggestions and methods presented here are by no means limited to this text and can be applied to any other tagged bibliographical/biographical text on our corpus. To show how our tagged texts can be used for this purpose, first I will briefly explain what I, as the annotator, have done on it and will make some preliminary suggestions to improve the quality of the text; then I will show a few possibilities for the corpus which can be helpful for a wider audience interested in the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; is the largest bibliographical collection indexing the Shiʿi written tradition in Arabic and Persian (and occasionally Turkish and Urdu) in 29 printed volumes and around 55000 entries, compiled by &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1573-3912_islam_SIM_7548&quot;&gt;Agha Buzurg al-Tihrani&lt;/a&gt; (1293/1876-1389/1970) in a span of 60 years searching through around 60 libraries in several countries from Iran and Iraq to Syria and Egypt (find the PDF &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/alzariah&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The text has a very clear structure with numbered entries which are the titles of the texts (manuscripts or published) sorted alphabetically according to the first letter. There are also cross-references which are not numbered. So, as the first step, I tagged all the entries as simple entries (### $), and cross-references with an asterisk (### $ *), and then I checked the sequentiality of the numbered entries through a Python script. Hundreds of numbers were typed incorrectly in our digital version, which I corrected manually. Entries that did not have a number or had duplicate numbers in the printed edition, I tagged with a ### $ + (see Figure 1) (however, it is not known whether such numbering problems should be attributed to the original manuscript or to the typists of the printed edition). In an enhanced digital version, the cross-references would be linked to their main entries, and a secondary numbering system could be set up to correct the incorrect numbers in the printed edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Screenshot of the folded text to show only the headers in EditPad Pro: a cross-reference tagged as ### $ * and two duplicate numbers tagged as ### $ +.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The categorisation of the headers should also be modified in an enhanced version. The entries are sorted according to their first alphabetical letter. So, the first-level headers (tagged with one pipe: ### |) are successive alphabetical letters. Occasionally, the author has introduced second-level headers (tagged with two pipes: ### ||) to group texts that have the first word of the title in common, or belong to a specific genre. Since the &lt;a href=&quot;https://alraqmiyyat.github.io/mARkdown/&quot;&gt;OpenITI mARkdown annotation system&lt;/a&gt; does not include closing tags, I used blank second-level headers to mark the end of these sections (Figure 2). Appropriate headers can be added in square brackets for all of such sub-categories to facilitate navigation. The other problem in the categorisation of the headers is that in the fourth volume (and in a very few cases in other volumes), after the first-level alphabetical headers, there is an additional layer of headers based on the second alphabetical letter of the entries, which has made the levelling of the whole text inconsistent (see Figure 3). In an improved version, the text could be made more accessible by extending this secondary level based on the second letter to the navigation of the entire text (in a way that makes clear this is done by the annotator, not by the author). So, the first-level headers will be the first alphabetical letter of the entries; the second-level headers will be the second alphabetical letter of the entries; and the third-level headers will be the genre or the first word of the title of the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Screenshot of the folded text to show only the headers in EditPad Pro: a blank second-level header (### ||) showing the end of the previous second-level section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;: Screenshot of the folded text to show only the headers in EditPad Pro: an additional layer of categorisation applied occasionally in the fourth volume based on the second alphabetical letter of the entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major issue in most large collections that needs to be dealt with is its appendices or supplements, compiled by the original author or by subsequent writers. In this case, the last volume of the text is an appendix compiled by the original author alphabetically indexing the texts he has found after publishing his book. Besides, the text has several supplements compiled by subsequent authors to complement the entries. An enhanced digital version offers the possibility to add links to these supplements. The entries indexed in the author’s appendix and the ones indexed in the supplements could be integrated into the text using abbreviations showing from which text each entry is drawn. I have created a sample in Figure 4 in which ABT-SUP stands for the entries taken from the author’s supplement; MAR stands for the entries taken from a contemporary supplement written by Muhammad Ali al-Rawadati entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://ebookshia.com/books/view/1106/%D8%AA%DA%A9%D9%85%D9%84%D8%A9+%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%B0%D8%B1%DB%8C%D8%B9%D8%A9+%D8%A7%D9%84%DB%8C+%D8%AA%D8%B5%D8%A7%D9%86%DB%8C%D9%81+%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%B4%DB%8C%D8%B9%D8%A9+%28%D8%AC%D9%84%D8%AF+1%29&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Takmilat&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a ila tasanif al-Shi’a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; and MTB stands for the entries taken from another contemporary supplement written by Muhammad al-Tabataba’i al-Bihbahani entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://noorlib.ir/book/view/18065?viewType=pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;al-Shari’a ila istidrak al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from the entries of the supplements, some of the entries indexed in the original text could also be linked to their correct places. The author introduces new texts that should have been mentioned in previous volumes after the phrase ‘قد فاتنا ذكره في محله’. For all such cases, links could be added to the relevant places in previous volumes. I showed one case in the figure with ABT-M which stands for Agha Buzurg al-Tihrani matn. Such an abbreviation system will make a digital version in which the readers have access to all the entries both in the original text and in the supplements in a successive order, while at the same time, the entries belong to each specific text is clearly recognisable, with the ability of adding the entries in newly-found or newly-compiled supplements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt;: A sample integrating three entries from the supplements plus one from the original text placed in its correct position. The first number is the successive number for all entries. The second one which is in parenthesis shows that the number either belongs to the original text, or is added (by a plus sign) from a supplement. The abbreviation and the following PAGE/NO shows the page number and the entry number of the supplement from which the entry is drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;named-entities&quot;&gt;Named Entities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing the text’s indexes (list of the names of people, places, etc.) will be greatly facilitated through this tagging method. Since Arabic keyboards are not uniform and often use different Unicode codes for the same letters, the first step in preparing indexes is to homogenise the letters (this is required since many of the large texts are typed by several typists, or produced by joining sections from different sources). The next step is tagging the names inside the text through a combination of automatic tagging and human annotation (Ideally, tagging the information inside the texts will be part of the project’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://maximromanov.github.io/mARkdown/&quot;&gt;analytical annotation&lt;/a&gt; phase which should be done according to individual researchers’ objectives. However, given the limitations in resources, this may take years). The text in question here, for example, is much more than a bibliographical collection, and in many cases, presents very useful information about the authors of the entries, or sometimes even the scribes of the manuscripts of the entries. Besides, the name of an author may be repeated several times in the text. So, the name of each person should have an in-text link showing in a pop-up window all the other places where that name appears in the text. This would allow the readers to have quick access to all the books written by each author and also his biographical information in case it is available in the text (the indexes that have been prepared for texts, sometimes published separately, can be used as a base here. See an index of names for &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://noorlib.ir/book/view/18064?viewType=pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for example). If the author is well-known, a link to EI2, EI3 or any other modern encyclopedia, or name authority files (like &lt;a href=&quot;http://viaf.org/&quot;&gt;VIAF&lt;/a&gt;) can complement the collection of the links in the pop-up window; otherwise, the links will be a good starting point for collecting information about less well-known authors or even the scribes. Besides, tagging other names in the text will also provide a great opportunity for scholars who will work on different aspects of the text. As an example, in many cases, the author mentions the names of the libraries in which he has found the books he introduces. Tagging the names of the libraries will enable the scholars interested in the history of libraries in Islamic world to reconstruct the lost stock of the libraries to some extent. Furthermore, the entries that have been published up to now can be linked to their respective items in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldcat.org/&quot;&gt;WorldCat&lt;/a&gt; database. This will allow us to have a list of the books that are lost, or are extant but have not been published yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt;: Items need to be tagged for producing a comprehensive index, marked with red rectangles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;text-reuse-data&quot;&gt;Text Reuse Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KITAB team’s text reuse data could enrich an enhanced digital version. The team uses the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dasmiq/passim&quot;&gt;passim&lt;/a&gt; algorithm to compare all texts in the corpus with each other and find instances where a pair of texts have passages in common. This data could be used to find out which parts of the text are drawn from previous texts and which parts are repeated in subsequent texts—a process which not only helps in any research about the text, but also in editing the text or reconstructing its lost sections (see Figure 6). Since large texts are more likely to extensively quote previous sources and be quoted in later sources, running passim on them will most probably bring very helpful results (for a general description of passim see &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/methods/text-reuse&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. There are some other blog posts on our website about it: &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/a/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/Adventures-in-Alignments-Training-an-Algorithm-to-Recognise-Text-Reuse/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/Algorithmic-Reading-of-Shi%CA%BFi-Hadith-Collections-Direct-Borrowing-and-Common-Sources/&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-project.org/On-Commentaries,-Digressions,-Transtextualities,-and-Rabbit-Holes/&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image7.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image7.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 6&lt;/strong&gt;: A list of 25 texts written by authors who died before Agha Buzurg for which passim has detected the most cases of text reuse with &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; on the left, and a list of the texts written by authors who died after Agha Buzurg for which passim has detected one or more cases of text reuse with &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; on the right (the columns on the right side of both lists show the number of instances of text reuse between the text and &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image8.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 7&lt;/strong&gt;: Graphical representation of the sections of &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; that are reused in all the texts on the corpus written by authors who died before and after Agha Buzurg. Darker colours signify more cases of text reuse in that section of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passim can also be run on a pair of texts to find similar passages. Figure 8 is the result of passim on the pair &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; and Muntajab al-Din Ibn Babawayh’s &lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;, another Shiʿi bibliography written in the 6^th^/12^th^ century, showing which parts of &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; are likely to be drawn from this text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image9.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 8&lt;/strong&gt;: A list of the sections of &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; that are taken from Muntajab al-Din’s &lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; based on the milestone IDs of the two texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image10.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 9&lt;/strong&gt;: Graphical representation of the information in Figure 8, showing the distribution of the reused passages of &lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; (on the bottom) in &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; (on the top). As it is evident, the cases of reuse are very sparse in comparison with the texts at the top of the table in Figure 6. However, for a detailed analysis of the text, they could still be of importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finding similar passages in a pair of texts, it will also be possible to observe the differences between them using our text-comparing app &lt;a href=&quot;https://pverkind.github.io/OpenITIdiffViewer/&quot;&gt;OpenITI Diff viewer&lt;/a&gt; (see Figure 10). The app can also be used for a second function. The OpenITI corpus contains different digital versions of the same texts —sometimes different digitisations of the same paper edition, and sometimes of different printed editions. Thus, most folders contain more than one edition of the text (this is not the case about &lt;em&gt;al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; which is a recent compilation most of which was published while the author was still alive). So, the app also enables specialist scholars (those who intend to present a newer edition of the text, for example) to compare different printed editions and easily observe the differences between them. This will save a lot of time and energy that close reading of the texts for comparison would require.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image11.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image11.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 10&lt;/strong&gt;: Using OpenITI Diff viewer app to compare a paragraph in &lt;em&gt;Al-Dhari’a&lt;/em&gt; with the corresponding paragraph detected as a text reuse case in Muntajab al-Din’s &lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; (the fifth case in Figure 8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last of all, let me emphasise again that the issues considered here are the most typical issues that can be enhanced in the digital versions of all large biographical/bibliographical texts. For an enhanced version, almost all such texts have a numbering system that need to be corrected; have categorised headers (usually alphabetical) that should be revised; have some supplements, written either by the original author or by the subsequent authors, that need to be integrated into the text (many of the supplements are also available on our corpus and are ready to be used for this purpose); need indexes and in-text links that are vital for mining the information inside the text (which can be prepared by tagging the necessary items inside the text by specialists); need to be collated with other editions through digital methods; and need to be set against preceding and following texts to discover which parts of their information is abstracted from previous sources and which parts are reproduced in subsequent texts. The tagged texts in OpenITI corpus, although not necessarily aimed at resolving all of the mentioned issues, provide an unequalled facility which paves the way for scholars and specialists in the field to deal with each one of them. Highly ambitious projects might go far beyond this. In this case, for example, it would not be far-fetched for a team of specialist researchers and editors to embark upon performing the same process on other Shiʿi bibliographical collections on the corpus, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/0475AH/tree/master/data/0460ShaykhTusi/0460ShaykhTusi.Fihrist&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Shaykh Tusi (d. 460) or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/0575AH/tree/master/data/0575IbnBabawayh/0575IbnBabawayh.Fihrist&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Muntajab al-Din (d. 575), aiming finally at creating the most comprehensive Shiʿi bibliography by joining all the collections together. The whole point is that the same process can be carried out on any other biographical/bibliographical collection (or set of collections) in the corpus in any given field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hamid Reza Hakimi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="viz" /><category term="markdown" /><category term="corpus" /><summary type="html">Tagging the structure of the texts in OpenITI corpus is an important step towards the ultimate goal of the KITAB project—Studying the Arabic textual tradition using text reuse detection (for a detailed description of the tagging process, see my other blog post here). However, its application goes much beyond the aims set for this project. In the first place, it creates a corpus of manually-tagged texts, annotated by human annotators and reviewed by second annotators, to which readers have access, with an interactive space enabling them to suggest corrections for any problem in the tags or in any part of the text itself through the issues reporting mechanism on our GitHub page. Besides, with a touch of creativity, such a corpus developed by spending so much time on preparing each single text can be freely used as a base by specialists who decide to work on specific texts in their area of specialty. In this blog post, I will try to explain how our annotated texts can be used to present enhanced versions of the texts, especially large biographical/bibliographical collections. By enhanced version, I mean a digital (and preferably online) version modified in order to facilitate using the content of the text for readers and also facilitate doing research on the text (or even more broadly on the genre of the text) for specialists. The text I will use here as an example is the famous Shiʿi bibliographical collection al-Dhari’a ila tasanif al-shi’a. Nevertheless, the suggestions and methods presented here are by no means limited to this text and can be applied to any other tagged bibliographical/biographical text on our corpus. To show how our tagged texts can be used for this purpose, first I will briefly explain what I, as the annotator, have done on it and will make some preliminary suggestions to improve the quality of the text; then I will show a few possibilities for the corpus which can be helpful for a wider audience interested in the text.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-11-22/hamid_reza_hakimi/media/image2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 8: The Afterlife of al-Tabari in Quotations</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-8-The-Afterli/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 8: The Afterlife of al-Tabari in Quotations" /><published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-8--The-Afterli</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-8-The-Afterli/">&lt;p&gt;In this series of blog posts, we have argued for the imperative to rethink writerly culture in ways that allow for a more meaningful exploration of al-Tabari’s (d. 310/923) sources. We have also advanced a more general argument about the nature of writing in the period in which al-Tabari lived. The question that we should be asking is not whether a particular piece of writing constituted a published, redacted book but rather what forms writing took, what evidence we have of these forms in the works that survive, and how ideas about writing itself might have contributed to the evolution of the tradition – including the loss and oblivion of many of its layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have observed that al-Tabari rarely refers to titled works as his sources. Interestingly, Yaqut also fails to mention titles for al-Tabari’s sources in his discussion of his famed predecessor’s sources. Instead, he refers to ‘the book’, &lt;em&gt;kitab&lt;/em&gt;, of so-and-so. For example, Yaqut shares a report noting that al-Tabari failed to use the &lt;em&gt;kitab&lt;/em&gt; of Muhammad b. al-Saʾib al-Kalbi or those of Muqatil b. Sulayman or Muhammad b. ʿUmar al-Waqidi when composing his &lt;em&gt;tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (Yaqut’s source makes the point that al-Tabari did use these books in writing up his &lt;em&gt;taʿrikh&lt;/em&gt;). Yaqut uses the same general terminology – the &lt;em&gt;kitab&lt;/em&gt; of so-and-so – when describing the sources that al-Tabari did use when he wrote about &lt;em&gt;taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;siyar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;akhbar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari’s own writings were recognised early on as important works in their own right. His students copied them, and their titles are recorded in the early biographical works. Yaqut reproduces a comment he says he found in a volume of al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; in the handwriting of al-Tabari’s student Abu Muhammad ʿAbd Allah b. Aḥmad b. Jaʿfar al-Farghani (d. 362/972–3):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear ʿAli b. ʿImran and Ibrahim b. Muhammad, I have given you an &lt;em&gt;ijaza&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;ajaztu la-ka&lt;/em&gt;) for the following books which I heard from Abu Jaʿfar al-Tabari (God have mercy on him!): the book on &lt;em&gt;tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, called &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; and the book, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa’l-anbiyāʾ wa-l-muluk wa-l-khulafaʾ&lt;/em&gt;, both of which I heard (&lt;em&gt;samiʿtu&lt;/em&gt;); for &lt;em&gt;al-Qaṭʿayn min al-Kitab&lt;/em&gt;, which I did not hear, but which I obtained through an &lt;em&gt;ijaza&lt;/em&gt;; the book treating the dating of transmitters (&lt;em&gt;rijal&lt;/em&gt;), called &lt;em&gt;Dhayl al-mudhayyal &lt;/em&gt;…&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Farghani is remembered as a major transmitter of al-Tabari’s works. He wrote a continuation of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, and his son Abu Mansur Ahmad b. ʿAbd Allah in turn wrote a continuation of the continuation.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the comment quoted by Yaqut, he tells two people – perhaps his own students – that he has received al-Tabari’s two major works in person through dictation. The &lt;em&gt;al-Qatʿayn min al-Kitab&lt;/em&gt; was transmitted through a mechanism that granted him permission to transmit the work without having heard it read aloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;al-qaṭʿayn&lt;/em&gt; is a curious one. Yaqut subsequently quotes Abu al-Hasan b. al-Mughallis who describes the contents of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, and says the term &lt;em&gt;al-qatʿayn&lt;/em&gt; refers to the &lt;em&gt;qatʿ&lt;/em&gt; of the Umayyads and the &lt;em&gt;qatʿ&lt;/em&gt; of the ʿAbbasids.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Ibn al-Nadim (d. 385/995) also refers to &lt;em&gt;qatʿan&lt;/em&gt;, when describing the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. He says that al-Tabari added the &lt;em&gt;qatʿan&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; as well as other contents that ran up to the year 302.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This may well suggest an original conception of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; that ended prior to the Umayyad period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For al-Tabari, and also his immediate readers, the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; therefore might have been viewed not as a continuous presentation of history, but rather as discrete segments added together and comprising it. Readers would know to read the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; differently depending on where in the narrative they landed. Segments on the Prophet’s life would be read differently than those on the Umayyads not just because of the topic, but also because of the manner of assembly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What authorized breaking books up? A significant factor would have been knowledge of their assembly, as was the case with the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; - both of the individual reports and also of the larger segments (e.g., the &lt;em&gt;qatʿayn&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;qatʿan&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citing-al-tabari&quot;&gt;Citing al-Tabari&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should not assume that al-Tabari’s words were conveyed onwards in the form of published works, in the sense described by Schoeler. Nor should we assume that a person who passed on information from one of al-Tabari’s books necessarily had access to the whole work; we know that later authors did not, and even early users of his oeuvre may not have had the complete texts at their disposal. In the long term, the manuscript evidence points even more strongly to the partial transmission of al-Tabari’s works. For example, there is a not a single complete manuscript witness of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. Our text reuse data shows, furthermore, just how extensively the works were excerpted and reused at an early date and for centuries afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Citations of al-Tabari point to a fragmentary reception of his writings, where subsequent generations passed on his works without direct reference to his works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have just begun work on a further data set that documents the afterlife of al-Tabari’s writings using manuscripts, text reuse data and citations of his works and his name. Within our data, we can already see that the &lt;em&gt;haddathani/haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula was used to refer to subsequent persons’ connections back to him in a way that suggests his words passed into notebooks much like his teachers’ words had done. Like al-Tabari, these people also seem to have copied his material into notes that were then recycled into other works, some of which have come down to us. Although more work needs to be done to understand the usages of the &lt;em&gt;haddathani/haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula in specific later works and contexts, it is noteworthy that it continued at all. Its persistence seems consistent with what scholars have described as the ongoing prestige of aurality.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To locate citations of al-Tabari, we created a regular expression that searched our database of machine-readable files of books written in the roughly 260-year period between al-Tabari’s death in 310/923 and the death of Ibn ʿAsākir in 571/1176. Our search targeted the following variant forms of Abu Jaʿfar Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari’s name combined with &lt;em&gt;haddathani/haddathana&lt;/em&gt; and its variants (a method similar to that which produced our data set on al-Tabari’s three books).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;محمد بن جرير&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;أبي جعفر الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;أبو جعفر الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;أبا جعفر الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;أبي جعفر محمد بن جرير الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;أبو جعفر محمد بن جرير الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;أبا جعفر محمد بن جرير الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This search did not catch all occurrences of al-Tabari’s name in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s written after his lifetime, because we excluded certain surface forms (such as Abu Jaʿfar and Ibn Jarir) that would have produced too many false hits. Even with the more restrictive formula, we found 315 instances of al-Tabari’s being cited in an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; across sixty-six works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, consider this long &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; from Ibn ʿAsakir, which appears in his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;. Ibn ʿAsakir invokes al-Tabari’s name within his biography of al-Walid II b. Yazid (r. 125-6/743-4) in the context of a report regarding the so-called third &lt;em&gt;fitna&lt;/em&gt;, during which Yazid b. al-Walid (r. approximately six months in 126/744) seized the caliphate by overthrowing his cousin al-Walid II:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I [Ibn ʿAsakir] read aloud to (&lt;em&gt;qaraʾtu ʿala&lt;/em&gt;) Abu al-Wafaʾ Huffāz b. al-Hasan b. al-Husayn from ʿAbd al-ʿAziz b. Ahmad, who said that ʿAbd al-Wahhab al-Maydani told us that Abu Sulayman b. Zabr said that ʿAbd Allah b. Ahmad b. Jaʿfar told him that Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari told him:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Ahmad b. Zuhayr told us that ʿAli b. Muhammad told him, from ʿAmr b. Marwan al-Kalbi, that Yaʿqub b. Ibrahim b. al-Walid told him that when Yazid b. al-Walid went out (&lt;em&gt;kharaja&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. rebelled), a &lt;em&gt;mawla&lt;/em&gt; belonging to al-Walid went out on a horse …&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in the second paragraph and the report can be traced to al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with some precisely reproduced phrasing (as well as some differences, which do not concern us here).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; itself is not mentioned. This is typical of Ibn ʿAsakir’s citations: even when referring to people who wrote books, he very often cites the people, not the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both Ibn ʿAsakir’s text and the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; itself, al-Tabari’s direct informant is named as Ahmad b. Zuhayr (d. 279/892), who, according to Gilliot, wrote an &lt;em&gt;histoire&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;) of the caliphal period and attended the lessons of Musʿab b. ʿAbd Allah al-Zubayri (d. 233/848 or 236/851) on the genealogy of the Arabs.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Ibn al-Nadim attributes four works to Ahmad b. Zuhayr (&lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Mutayyamin&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Iʿrab&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Kitab Akhbar al-shuʿaraʾ&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this process, books were rendered doubly invisible. First, al-Tabari copied material from Ibn Zuhayr’s writings (which he obtained directly from the author) into his own &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. Then, what al-Tabari wrote was converted back into note format for several generations (as witnessed in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;). Finally, the material was absorbed into Ibn ʿAsakir’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;, with the identities of its previous book-form carriers – the writings of Aḥmad b. Zuhayr and al-Tabari – erased. In Ibn ʿAsakir’s work, these other writings have become invisible as books. Each of the people involved in this and similar chains of writing has gone to the trouble of creating a work. But it is as if each person afterwards has reserves credit for authoring a book only to himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concluding-remarks&quot;&gt;Concluding Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data for these blog posts was collected over several weeks during the Covid-19 pandemic. It was an extraordinary time to be buried in spreadsheets, doing this sort of intensive work. Perhaps it would have seemed less interesting in a different time. We did not set out to write eight posts, only two. But as we immersed ourselves in the data, we came to see the potential for gathering more data to address different aspects of the questions outlined at the start. In the months to come, we hope to publish our work in a peer-reviewed journal with additional reflections, data and corrections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method we are developing can be used with any text that is well structured (including having regularly marked paragraphs) and whose author cites sources according to a regular pattern. The Transmission Chains table can be filtered and sorted to address questions we have not raised (though keeping in mind the problems outlined in Post 2). The Name Normalisation table can be reused and expanded to, for example, study citation patterns in works written earlier or later. Scholars often work on a single book by a well-known author. The OpenITI corpus provides access to many less-known works, and digital methods applied to the entirety of an author’s surviving oeuvre can often shed more light on the author’s working methods than can close scrutiny of a single work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our data provided us with a complex new perspective on how al-Tabari worked, but we want to emphasise how much can also be learned by far more simple explorations. We encourage you to download the corpus through Zenodo and, as a matter of routine, to search individual works and the corpus broadly. Doing so will reveal hitherto unseen patterns, including in the structures of various works and in the frequencies of citation partners (as in our case). There is now a vast number of texts at your fingertips that you can not only read and search but also annotate and return to again and again on your own computer. We will be adding more book files to the OpenITI corpus in the future. If you do not see something that you would like to see in the corpus, please be in touch: if you can get hold of the work in question in a PDF file of reasonable quality, you can now create a machine-readable file of it through our Optical Character Recognition pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Digital Humanities is a field built on teamwork. We worked intensively together, even if separated by geography (Sarah in the United Kingdom and Masoumeh in Germany). We relied on the contributions, feedback and questions of a team of KITABis, whose input has been invaluable, and on those of reviewers of the project, especially Letizia Osti and Konrad Hirschler, who read these posts and improved them with their comments. We welcome your thoughts, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yaqut, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-ʿudabaʾ&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, Shamela0009788-ara1.mARkdown, ms. 1812. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The quotation goes on to list other works of al-Tabari. Yaqut, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-ʿudabaʾ&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, ms. 1801. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;F. Rosenthal, ‘Al-Farg̲h̲ānī’, in &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd ed., &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org.iij.idm.oclc.org/10.1163/1573-3912_islam_SIM_2280&quot;&gt;[http://dx.doi.org.iij.idm.oclc.org/10.1163/1573-3912_islam_SIM_2280]{.ul}&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wa-innama kharaja dhalika ila al-nas ʿala sabil al-ijaza ila sanna arbaʿ wa-tisʿin wa-miʾatayn&lt;/em&gt;. Yaqut, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-ʿudabaʾ&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, ms. 1815. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ibn al-Nadim, &lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, 0385.Fihrist.Shia003355-ara1.mARkdown, ms. 285, search term القطعان. On the term &lt;em&gt;qatʿan&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;qatʿayn&lt;/em&gt;, see Savant, &lt;em&gt;Cultural History of the Arabic Book&lt;/em&gt; (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See, for example, Letizia Osti’s forthcoming monograph on al-Suli. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ibn ʿAsakir, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, JK000916-ara1, ms. 25095. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, Shamela0009783BK1--ara1.completed, ms. 3267. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, ms. 1132. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Claude Gilliot, ‘La formation intellectuelle de Tabari (224/5–310/839–923)’, &lt;em&gt;Journal asiatique&lt;/em&gt; 276 (1988), 203–44, at 220–1. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">In this series of blog posts, we have argued for the imperative to rethink writerly culture in ways that allow for a more meaningful exploration of al-Tabari’s (d. 310/923) sources. We have also advanced a more general argument about the nature of writing in the period in which al-Tabari lived. The question that we should be asking is not whether a particular piece of writing constituted a published, redacted book but rather what forms writing took, what evidence we have of these forms in the works that survive, and how ideas about writing itself might have contributed to the evolution of the tradition – including the loss and oblivion of many of its layers.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 7: Text Reuse Alignments</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-7-Text-Reuse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 7: Text Reuse Alignments" /><published>2021-10-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-7--Text-Reuse-</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-7-Text-Reuse/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post 7: Text Reuse Alignments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did al-Tabari create his extensive works? We contend that well-organised sets of notes played a critical role. Our argument relies on reasoning about the practicalities of working at scale, as well as our analysis of a data set consisting of thousands of citations that al-Tabari begins with the formula ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). As demonstrated in previous posts, we have counted and tabulated these people who, he says, gave him information and have sketched visually (through tree maps) the bundles of notes he likely copied down and collated into notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also draw on text reuse alignments. As evidence, these are of an altogether different character and derive from a different data set. The alignments that we have identified between al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt; (files Shamela0009783BK1, Shamela0007798 and JK008250Vols in the OpenITI corpus, respectively) consist of 1,374 rows in which a passage of at least ten words in one of the works overlaps with a passage in another of the works. The books are divided into chunks of 300-word tokens, so the maximum length of an identified alignment is 300 words. The largest share of the alignments found is between the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (1,101), but there are also significant alignments between the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; (229) and a few between the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; (44). Of the alignments between the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, 258 contain 100 words or more, and 54 exceed 200 words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The algorithm that generated these alignments is called passim, and it is able to find aligned text passages rather well. For example, it recognises alignments even if the overlapping passage runs continuously in one text but contains additional insertions of phrases, names or other words in the other text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even short alignments often point to a shared source. The following brief alignment between the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, provides an example. Differences are highlighted, and dashes mark a word missing from one of the parallel texts. Even without knowing Arabic, one can see that the differences are not substantial in terms of quantity. Both alignments begin by citing Ibn Ishaq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, milestone 66:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p dir=&quot;rtl&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;&gt; ابن اسحاق قال يقال والله اعلم خلق الله ادم ثم وضعه ينظر اليه اربعين يوما قبل ان ينفخ فيه الروح حتى عاد صلصالا كالفخار ولم تمسه نار قال فلما مضي له &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, milestone 292:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p dir=&quot;rtl&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;&gt; ابن اسحاق \-\--فيقال والله اعلم خلق الله ادم ثم وضعه ينظر اليه اربعين عاما قبل ان ينفخ فيه الروح حتي عاد صلصالا كالفخار ولم تمسه نار قال فيقال والله &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, the passage is found in a section dedicated to the topic of Adam’s creation (&lt;em&gt;al-qawl fī khalq Ādam&lt;/em&gt;), and it is preceded by an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; going back to Muhammad b. Humayd (d. 248/862). The report begins with ‘Ibn Ishaq said’. The following translation loosely follows Rosenthal’s:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ibn Ishaq said, reportedly (God knows best!), that God created Adam, then put him down and looked at him for forty days before blowing the spirit into him, until he became &lt;em&gt;ṣalṣāl&lt;/em&gt; like potter’s clay untouched by fire. [Ibn Ishaq] said that once [that period] had passed …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, Ibn Ishaq is cited without an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;, and the word ‘said’ that follows his name in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; precedes it, thus falling outside the alignment. More critically, in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;’s version, God looked at Adam for forty years rather than forty days (&lt;em&gt;ʿāman&lt;/em&gt; versus &lt;em&gt;yawman&lt;/em&gt;). The passage appears in the context of commentary on Quran 2:30: ‘When your Lord said to the angels, I am putting a successor (&lt;em&gt;khalīfa&lt;/em&gt;) on earth, they said, “Will You place someone there who will cause corruption on it and shed blood, while we glorify You with Your praise and extol Your holiness?” [God] answered, “Surely, I know that which you do not know.”’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous such closely related passages, and once passim has identified and output them into a CSV file, we can spot their differences. But in its current form, passim does not capture paraphrase unless it occurs within a chunk that otherwise aligns. In general, this means that we have a harder time finding evidence of reuse when an author actively revised the source text into his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the longest alignments between the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, both texts rely heavily on Muhammad b. Humayd’s transmission of Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, of the ten longest alignments, all but one can be traced to Muhammad b. Humayd. The &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; – as passed on by Muhammad b. Humayd – represents a major source common to all three of al-Tabari’s works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond Muhammad b. Humayd, we find other direct informants. As an experiment, we searched through the passim output files for the surface forms of the ten most often cited direct informants. Of the 1,374 alignments, 555 contain one of the names – and in fact all ten top informants are named. Although this evidence is not extensive, it does suggest that al-Tabari reached back to the same trusted notebooks for his different works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not Copying Between Works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general picture of text reuse yielded by our data set is one of a few extensive alignments and many more fragmentary ones. The most obvious explanation for this phenomenon is that al-Tabari used a common set of notes but adapted them differently in different contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous scholars have held the view that al-Tabari did not copy wholesale the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; into the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (or vice versa), and that is also what our data and visualisations suggest.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Image 1: Alignments between the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (on the top) and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (on the bottom). Based on passim run of February 2021. Files compared: Shamela0009783BK1 and Shamela0007798.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest section of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; that is aligned with the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; falls within a discussion of events in the Prophet’s lifetime, specifically concerning the Prophet’s wife ʿAʾisha. The arrangement owes much to &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; material derived from Muhammad b. Humayd, and the frequency of mentions of Muhammad b. Humayd’s name in the aligned passages also points to both texts relying heavily on the &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Image 2: Alignments between the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; (on the top) and the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (on the bottom). Files compared: JK008250Vols and Shamela0009783BK1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, there are very few alignments between the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, and no obvious pattern. The total number of aligned passages between these two works is forty-four, and the longest passage consists of 239 words. Eight further alignments contain 100 words or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Image 3: Alignments between the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; (on the top) and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (on the bottom). Files compared: JK008250Vols and Shamela0007798.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, there are a total of 229 aligned passages, the longest of which is 265 words. Of these alignments, forty-five contain at least 100 words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In view of the most closely aligned sections in the two works, it is possible that al-Tabari used some short sections of the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-āthār&lt;/em&gt; to write up a few parts of the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, for example. Such consultations though would be few, if any at all. The general pattern and imprecision of the alignments do not support the conclusion that this was his primary modus operandi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our final blog post, we bring our exploration to a close with a brief but important reflection on how al-Tabari himself became a direct informant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Our translation loosely follows Wahiuddin Khan’s. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;E.g., Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 80–134 (where he combs the biographical sources). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="releases" /><summary type="html">Post 7: Text Reuse Alignments</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-25/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">OpenITI release 2021.2.5</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021-2-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OpenITI release 2021.2.5" /><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021-2-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021-2-5/">&lt;p&gt;The KITAB team has released a new version (2021.2.5) of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI&quot;&gt;OpenITI&lt;/a&gt; corpus at &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/5550338&quot;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;. The release is open access. It is our fifth release (second release in 2021). You can also access the release through our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release features 10,342 books, including all versions and editions (2,050,063,811 words), of which 6,337 are unique books written by 2,636 authors. In the release, 181 new ids have been added that reflect either new books, including OCRed books, which are assigned a new unique id, or changes to existing ids and corresponding URIs (resulting in new ids). In terms of structural annotation, 120 books have a new status, of which eighty-two are fully available in structural OpenITI mARkdown with a .mARkdown extension. Currently, there are 353 books in mARkdown, which have been reviewed and vetted by the annotation team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To access the major changes to the URIs as well as the statistics on the corpus, please see the release notes and the corresponding csv files at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/5550338&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE/tree/master/release_notes&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cite this version please include the following information (the bibliographical export is available at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3891466&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorenz Nigst, Maxim Romanov, Sarah Bowen Savant, Masoumeh Seydi and Peter Verkinderen, OpenITI: A Machine-Readable Corpus of Islamicate Texts (Version 2021.2.5) [data set] (October 2021), Zenodo, https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5550338.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="release" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="news" /><summary type="html">The KITAB team has released a new version (2021.2.5) of the OpenITI corpus at Zenodo. The release is open access. It is our fifth release (second release in 2021). You can also access the release through our GitHub repository.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/releases.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/releases.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 6: Sources Common to All of al-Tabari’s Works</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-6-Sources-Com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 6: Sources Common to All of al-Tabari’s Works" /><published>2021-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-6--Sources-Com</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-6-Sources-Com/">&lt;p&gt;The argument we are advancing in these blog posts is that when al-Tabari (d. 310/923) created his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt;, he relied on notes that were bound into notebooks of some kind, and we can reconstruct something of their contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We base our argument of the notebooks’ existence on practical evidence: the long interval between the time of writing and the time of his contact with the people he cites, the extensiveness of the citations (which would represent an astonishing feat of memory without written records) and the quick pace at which al-Tabari appears to have worked. There is also more direct evidence. This evidence consists of the citations themselves, including the ways in which they map onto probable notebooks, and of the alignments between all three books revealed by text reuse data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further point that emerges from our data set is the extent to al-Tabari appears to have gone back to the same sets of notes when composing each of his works. Let us look more closely at our data and numbers on this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewing all 849 names on our list of direct informants provides only a weak picture of sources common to the works. This list, as noted in an earlier post, contains many names that occur only once or twice in al-Tabari’s works, and the identities of many of them are uncertain. The list shows that al-Tabari relied on 347 direct informants for the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, 543 for the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and 342 for the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. Cross-checking pairs of these sub-lists shows that the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; have 139 direct informants in common, the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; have 110 in common and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; have 229 in common. All three works share 104 direct informants. These figures seem to suggest that he drew on many different sources and mostly used different sources for each work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the picture becomes more interesting when we focus on the smaller number of people on whom al-Tabari relied intensively. Recall that 51% of all of al-Tabari’s citations in our data set came from just eight people; twenty people accounted for 79% and fifty people for 89% of citations. It is these relatively few direct informants who mattered most to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By focusing on this small subset we get a clearer picture of al-Tabari’s working habits. Of the fifty direct informants cited most frequently, thirty-eight are cited in all three of his works. Of the top twenty, eighteen appear in all three, and each of the top ten is cited in each work. In other words, al-Tabari’s most important direct informants constituted his core source base for all three of his works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among these direct informants, there is a further subset consisting of people cited numerous times in each of the three works. The &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; took years to complete, and in the drawn-out writing process, the notes from these informants were al-Tabari’s go-tos and trusted favourites. In their case it seems especially probable that he had at his disposal stable notes bound together for easy reference and citation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Died&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tabari met in&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total count&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;*Count in *Tahdhib **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;248/862&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Rayy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2879&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;457&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2126&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;296&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. Bashshar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;252/866&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Basra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1644&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1240&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;370&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Abu Kurayb&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;248/862&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kufa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1609&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;69&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1033&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;507&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. al-Muthanna&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;250/864&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Basra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1081&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;649&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;385&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: Four direct informants on whom al-Tabari relied heavily and whose material was likely preserved in well-organised notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among al-Tabari’s informants, Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862), Muhammad b. Bashshar (d. 252/866), Ab Kurayb (d. 248/862) and Muhammad b. al-Muthanna (d. 250/864) stand out. It is not hard to see why al-Tabari saw these individuals’ works as particularly worthy of careful collation and frequent citation. Muhammad b. Humayd transmitted Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;, an important source both for history (&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;) and for interpretation of the Qur’an (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;; he is also cited 296 times in the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; within our data set).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other figures are well-known Hadith scholars. Scott Lucas’s work on al-Tabari’s ‘teachers’ has shown that Hadiths from each of these three are cited in all six of the canonical Sunni Hadith collections (i.e. those of al-Bukhari, Muslim, Abu Dawud, al-Tirmidhi, al-Nasaʾi and Ibn Maja).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These numbers are of interest for our understanding of knowledge transmission in the third/ninth and fourth/tenth centuries and beyond. How did an author whose works mattered so much to posterity put together his very large works? Reliable materials mattered. And those that al-Tabari deemed reliable he returned to again and again in his works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our next post, we examine text reuse alignments between al-Tabari’s works, which also suggest a common source base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Scott C. Lucas, &lt;em&gt;Selections from the Comprehensive Exposition of the Interpretations of the Verses of the Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge: Royal Aal Al-Bayt Institute for Islamic Thought and Islamic Texts Society, 2017), esp. ii, 467–82 (‘Appendix B: Ṭabarī’s Teachers’). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">The argument we are advancing in these blog posts is that when al-Tabari (d. 310/923) created his Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk, Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan (Tafsir) and Tahdhib al-athar, he relied on notes that were bound into notebooks of some kind, and we can reconstruct something of their contents.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 5: Reconstructing al-Tabari’s Notebooks</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-5-Reconstruct/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 5: Reconstructing al-Tabari’s Notebooks" /><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-5--Reconstruct</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-5-Reconstruct/">&lt;p&gt;In our previous blog post, we argued that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) had to hand an extensive written collection consisting of sets of well-written notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we demonstrate that the data we have collected helps us begin to visualise the notebooks that served as al-Tabari’s ‘data carriers’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Scholars have often mined al-Tabari’s citations for evidence of earlier works. They have given the lion’s share of their attention to reputed authors such as Mujahid and Sayf b. ʿUmar who lived two or more generations before al-Tabari. By contrast, our starting point is his direct informants and the material they passed on to al-Tabari. In some cases, they combined material from many different sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tree-maps&quot;&gt;Tree Maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visualise al-Tabari’s notebooks using a tree map that was created from a subset of the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s introduced by the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;) – specifically, &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s with at least three transmitters after al-Tabari. The tree map displays each person in an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; as a rectangle; the size of the rectangle is proportional to the number of times the person is cited. Our main tree map contains four layers of rectangles: al-Tabari himself (dark pink), his direct informants (dark orange), their informants (light orange) and the latters’ informants (yellow). For example, in the first notebook, Bishr b. Muʿadh’s (d. 245/859–60) main source is Yazid b. Zariʿ (d. 182/798-9?). All but twenty of the 2,387 chains that contain three persons after al-Tabari run thus: Bishr b. Muʿadh &amp;lt; Yazid b. Zariʿ &amp;lt; Saʿid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to stress that our tree maps do not represent the entirety of the data set, only the subset that fits their parameters. A tree map focused on &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s containing three transmitters will exclude all &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that are shorter than three transmitters. Similarly, a tree map visualising &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s of at least five transmitters will exclude &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s with fewer than five, resulting in a smaller subset and a different tree map. Historians interested in the earliest layers of transmission may find the longer &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; tree maps particularly interesting, as they highlight chunks of material that seem to have passed through multiple generations to al-Tabari’s direct informants and on to him. But they should remember that the data set was created to prioritise al-Tabari’s direct informants, not transmitters five generations removed from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The images included here are excerpts from a larger set of tree maps that we will publish with our data set in a forthcoming print publication. Bibliographical information is collated from publications by Gilliot, Athari and Lucas,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as well as from Ibn Nadim’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; and the relevant &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt; articles. We have also consulted other sources.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;six-sets-of-notes&quot;&gt;Six Sets of Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is a series of visualisations of six possible – even likely – collections of notes used by al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 1: Bishr b. Muʿadh&lt;/strong&gt; (d. 245/859–60), cited 2,418 times, filtered to 2,387 chains of at least three transmitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 1: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes on his lessons with Bishr b. Muʿadh in Basra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari relies on Bishr b. Muʿadh chiefly for reports going back to an authority he calls Saʿid, transmitted via Yazid b. Zariʿ. Ibn al-Nadim mentions in his bio-bibliographical &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;em&gt;Kitab Saʿid b. Bashir ʿan Qatada&lt;/em&gt; within a list of compilations of Quran commentary (&lt;em&gt;tasmiyat al-kutub al-musannafa fi tafsir al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt;). Qatada b. Diʿama (d. ca. 117/735) was a ‘successor’, that is, he belonged to the generation of Muslims after the Prophet’s death. He was famed for his memory and his knowledge of genealogies, lexicography, historical traditions, Quranic exegesis, variant Quran readings (&lt;em&gt;qiraʾāt&lt;/em&gt;) and Hadith. As for Saʿid, Muhammad b. Saʿd (d. 230/845) has an entry for Abu ʿAbd al-Rahman Saʿid b. Bashir al-Azdi, who, he says, died in 170 (786 or 787 CE), at the start of Harun al-Rashid’s caliphate; he also mentions that Saʿid b. Bashir was from Basra but settled in Damascus. He quotes several reports from Qatada through Saʿid b. Bashir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that continue after Saʿid, we indeed find that nearly all go back to Qatada. But can we be sure that the Saʿīd who passed on material from Qatada was it Saʿid b. Bashir? We cannot. Al-Tabari received reports from Qatada through several routes, including via a transmitter he names explicitly as Saʿīd b. Bashīr and another he calls Saʿīd b. Abī ʿUrūba, who may or may not be the same person. It is perhaps significant that when he refers specifically to Saʿid b. Bashir as a source for Qatada, his direct informant was not Bishr b. Muʿadh but rather a variety of other people (as many as nine). This means that we cannot be certain that there is only one Saʿīd who reported from Qatada or that al-Tabari received material from Saʿid b. Bashir through Bishr b. Muʿadh .&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is where further work on named entities would be particularly useful. We can say, however, that whatever the origin of its contents, al-Tabari’s Bishr b. Muʿadh notebook contained a lot of material from Qatada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari used this notebook mainly for the &lt;em&gt;Jāmiʿ al-bayān&lt;/em&gt;, but he also picked it up for the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and a few times for the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. The citations from it in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; all occur early in the book, with the last (at milestone 984) being found in al-Tabari’s reporting on the sixth year of the hijra. The sixth year is when the Prophet attempted to return to Mecca to make the lesser pilgrimage (&lt;em&gt;ʿumra&lt;/em&gt;) and ended up concluding the accord of al-Hudaybiyya (March 628). Al-Tabari cites Bishr as one of several sources on the events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 2: Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi&lt;/strong&gt; (d. 248/862), cited 2,879 times, filtered to 2,312 chains of at least three transmitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 2: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes on his lessons with Muhammad b. Humayd in Rayy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the frequency of citation, the notes al-Tabari obtained from Muhammad b. Humayd were by far the most important for the former’s works. Given the large number of quotations from these notes, they may have occupied numerous books or booklets. In biographical literature, Muhammad b. Humayd is well-known as a transmitter of Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; through the intermediary Salama b. al-Fadl, and it is likely that the material he transmitted from Ibn Ishaq was bound together. In this case, the difference between such notebooks versus a ‘book’ obtained through an &lt;em&gt;ijāza&lt;/em&gt; may have been slight. The data rightly challenges us to think harder not just about ‘actual books’ but also about the concept of notes and notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In writing the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, our data would say that al-Tabari relied almost exclusively on the notes from Muhammad b. Humayd for Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But for his other works he drew also on other notebooks containing material from the &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;, especially those of Abu Kurayb (d. 248/862), Yaʿqub b. Ibrāhim al-Dawraqi (d. 252/866), and Sufyan b. Wakiʿ (d. 247/861), as well as at least seven others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the large number of citations represented in this tree map, we might imagine that the material al-Tabari obtained from Jarir b. ʿAbd al-Hamid, Mihran b. Abi ʿUmar and Abu Tamila Yahya b. Saʿid would likewise have been bound. But how these notebooks would have been stored within al-Tabari’s own shelving system is another question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all material transmitted by Mihran from ‘Sufyan’ is quoted in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; from Sura 41 (‘Fussilat’) onwards; this is most likely a collection of the exegetical opinions of Sufyan al-Thawri (d. 161/778). Al-Tabari also cites other direct informants for Sufyan al-Thawri’s opinions, including Yunus b. ʿAbd al-Aʿla (d. 264/877), Abu Kurayb (d. 248/862), and al-Harith b. Muhammad (d. 282/895), as well as the chains Muhammad b. Humayd &amp;lt; Salama b. al-Fadl &amp;lt; Sufyan and Muhammad b. Humayd &amp;lt; Harun &amp;lt; Sufyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be worthwhile to compare the fragmentary Quran commentary attributed to Sufyan&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;. We have not done this. But we do have a machine-readable &lt;em&gt;tafsir&lt;/em&gt; text attributed to Sufyan al-Thawri in the OpenITI corpus (under identifier Shia002462; 29,140 words),&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which has twelve short alignments with al-Tabari’s text; the longest of these measures sixty-one words.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 3: Al-Muthanna b. Ibrahim al-Amuli&lt;/strong&gt; (d. unknown), cited 2,259 times, filtered to 1,973 chains of at least three people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 3: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes from his lessons with al-Muthanna in Rayy (possibly Amul also).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notes that al-Tabari assembled from al-Muthanna b. Ibrahim al-Amuli are quite diverse, with the largest pieces deriving from transmitters named Ishaq b. al-Hajjaj and Abu Salih ʿAbd Allah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter appears in Ibn al-Nadim’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; as Abu Salih ʿAbd Allah b. Muhammad b. Yazdad b. Suwayd (d. 223/837-8). Ibn al-Nadim calls him an eloquent scribe (&lt;em&gt;ahad al-kuttab al-bulaghaʾ&lt;/em&gt;) and attributes to him a &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and a book of epistles (&lt;em&gt;Kitab rasaʾilihi&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari refers to him in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; as ‘the scribe of al-Layth’ (&lt;em&gt;katib al-Layth&lt;/em&gt;); al-Layth appears within the tree map, too. This seems to refer to the famous traditionist and &lt;em&gt;faqih&lt;/em&gt; al-Layth b. Saʿd (d. 175/791).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Abu Salih ʿAbd Allah also transmitted from Muʿawiya b. Salih. In our &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, Muʿawiya’s reporting goes back to Ibn ʿAbbas through ʿAli b. Abi Talha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Zychowicz-Coghill has recently collected witnesses to a &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; by al-Layth on the basis of a recension by Yunus b. Bukayr that is quoted in five other texts. He argues that al-Tabari did not draw on al-Layth’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, our data reveals additional evidence in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; that contradicts his contention. Al-Layth is in fact cited in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, but through other &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s (and not, according to our data, through Yunus b. Bukayr).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Layth’s situation is complex, and readers will be forgiven if they find it a bit hard to follow. For us, the most important feature of it is that it allows us to discern how works that Ibn al-Nadim may have recognised as written works were broken down before al-Tabari’s lifetime, absorbed into subsequent writings, and then reabsorbed into al-Tabari’s book. This process seems to have carried memories of earlier works and their conservators (e.g. the reference to &lt;em&gt;katib al-Layth&lt;/em&gt;) but without either citing the works themselves or making an effort to keep them intact. That is why reconstructions are so tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of al-Tabari and, indeed, text reuse data in general, confirm what Beatrice Gruendler has recently argued, which is that in the third/ninth century (as well as beyond) the authorial agency of scholars such as al-Tabari was often exerted through acts of ‘memorizing, collecting, arranging, commenting, and transmitting of pre-existing sources’. As she writes, ‘This dealing with extant text made a scholar no less of an author in the eyes of his contemporaries, as he provided a repository of the knowledge that they needed.’ Gruendler distinguishes between different types of authorial agency. In poetry, authorship was recognised in the creation of a text, and a ‘basic difference already existed between a “ripped off” verbatim formulation and a borrowed reformulated motif’. In the case of poetry, ‘word-by-word’ copying was frowned on, though ‘a degree of reformulation changed the discourse from ownership to literary inspiration’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we step back, we can understand these two forms of agency as part of a wider epistemology, which attributed greater prestige to adaptation than to simple, perfect reproduction. The reproduction of a work – as a &lt;em&gt;katib&lt;/em&gt; – did not initiate one into the genealogy of a master, whereas a student’s transmission of a teacher’s work (as a &lt;em&gt;rawi&lt;/em&gt; or otherwise) incorporated the student’s persona into the text’s lineage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hierarchy of prestige can be detected in al-Tabari’s citations. Consider the following examples, which indicate al-Tabari’s efforts to track specific pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebooks 4 and 5:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ismaʿil b. ʿAbd al-Rahman al-Suddi&lt;/strong&gt; (d. ca. 127/745) via &lt;strong&gt;Musa b. Harun al-Hamdani&lt;/strong&gt; (d. unknown) and &lt;strong&gt;Muhammad b. al-Husayn&lt;/strong&gt; (d. 261/874), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 4: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes from his lessons with Musa b. Harun al-Hamdani (d. unknown) and Muhammad b. al-Husayn (d. 261/874).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The direct informants here are the obscure Musa b. Harun and Muhammad b. al-Husayn al-Baghdadi, a Hadith scholar from Nisa in modern-day Turkmenistan). Both transmit through different intermediaries (ʿAmr vs. Ahmad) from Asbat b. Nasr al-Hamdani, who in turn transmits from al-Suddi, a &lt;em&gt;mawla&lt;/em&gt; who was a popular preacher in Kufa. In both cases, al-Suddi’s ‘box’ (that is, the material he provided) is neatly nested inside Asbat’s. However, the material from al-Suddī accounts for less than half of the three-person &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s from either Musa b. Harun (who starts a total of 508 chains) and or Muhammad b. al-Husayn (who starts 528).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examining these citations, G. H. A. Juynbol questioned the degree to which the material attributed to al-Suddi could be used to understand his views: ‘In al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, countless exegetical remarks ascribed to al-&lt;em&gt;Suddi&lt;/em&gt; can be found and could conceivably be brought together in a volume. Whether such a compilation would allow conclusions as to a certain bias or predilection on his part, if any, has as yet to be established.’ Ibn al-Nadīm does indeed mention a &lt;em&gt;Kitab Tafsir al-Suddi&lt;/em&gt; within the section, mentioned above, that lists compilations of Quranic commentary (&lt;em&gt;tasmiyat al-kutub al-musannafat fi tafsir al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 6: ʿAbd Allah b. al-ʿAbbas&lt;/strong&gt; (d. ca. 68/687–8) via Muhammad b. Saʿd (d. 276/889).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 5: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes on information received through a family &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; from Muhammad b. Saʿd (d. 276/889) in Baghdad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari met Muhammad b. Saʿd b. Muhammad b. al-Hasan b. ʿAtiyya b. Saʿd b. Junada al-ʿAwfi in Baghdad. The information he received from the latter originates with ʿAbd Allah b. al-ʿAbbas (d. ca. 68/687–8), a member of the first generation of Muslims who is frequently called the father of Quranic exegesis. The full chain, in which the description of family relations reflects the respective quoted speaker’s perspective, runs as follows: Muhammad b. Saʿd &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;abi&lt;/em&gt; [‘my father’] &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;ʿammi&lt;/em&gt; [‘my paternal uncle’, i.e. Muhammad b. Saʿd’s great-uncle] &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;abihi&lt;/em&gt; [‘his father’, i.e. the great-uncle’s father] &amp;lt; Ibn ʿAbbas. Franz Rosenthal described al-Tabari’s material from Muhammad b. Saʿd as an ‘unpublished’ book and ‘the heirloom of a particular family’ and noted that ‘a family &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; as complete as this is most remarkable’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that although generating our data was challenging, once generated it is relatively easy to read. Filtering the data in the Transmission Chains table to order the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s alphabetically by the name in position 5, for example, reveals numerous identical &lt;em&gt;isnads&lt;/em&gt; running back to Ibn ʿAbbas. The interpretation of these &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s will, of course, remain a subject of debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Limits of Our Argument&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholars such as Lawrence Conrad, Andrew Rippin, Ella Landau-Tasseron and Arietta Papaconstantinou have rightly raised questions about efforts to reconstruct lost sources.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There is an understandable concern in the field about the risks associated with mining later sources for evidence of earlier ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work is a comparatively modest effort. Our primary focus is on what al-Tabari had to hand, not on whether any given chunk of material can in fact be traced back to Umayyad times. We make no judgement, for example, about whether the Ibn ʿAbbas notebook actually goes back to the man himself. Indeed, we are sceptical that the notebooks can be reconstructed. Instead, they can be described, given that we possess only extracts from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the earlier layers, we are also generally sceptical about the possibility of reconstructing ‘actual books’ from earlier time periods on the basis of quotations and citations found in works that survive today. Our scepticism arises from the fact that authors treated their notes as reusable materials. Now that technology can aid us in new ways, further work on assessing alignments will be worthwhile, but we should be searching for more nuanced ways to describe what we find. What was the nature of these earlier works? Corpora of quotations can be collected and described and sketches of the early written tradition developed on the basis of this evidence, as Kevin Jaques is doing for Ibn Ishaq and as Zychowicz-Coghill has done for al-Layth b. Saʿd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our main bone of contention with efforts at reconstruction that mine later sources for earlier works is that they often give little or no attention or agency to the persons we call al-Tabari’s direct informants. Al-Tabari drew on a material reality that had its own form and organisation. Broadly speaking, our work reflects the field’s rising attention to the materiality of texts, although we do not work with manuscripts. Rather, we direct our attention to where the material has vanished but direct citations of it remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our next post, we compare al-Tabari’s books and investigate how different notebooks fed into different works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Beatrice Gruendler, &lt;em&gt;The Rise of the Arabic Book&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2020), 67. Maxim Romanov has made this argument for al-Dhahabi’s (d. 748/1348) &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-Islam&lt;/em&gt;; see e.g. Romanov, ‘Observations of a Medieval Quantitative Historian?’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 94/2 (2017), 462–95, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1515/islam-2017-0028&quot;&gt;[https://doi.org/10.1515/islam-2017-0028]{.ul}&lt;/a&gt;, at 482ff. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Claude Gilliot, ‘La formation intellectuelle de Tabari (224/5–310/839–923)’, &lt;em&gt;Journal asiatique&lt;/em&gt; 276 (1988), 203–44; Akram Atharī, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyūkh al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt; (Amman and Cairo: n.p., 2005); and Scott C. Lucas, &lt;em&gt;Selections from the Comprehensive Exposition of the Interpretations of the Verses of the Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge: Royal Aal Al-Bayt Institute for Islamic Thought and Islamic Texts Society, 2017), esp. ii, 467–82 (‘Appendix B: Ṭabarī’s Teachers’). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;E.g. Muhammad S. H. Hallaq, &lt;em&gt;Rijal Tafsir al-Tabari, jarhan wa-taʿdilan: Min tahqiq Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan li-Ahmad Shakir wa-Mahmud Shakir&lt;/em&gt; (Beirut: Dar Ibn Hazm, 1999). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. Athari, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt;, 159. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;R. Kevin Jaques has assembled a list of persons upon whom al-Tabari relied for Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;, plus locations within the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sufyan al-Thawri, &lt;em&gt;Tafsir al-Qurʾan al-karim&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Imtiyaz ʿAli ʿArshi (Rampur: n.p., 1965). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This work was published as &lt;em&gt;Tafsir al-Thawri&lt;/em&gt;, edited by ‘a committee (&lt;em&gt;lajna&lt;/em&gt;) of &lt;em&gt;ʿulamaʾ&lt;/em&gt;’, in 1403 AH [1982–3 CE]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The alignments are available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.kitab-project.org/passim01022021/Shia002462-ara1/Shia002462-ara1_Shamela0007798-ara1.inProgress.csv&quot;&gt;[http://dev.kitab-project.org/passim01022021/Shia002462-ara1/Shia002462-ara1_Shamela0007798-ara1.inProgress.csv]{.ul}&lt;/a&gt; (included in the data set associated to these blogs). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari refers to al-Layth b. Saʿd (also as al-Layth b. Saʿd al-Misri), but in our data set this name never appears in the al-Muthanna &amp;lt; ʿAbd Allah chains, which refer only to ‘al-Layth’. Al-Tabari may well have maintained in his citations the different surface forms of names that he had recorded in his notes. Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (d. 463/1071) describes an ʿAbd Allah b. Saliḥ b. Muhammad b. Muslim Abu Salih as an Egyptian who was the &lt;em&gt;katib al-Layth b. Saʿd&lt;/em&gt; and who accompanied the latter to Baghdad. The names here do not quite match (ʿAbd Allah b. Muhammad versus ʿAbd Allah b. Salih). See al-Khatib al-Baghdadi, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh Baghdad&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, Shamela0000736-ara2.mARkdown, search term: كاتب الليث. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Edward Zychowicz-Coghill, &lt;em&gt;The First Arabic Annals: Fragments of Umayyad History&lt;/em&gt; (Berlin: de Gruyter, 2021), 3. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gruendler, &lt;em&gt;Rise of the Arabic Book&lt;/em&gt;, 60–2. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 6 and 215, n. 337. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lawrence Conrad, ‘Recovering Lost Texts: Some Methodological Issues’, &lt;em&gt;Journal of the American Oriental Society&lt;/em&gt; 113/2 (1993), 258–63; Andrew Rippin, ‘&lt;em&gt;Tafsir Ibn ʿAbbās&lt;/em&gt; and Criteria for Dating Early &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; Texts’&lt;em&gt;, Jerusalem Studies in Arabic and Islam&lt;/em&gt; 18 (1994), 38–83; Ella Landau-Tasseron, ‘On the Reconstruction of Lost Sources’, &lt;em&gt;al-Qanṭara&lt;/em&gt; 25 (2004), 45–91; Arietta Papaconstantinou, review of Robert Hoyland, &lt;em&gt;Theophilus of Edessa’s Chronicle and the Circulation of Historical Knowledge in Late Antiquity and Early Islam&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Le Muséon&lt;/em&gt; 126 (2013), 459–65. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">In our previous blog post, we argued that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) had to hand an extensive written collection consisting of sets of well-written notes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 4: The Form of al-Tabari’s Sources: His Probable Notebooks</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-4-The-Form-of/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 4: The Form of al-Tabari’s Sources: His Probable Notebooks" /><published>2021-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-4--The-Form-of</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-4-The-Form-of/">&lt;p&gt;In the preceding posts, we showed that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) used the phrases ‘he told me’ and ‘he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;) in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt; to indicate people from whom he had obtained information directly. He mentions hundreds of people in this manner – but a very small subset of them accounts for the majority of his citations. Al-Tabari’s three works contain a vast amount of material from direct informants, and most of that material came into his possession early in his life, a long time before he composed his books. It is our contention that al-Tabari made use of an extensive written record to preserve and organise his material over the decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-notes&quot;&gt;Why Notes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This contention may be met with scepticism. One might argue that al-Tabari memorised the information he obtained from his informants and could recall it without the need for written aids. Memorisation of reports was a culturally valued skill in his time. However, there are five main reasons to think that he in fact drew on well-written and well-organised notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The long time – as much as half a century – that had elapsed between his contact with the sources and his writing (see the previous post).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The extensiveness of the citations. There are thousands of pieces of information from different informants scattered across thousands of pages of his works. Citation chains featuring direct informants alternate with other citation chains, disappear for hundreds of pages and then reappear. The feats of medieval memory defy our imagination today, and we do well not to underestimate its role and importance. But the rote recall and deft manipulation of purely oral information on such a scale does seem highly unlikely. A model of memory operating like an index is more plausible: al-Tabari had an extensive mental map of his data, which allowed him to locate what he needed in his notes as he created his own works, drawing on, but not merely reproducing, earlier writings with their own forms. All three of his works are highly structured, by chronology (&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;), Quranic chapters (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) or early traditionists (&lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari’s memory feat was to map the contents of these earlier works, with their own forms, into his own.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The efficiency of al-Tabari’s work. Much of the material he incorporated into his own works may already have been systematically arranged along lines similar to the structure of his own works. But his fast writing pace can also be explained by a well-organised collection of written material – that is, notebooks that he had compiled in specific times and contexts during his youth and that he returned to again and again. The most often used notebooks, based on notes collected from only a few persons, a crucial role for al-Tabari. He relied heavily on them as well as on other written sources, including another written source, whose extensive reuse by al-Tabari can be detected in our data (though he does not cite the work).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The regular citation of the same transmission chains pointing back to earlier written works. Al-Tabari relied substantially on information from individuals who lived before him, many of whom are reported to have written books of their own. Although he could not have met these people in person, his most important direct informants provided him with access, possibly only lightly mediated, to these earlier compositions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The three works’ close (though not exact) alignments with other surviving texts, including al-Tabari’s own. When using earlier texts, he appears to have made adjustments to them to fit the thematic interests of his own books.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal already noted al-Tabari’s probable use of notebooks as well as the scarcity of his citations of actual books by others. He concluded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There can be no doubt that the ‘I was told’ and ‘we were told’ at the opening of chains of transmitters have as a rule to be taken literally as indicating direct personal contact or contact within the setting of public lectures and instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosenthal nonetheless discerned a pretence of orality in al-Tabari’s citations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It must also be assumed that he often referred to someone with whom he undoubtedly had some personal contact, but later, he used the source that was transmitted to him by that individual in its written (published) form and quoted from it while pretending all the time to rely upon oral transmission.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our view, it is more reasonable to read al-Tabari’s citations with &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; as explicit acknowledgement of material that he received orally and recorded in his notes and notebooks. By using these distinctive phrases (and differentiating them from phrases such as &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;), he was emphasising that the transmission took place through personal contact, which was considered more prestigious and more authoritative than transmission of written material alone. From al-Tabari’s perspective, he was saying exactly what he was doing; there was no pretence involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregor Schoeler’s depiction of aurality among Muslim writers of the third/ninth century may partly explain al-Tabari’s learning situation. As noted in our first blog post, in his discussion of forms of writing in this period, Schoeler distinguished between essentially private notes and notebooks (&lt;em&gt;hypomnēmata&lt;/em&gt;, sing. &lt;em&gt;hypomnēma&lt;/em&gt;), on the one hand, and ‘actual books, composed and redacted according to the canon of stylistic rules, and intended for publication’ (&lt;em&gt;syngrammata&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;syngramma&lt;/em&gt;), on the other. The Arabic tradition refers to both types as books (&lt;em&gt;kutub&lt;/em&gt;, sing. &lt;em&gt;kitāb&lt;/em&gt;). Before the third/ninth century, the conventions that would later mark a ‘published’ book had not yet crystallised, and accordingly many books written in that period do not survive, while others, such as the &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; of Ibn Ishaq and the &lt;em&gt;Muwaṭṭaʾ&lt;/em&gt; of Malik b. Anas, survive in multiple variant versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book historians have identified the third/ninth century as a turning point at which &lt;em&gt;syngrammata&lt;/em&gt; began to flourish. Most recently, Beatrice Gruendler has painted a detailed picture of this century, in which books appeared as ‘new media’. Al-Tabari’s numerous and extensive writings represent a milestone that ought to be considered in any periodisation of book history. It is hard to imagine them coming into existence fifty years earlier, when he was still a student and the ‘rise of the Arabic book’ was only beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But did scholars such as al-Tabari view the materials at their disposal in strictly binary terms – as either notes/notebooks or ‘actual books’ or, to put it differently, as either ‘published’ or unpublished works? Al-Tabari gives little indication of such binary thinking in his citations. We might look for a distinction in how he cites people (whose information he recorded as notes) versus how he cites redacted books (which he accessed without direct contact with the authors). But he only rarely acknowledges books as his sources. Even when he cites someone known to have authored a relevant book, he usually fails to mention the work in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when citing reports from Sayf b. ʿUmar (d. during the reign of al-Rashid, r. 170–93/786–809), al-Tabari repeatedly uses phrasing that suggests he accessed Sayf’s work in the form of written material acquired by al-Sari, who himself relied on Shuʿayb (&lt;em&gt;wa-amma al-Sari, fa-innahu qala fi kitabihi ilayya&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;haddathana Shuʿayb ʿan Sayf&lt;/em&gt; …).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Modern scholars, mostly basing their discussions on al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, have speculated about the nature of Sayf’s work, which no longer survives, primarily for the purpose of assessing its reliability (or lack thereof) as a source for the events it relates.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The title &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Futuh al-kabir wa-l-ridda&lt;/em&gt; as the name of Sayf’s lost work does not appear in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;; its widespread use and attribution today appear to derive from Ibn al-Nadim’s (d. 385/995) &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that what is required for a more nuanced understanding of al-Tabari’s work and the literary culture of his time is deeper probing of the variety of written forms that existed and were likely to be used by people such as al-Tabari. What forms might notes have taken? What sorts of ways of binding material together can we imagine? It may have been conventional within &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s to mention individuals and not their works, but what does this convention tell us about how authors such as al-Tabari thought about the works at their disposal and what they could expect in terms of the treatment of their own works afterwards?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line of enquiry requires an openness to the many ways in which al-Tabari and his peers might have constructed and conceived of their own works. It could have the effect of demoting ‘actual books’ as the main, privileged carriers of information in the third/ninth and fourth/tenth centuries and beyond.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Therefore, we would do well to broaden our understanding of authorship to include many forms of writing and writerly culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aligning-al-tabaris-books&quot;&gt;Aligning al-Tabari’s Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence of text reuse in al-Tabari’s works indicates that he drew repeatedly on the same written sources in his writings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 1. An excerpt from a longer alignment (displayed furthest to the right, with the excerpt circled in red) between passages based on Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (on the right; OpenITI, Shamela0009783, milestones 596–604) and in his &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (on the left; OpenITI, Shamela0007798, milestones 9635–41). Text found only in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; is highlighted in green; text found only in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; is highlighted in blue. The long green block comes from Hisham b. Muhammad al-Kalbi. Alignment generated with Ryan Muther’s adaptation of David Smith’s passim software and fed into the OpenITI Diff viewer application (created by Peter Verkinderen, who also designed the way to visualise the location of the excerpt within the whole).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alignment shown on the far right side of Image 1 covers ten consecutive pages in the Leiden edition of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and almost the same in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is one of the longest alignments between the two works. Looking at it gives the impression that one is seeing the seams that run between and link the works. The passages overlap very closely, but they have slight wording differences that could reflect al-Tabari’s own different readings of the text that he received from Muhammad b. Humayd in Rayy while in his teens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closeness of the two texts is evident in the very first sentences in the alignment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;: He [Ibn Ishaq] said: Abraha then built al-Qalis (or al-Qullays) in Sanʿaʾ. He built a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) unlike any seen on earth in its time. Afterwards, he wrote to the Negus, the king of the Abyssinians, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;O king! I have built for you a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) the like of which has never been built for any king before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;: He [Salama b. al-Fadl] said: Ibn Ishaq told us (&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;) that Abraha built a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) in Sanʿaʾ. He was Christian and called it (&lt;em&gt;sammaha&lt;/em&gt;) al-Qalis (or al-Qullays). It was unlike any seen on earth in its time. He wrote to the Negus, the king of the Abyssinians, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;O king! I have built for you a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) the like of which has never been built for any king before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For al-Tabari, the account of the building of the church in Sanʿaʾ may have been a familiar story, one that he taught regularly in his afternoon teaching sessions in Baghdad. When he sat down to compose the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, the text of this story was well known to him; it was alive in his memory. Writing it down may have been akin to singing for him, insofar as he had internalised the text down to the level of the words and so could improvise when addressing his audience. In the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, he seems to have added the clarification that Abraha was a Christian and that the church he built was called al-Qalis (or al-Qullays). The beginning of the story is thus similar but not identical in the two texts, but when quoting the Negus’s letter al-Tabari appears to have returned to his notes to ensure verbatim accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both reports rely on a transmission chain that ran from his direct informant, Muhammad b. Humayd (d. 248/862), through Salama b. al-Fadl (d. after 190/805-6) to Ibn Ishaq (d.c. 151/768), though the chain is cited explicitly in connection with this story only in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, al-Tabari gives the chain earlier in the text, at the beginning of the overall narrative, without repeating it thereafter). It is likely that the clarification in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; was added by al-Tabari himself, though we cannot know for sure without access to the notes themselves. It is also possible that the clarification was already present in al-Tabari’s notes, or that both texts differ slightly from the text recorded in the notes. Or that a copyist or copyists were involved along the way. We do not, at present, have an earlier, independent text of Ibn Ishaq’s work against which to compare al-Tabari’s version, but a cursory look at text reuse data for this passage in works written after al-Tabari’s lifetime suggests that the version in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; aligns more closely with other transmissions of Ibn Ishaq’s text than does the version in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of al-Tabari’s notes would have been thoroughly familiar to him, but others he would have known less well, perhaps because he never taught from them, even if he drew on them for his works. Infrequently recalled material – like a melody one has heard only once or twice long ago, to continue the singing metaphor – would not lend itself so easily to improvisation or expansion. It is possible that the many much shorter and often very precise alignments between al-Tabari’s works reflect instances in which he reproduced such less familiar material from his notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of his long and illustrious career, al-Tabari was extraordinarily productive in several different fields, including Quran commentary, history and law (in his catalogue of authors, Ibn al-Nadim places him in the chapter on &lt;em&gt;ʿulamaʾ&lt;/em&gt;). We might reasonably speculate that al-Tabari copied parts of his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; into his &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, or vice versa. That would have been efficient. But the text reuse data indicates that that is not how he generally worked. Instead, it seems that he went back to the same sources again and again in the course of composing each of his works. We examine the alignments between his works more closely in a later post, when we consider his reliance on notebooks for his three major works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Discussed in Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 5–6 (citing Yaqut); see also 52-4. Heribert Horst has also argued that al-Ṭabarī’s sources were mostly lecture notes, written down as an aide-mémoire. He examined a large number of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and concluded that al-Tabari relied on only four or five ‘complete books’ (&lt;em&gt;vollständige Bücher&lt;/em&gt;), by ʿAli b. Abi Ṭalha, Mujahid, ʿAbd al-Rahman b. Zayd b. Aslam, Ibn Ishaq and possibly Ibn Saʿd. Horst, ‘Zur Überlieferung im Korankommentar aṭ-Ṭabarīs’, &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift der deutschen morgenländischen Gesellschaft&lt;/em&gt; 103 (1953), 290–307, at 307. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See, for example, al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, Shamela0009783BK1-ara1.completed, ms. 1302. R. Stephen Humphreys translates this phrase as ‘It was transmitted to me in writing by al-Sarī.’ See al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, xv: &lt;em&gt;The Crisis of the Early Caliphate:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Reign of ʿUt̲h̲mān&lt;/em&gt;, trans. R. S. Humphreys (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1990), 47. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a still-useful summary of the scholarly treatment of Sayf, see Ella Landau-Tasseron, ‘Sayf ibn ʿUmar in Medieval and Modern Scholarship’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 67 (1990), 1–26. See also F. M. Donner, ‘Sayf b. ʿUmar’, in &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd ed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ibn al-Nadim, &lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, 0385.Fihrist.Shia003355-ara1.mARkdown, search term: سيف بن عمر. It is also noteworthy that the plural term الفتوح occurs only sixteen times in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a related discussion, see Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘People vs. Books’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. J. de Goeje et al., 15 vols in 3 series (Leiden: E. J. Brill, 1879–1901), i, 934–45; al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, v: &lt;em&gt;The Sasanids, the Byzantines, the Lakhmids, and Yemen&lt;/em&gt;, trans. C. E. Bosworth (Leiden: Brill, 1999), 217–35; al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan&lt;/em&gt;, ed. ʿAbd Allah b. ʿAbd al-Muḥsin al-Turki ([N.p.]: [Dar Hijr li-l-Tabaʿa wa-l-Nashr wa-l-Tawaziʿ wa-l-Iʿlan], 2001), xxiv, 636–44. See also al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, v: &lt;em&gt;The Sasanids, the Byzantines, the Lakhmids, and Yemen&lt;/em&gt;, trans. C. E. Bosworth (Leiden: Brill, 1999), 217–35. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">In the preceding posts, we showed that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) used the phrases ‘he told me’ and ‘he told us’ (haddathani/haddathana) in the Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk, the Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan (Tafsir) and the Tahdhib al-athar to indicate people from whom he had obtained information directly. He mentions hundreds of people in this manner – but a very small subset of them accounts for the majority of his citations. Al-Tabari’s three works contain a vast amount of material from direct informants, and most of that material came into his possession early in his life, a long time before he composed his books. It is our contention that al-Tabari made use of an extensive written record to preserve and organise his material over the decades.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 3: How Many People Did al-Tabari Talk To?</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-3-Post-3-How/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 3: How Many People Did al-Tabari Talk To?" /><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-3--Post-3--How</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-3-Post-3-How/">&lt;p&gt;This is the third in a series of blog posts examining al-Tabari’s (d. 310/923) citations in his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jāmiʿ al-bayān ʿan taʾwīl āy al-Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;), and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-āthār&lt;/em&gt;. In the first and second posts we presented our questions, method and data set. The data set consists of six tables created iteratively using a series of analytical procedures developed by both of us and implemented by Masoumeh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we tackle the size of al-Tabari’s likely source base. In particular, we seek to establish how many people he credits with a major role in providing the information on which he relies. Al-Tabari’s books are full of citations, giving the impression that he drew actively on numerous sources of information. How big was his source base? And how many people gave him significant amounts of information directly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-small-number-of-very-important-direct-informants&quot;&gt;A Small Number of Very Important Direct Informants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to grips with al-Tabari’s source base means wrestling with a long and complicated list of names whose referents countless generations have already struggled to identify. We cannot access these sources directly, unmediated by the efforts of the intervening generations. But using digital methods, we can discern and analyse frequencies and patterns of citation on a scale that is unprecedented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to determine precisely how many people al-Tabari reported from directly using the &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula, but we were able to form a fairly good estimate of that number, and it is surprisingly small. We looked at all 32,115 &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that feature this formula in any of al-Tabari’s three works and counted the number of citations for each direct informant (the first person in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;); these figures are presented in the Direct Informants Overview table, described in our previous post. After listing the informants in the order of the frequency with which they are cited, we calculated the cumulative total number of citations and the percentage of the total that the citations represent at each level – the top informant, the top two informants, the top three and so on down the list. This information is found in the ‘Cumulative count’ and ‘Cumulative percentage’ columns. The table yields the following data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of names&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;% of all citations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;36%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;42%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;56%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;59%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;79%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;93%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: The percentage of al-Tabari’s citations accounted for by his most frequently cited direct informants, at different sample sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1 shows the high degree to which al-Tabari relied on a small group of core informants – indeed a very small group, in view of the large size of his works. The numbers are dramatic: more than half (51%) of al-Tabari’s citations go back to a mere eight direct informants, and the vast majority – nearly 80% – of his citations are to just twenty people. This is extraordinary, especially considering that he often names an informant on first mention but not in subsequent references, when his readers know whom he means. Since our method catches only explicit mentions of informants’ names, it is likely to understate the true frequency of references to the most common informants. In reality, then, the degree of concentration is probably even higher than it appears from our figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, 749 names cited by al-Tabari appear as direct informants in only about 7% of his citations across all three works. There are hundreds of names that appear just once, though many of these names may represent variant surface forms of the same name. The total number of people from whom al-Tabari actually harvested information is likely to fall far short of this high figure. More probably it lies in the neighbourhood of 200–300; but within this number, a very small group played an outsized role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-top-ten&quot;&gt;The Top Ten&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that al-Tabari worked efficiently, drawing maximum benefit from a small set of sources. But who were these people? What follows is an annotated list of the ten most often cited informants in order of the frequency of their citation. These ten persons are cited in all three of al-Tabari’s works, and according to our data set they together account for 59% of all references to a direct informant. The list specifies how many times al-Tabari cites each individual (that is, how often the individual’s name begins a paragraph in our machine-readable files) after &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; (‘he told me’) and &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; (‘he told us’), respectively. The biographical information given below has been collated from publications by Gilliot, Athari and Lucas.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We also list the variant surface forms of each name. It is important to note that surface forms can vary for many reasons, including different appellations by which a person was known, the effect of Arabic case endings (which vary depending on the sentence’s syntax), and typological and other errors, both those present in the source texts and those arising from the normalisation of Arabic script in the OpenITI corpus. (As an example, the variation in the dotting of the final yaʾ under Bishr b. Muʿadh below appears already in the source on which the OpenITI file is based.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862). Cited 2,879 times (21 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/2,858 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Rayy, where he stayed for five years after leaving home at the age of 12. Ibn Humayd transmitted a recension of Ibn Ishaq’s biography of the Prophet to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن حميد&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن حميد الرازي&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن حميد&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن حميد الرازي&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In terms of Ibn Ishaq’s biography of the Prophet, it is hard to know precisely what Muhammad b. Humayd had to hand. It may have been the case that al-Tabari worked off of a written version. This was the view of Heribert Horst, who concluded that Ibn Ishaq’s book was one of only four or five ‘complete books’ (&lt;em&gt;vollständige Bücher&lt;/em&gt;) upon which al-Tabari relied.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; R. Kevin Jaques believes it likely that al-Tabari heard a portion of an Ibn Ishaq version from Muhammad b. Humayd, but received permission (in the form of an an &lt;em&gt;ijaza&lt;/em&gt;) to transmit the entirety. As Jaques writes, ‘In al-Tabari’s citation of Ibn Humayd, he would have received an ʿ&lt;em&gt;ijāza&lt;/em&gt; to transmit Ibn Humayd’s ideas as if al-Tabari had heard the entirety of it from Ibn Humayd’s lips. What was accredited for transmission was, in effect, the oeuvre of the author.’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;While al-Tabari may have worked in this way, the high prevalence of the ‘he told me’ formula represents his access as based on a relationship that ran over time. Yaqut quotes Ibn Kāmil (d. 350/961), a contemporary and early biographer of al-Tabari, as saying that al-Tabari wrote down over 100,000 Hadiths based on reporting from Muhammad b. Humayd (&lt;em&gt;kataba ʿan Ibn Humayd&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The account falls within Ibn Kamil’s description of al-Tabari’s journey in search of knowledge, an account that generally emphasises how much al-Tabari wrote down and stored up for later use (including mention of his rearrangement of his materials). The sense from Yaqut (via Ibn Kamil) would be that al-Tabari heard individual reports from Muhammad b. Humayd, not that he sat down to a written out version of the Prophet’s biography.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Of course, Muhammad b. Humayd passed on more material than the Prophet’s biography. This leaves open the possibility that Ibn Kamil’s account – emphasising bit by bit acquisition – applies to this other material, not the biography by Ibn Ishaq. This is not, however, what Yaqut’s text straight-forwardly says.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bishr b. Muʿadh (d. 245/859–60). Cited 2,418 times (23 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/2,395 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Basra. Al-Tabari relies on him and two intermediaries for a major collection of exegetical opinions from an early traditionist, Qatada (d. ca. 118/736–7).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بشر&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بشر بن معاذ العقدى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بشر بن معاذ العقدي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Al-Muthanna b. Ibrahim al-Amuli (d. unknown). Cited 2,259 times (2,064 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/195 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him either in Amul or in Rayy.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبراهيم&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبراهيم الآملي&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبراهيم الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبرهيم الآملي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yunus b. ʿAbd al-Aʿla al-Sadafi (d. 264/867). Cited 2,250 times (2,113 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/137 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). A famous early supporter of al-Shafiʿi and a major scholar in Egypt, where al-Tabari met him. For al-Tabari, he is the source of a Quran commentary by ʿAbd al-Rahman b. Zayd.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس بن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس بن عبد الأعلى الصدفى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس بن عبد الأعلى الصدفي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Al-Qasim b. al-Hasan (d. 272/885). Cited 1,699 times (56 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1643 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Baghdad. Gilliot says this is probably Abu Muhammad al-Qasim b. al-Hasan b. Yazid al-Hamdani al-Saʾigh. He is cited in numerous reports in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; as reporting from the Meccan Ibn Jurayj (d. 150/768), who composed a &lt;em&gt;Sunan&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;القاسم&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;القاسم بن الحسن&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. Bashshar, called Bundār (d. 252/866). Cited 1,644 times (16 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,628 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Basra. He was a major Hadith scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن بشار&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بن بشار&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن بشار&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Abu Kurayb (d. 248/862). Cited 1,609 times (12 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,597 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Kufa. One of the transmitters of Ibn Ishaq from Yunus b. Bukayr (d. 199/815). Gilliot mentions (on the basis of Yaqut’s &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-ʿudabāʾ&lt;/em&gt;) that al-Tabari memorised Abu Kurayb’s reports; the reports also indicate that al-Tabari may have written them down afterwards as notes.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;أبا كريب محمد بن العلاء أبو كريب&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;أبو كريب محمد بن العلاء&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن العلاء&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن العلاء أبو كريب&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن العلاء الهمداني&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sufyan b. Wakiʿ (d. 247/861). Cited 1,443 times (16 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,427 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Kufa.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن وكيع&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;سفيان بن وكيع&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;سفيان بن وكيع بن الجراح&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. ʿAmr al-Bahili (d. 249/869). Cited 1,411 times (1,306 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/105 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). He is a Basran Hadith collector who settled in Baghdad. Mujahid’s (d. 104/722) exegetical opinions passed into the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; partly through him.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عمرو&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عمرو الباهلي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ibn ʿAbd al-Aʿla (d. 245/859–60). Cited 1,278 times (48 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,239 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Basra. Al-Tabari relies on him for Maʿmar’s collection of exegetical opinions from Qatada (a second major source of Qatada’s opinions alongside Bishr b. Muʿadh).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى الصنعانى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى الصنعاني&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى بن واصل&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عبد الأعلى الصنعانى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عبد الأعلى الصنعاني&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari was born in Amul in 224 or 225/838 or 9. Given the death dates of his top ten sources (whose average year of death was 252/866), he must have been very young – in his teens and twenties – when he gathered reports from most of them. This is consistent with the story biographers tell of al-Tabari’s ‘intellectual formation’ (to use Claude Gilliot’s term). After leaving home at the age of 12 he lived for around five years in Rayy before moving to Baghdad, where he spent about a year. Afterwards, he spent two years or somewhat less in southern Iraq (Wasit, Basra and Kufa) before returning to Baghdad for a further eight years. Then he embarked on what C. E. Bosworth called his ‘major educational and research journey’, which took him to Syria, Palestine and Egypt. He eventually landed back in Baghdad in 256/870, where he flourished as a scholar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His return to Bag̲h̲dād marked the end of his student &lt;em&gt;Wanderjahre&lt;/em&gt;, and he now settled down for the remaining fifty years of his life in order to devote himself to teaching and authorship, producing an amount of high-quality scholarship such as to evoke the admiration, in an age of prolific authors anyway, of both contemporaries and subsequent generations.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari’s biography thus supports the impression that he largely collected his information in the early period of his life. It is further corroborated by the information we can gather on his most frequently cited direct informants beyond the top ten: the average year of death for the top 100 is 256/869–70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the overall data set of 32,115 &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, the terms &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; begin an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; approximately 38% and 62% of the time, respectively. It seems that al-Tabari deliberately distinguished transmission to him, singly, from transmission to him as part of a group, since he made a point of using a specific term – either &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; – nearly exclusively for each direct informant listed above. Still, more work should be done to discern and interpret the patterns in his use of the terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It thus appears that al-Tabari encountered the major sources of the information he relied on in his books when he was young, long before he compiled his works. Such citation of much older persons is, of course, common and reflects the widespread desire to minimise the number of transmitters in an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (on the rationale that information flow is more reliable over fewer people). The terms he uses indicate that his learning occurred in group settings more often than it did in one-on-one situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we explain al-Tabari’s reproduction of this knowledge in books that he wrote as much as a half-century after his first exposure to the source material? How does he manage to quote, for example, nearly 3,000 reports (in our data set) from Muhammad b. Humayd, with whom he studied as a teen, in his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;? In the next blog post we argue that al-Tabari maintained a set of notebooks and put them to efficient and good use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Claude Gilliot, ‘La formation intellectuelle de Tabari (224/5–310/839–923)’, &lt;em&gt;Journal asiatique&lt;/em&gt; 276 (1988), 203–44; Akram Athari, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; (Amman and Cairo: n.p., 2005); and Scott C. Lucas, &lt;em&gt;Selections from the Comprehensive Exposition of the Interpretations of the Verses of the Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge: Royal Aal Al-Bayt Institute for Islamic Thought and Islamic Texts Society, 2017), esp. ii, 467–82 (‘Appendix B: Ṭabarī’s Teachers’). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The others were compositions by ʿAli b. Abi Talha, Mujahid, ʿAbd al-Rahman b. Zayd b. Aslam, and possibly Ibn Saʿd. Horst, ‘Zur Überlieferung im Korankommentar aṭ-Ṭabarīs’, &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift der deutschen morgenländischen Gesellschaft&lt;/em&gt; 103 (1953), 290–307, at 307. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jaques has spent more than ten years collecting evidence for the transmission of Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;. It seems unlikely to Jaques that al-Tabari copied the entirety of the text from Ibn Humayd’s audition. ‘It seems to me more likely that al-Tabari made, or had made, and was given a copy, of the text that Ibn Humayd got from Ibn al-Fadl.’ Personal communication, 4 September 2021. See also Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 6-7. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yaqut, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-ʿudabaʾ&lt;/em&gt;, ed. ʿUmar Faruq al-Tabbaʿ (Beirut: Muʼassasat al-Maʻarif: Dar Ibn Hazm, 1999), i, 520-1. The number should not be taken literally; the same figure is used for reports from Abu Kurayb. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;C. E. Bosworth, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’, &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam,&lt;/em&gt; 2nd ed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">This is the third in a series of blog posts examining al-Tabari’s (d. 310/923) citations in his Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk, Jāmiʿ al-bayān ʿan taʾwīl āy al-Qurʾān (Tafsir), and Tahdhib al-āthār. In the first and second posts we presented our questions, method and data set. The data set consists of six tables created iteratively using a series of analytical procedures developed by both of us and implemented by Masoumeh.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 1: Al-Tabari’s Direct Informants: Work on a New Data Set</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-1-Al-Tabari-s/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 1: Al-Tabari’s Direct Informants: Work on a New Data Set" /><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-1--Al-Tabari%E2%80%99s</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-1-Al-Tabari-s/">&lt;p&gt;In a series of eight blog posts, we share some results of experimental work on citations in three works by Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari (d. 310/923). These are his universal history, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;; his Quran commentary, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt;, an incomplete work on traditions, arranged according to the last transmitter of the Hadiths and also according to the Prophet’s Companions. All three are important works in their own fields and contain numerous citation chains (&lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s). These &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s provide a fascinating and previously untried opportunity for historians to understand his working methods.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-we-want&quot;&gt;What We Want&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three works, al-Tabari refers repeatedly to people who gave him information directly with the phrase ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Our goal was to use these citations to build up a picture of his working methods relevant to Arabic book history. Our specific questions were the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari’s books are full of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and give the general impression of a man on the move, gathering information from many corners. How big was his source base? In particular, how many people gave him information directly on a significant scale (we call these people ‘direct informants’)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What form might the material he obtained from these people have taken? The field generally now accepts the idea that notebooks played a major role in knowledge transmission, especially before al-Tabari’s lifetime. Al-Tabari rarely cites books – that is, works that circulated under specific titles. Do his books provide evidence of the use of notebooks?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To what extent do all three works rely on a common source base? Did al-Tabari reuse his own material, copying, for example, parts of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; into the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, or vice versa?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions address a larger set of issues in book history relating to the idea of the book and the form and evolution of the written Arabic tradition in the third/ninth century and beyond. A major argument running through these posts is that al-Tabari worked efficiently. The total word count of the three works considered here is 4.72 million words. But despite the size of his works and the number of citations in them, he relied heavily on a surprisingly small number of people as his sources. Another major argument is that he relied specifically on notes, collated into notebooks whose structure and content we can imagine in some detail, if not reconstruct precisely. His ability to recall information from these notebooks was critical to his compositional method. He compiled the notebooks in his youth using information he obtained from people with whom he spent significant periods of time. The material that found its way into his writing was (metaphorically) indexed to these people, his experiences with them and the writings that he carried with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book historians working on the third/ninth century struggle to make sense of what can seem a bewildering situation. We find references to works and authors from this period in, among others, the &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; of the bio-bibliographer Ibn al-Nadim (d. 385/995). But when we try to match a book to an author, we often find that the book took its final form only much later – perhaps after decades or more. Or we discover that when Ibn al-Nadīm refers to a person’s writings, he had in mind something smaller, or less permanent, than what we would today recognise as a book. The most frequently encountered situation is that a work mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; no longer survives, at least independently. More perplexingly, we find citations of authors in works that post-date the authors’ lifetimes, but with no references to actual books written by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we as historians describe the working habits of authors in this period, we may feel like the proverbial blind men, each trying to describe an elephant but able only to name a feature or two of it – be it ears, tail or skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than thirty years ago, Gregor Schoeler prompted us to think harder about the meaning of ‘book’, especially in the second/eighth and third/ninth centuries (Schoeler had predecessors, but his impact on the cohort of current historians has been unique). He distinguished an essentially private note set or notebook (&lt;em&gt;hypomnēma&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;hypomnēmata&lt;/em&gt;) from ‘actual books’, purposely crafted for publication to an audience of readers (&lt;em&gt;syngramma&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;syngrammata&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This important distinction supplanted the earlier perceived binary between the written and the oral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historians adopted Schoeler’s model and have used it particularly to describe the emergence and development of what for him were ‘actual books’. The third/ninth century is now frequently considered the period that witnessed the ‘rise of the Arabic book’ (as Beatrice Gruendler’s 2020 monograph is titled). Letizia Osti and James Weaver have made the important observation that from the second half of the third/ninth century onwards, books come to possess features that make them ‘increasingly usable for independent reading and study’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Division into topical chapters, hierarchical structuring, the use of section- and chapter-headings, detailed tables of contents within programmatic introductions, and alphabetically ordered lemmata, as well as regular cross-referencing, all enable the autonomous reader to navigate unfamiliar material with greater ease, to some extent perhaps facilitating consultation in addition to linear reading.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the third/ninth century no doubt witnessed changes towards the ‘well-organised book’, we would like to add a further layer of complexity by giving greater consideration to the personal side of writing. We believe that citations and text reuse data reveal that authors’ approaches to their writing were more diverse than we recognise today and that the types of authority that these approaches carried were also more varied than we currently imagine. We can perceive these features by examining al-Tabari’s citations and reading Ibn al-Nadim’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; alongside them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are convinced that further questions can productively be asked about the written Arabic tradition. The question we wish to pose is not whether a piece of writing constituted a published, redacted book but rather what forms did writing take, what evidence do we have of these forms in works that do survive and how might ideas about writing itself have contributed to the evolution of the tradition as it survives – including the loss and oblivion of many of its layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari was working with bounteous written materials – including, prominently, Quranic exegesis, historiography and Hadith – and these materials took many different forms. Many of them represented second- and third-generation offshoots of earlier writings, bundled together, as, for example, in the case of al-Tabari’s access to al-Madaʾini’s (d. ca. 224/839 or 228/842–3) historical material, studied by Ilkka Lindstedt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important question concerns the extent to which the situation in al-Tabari’s lifetime resembles that in later eras. Our data points to continuities in practice across the third/ninth century and indeed beyond, with later scholars citing al-Tabari personally, rather than his books, surprisingly often. The Arabic book thus seems to show continued reliance on earlier forms of written transmission, including those supported by aurality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the advancement of the field, we should seek to discern such continuities in writerly practice in later periods, in which writers relied on notes and blends of writing and aurality (as described, for example, by Konrad Hirschler).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This type of blended transmission was clearly critical for Hadith and the disciplines that supported it, but it appears that history writing, and perhaps other genres, too, shared these practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first blog post, we introduce our method; in the second, we present our data. Over the subsequent posts, we then consider each of the above questions as we demonstrate what al-Tabari’s citation practices reveal about the working habits of a major author in the late third/ninth and early fourth/tenth centuries and the shape of the material on which he relied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;method&quot;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari uses several terms to denote transmission of information from other people, but only a few of these terms indicate direct, personal contact. The phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;) at the beginning of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (citation chain) are by far the most common markers of such contact. We are most interested in the name that introduces the &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;, representing the transmitter closest to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd told me (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;) that Jarīr said that he was told by Mughira, from al-Musayyib b. Rafiʿ, that Abu Hurayra said: Abraham never lied, except on three occasions…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; with whom al-Tabari implies having had direct contact is Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862). That al-Tabari indeed had direct contact with Muhammad b. Humayd and the other individuals for whom he uses the ‘he told me’ phrases is supported by biographical works that discuss al-Tabari’s life. For example, al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (d. 463/1071) wrote that al-Tabari&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;heard (&lt;em&gt;samiʿa&lt;/em&gt;) Muhammad b. ʿAbd al-Malik b. Abi al-Shawarib, Ishaq b. Abi Israʾil, Ahmad b. Maniʿ al-Baghawi, Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi, Abu Hammam al-Walid b. Shujaʿ, Abu Kurayb Muhammad b. al-ʿAlaʾ, Yaʿqub b. Ibrahim al-Dawraqi, Abu Saʿid al-Ashajja, ʿAmr b. ʿAli, Muhammad b. Bashshar, Muhammad b. al-Muthanna, and a circle comprising many people like them from Iraq, Syria and Egypt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari cites all but one (Abu Saʿid al-Ashajja) of these people in his works using the ‘he told me’ phrases. However, although al-Khaṭīb mentioned only ten names, al-Tabari seems to identify hundreds of direct contacts. Further, al-Khatib may well have been relying on the very same evidence as we are for identifying al-Tabari’s direct informants. But even if he was, it would still be noteworthy that he interpreted the ‘he told me’ phrases in the same way as we do – as indicators of direct contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph 1: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; across al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. Graph designed by Peter Verkinderen and Masoumeh Seydi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frequency of this formula can be represented graphically. In Graph 1, the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; has been broken down into chunks of 1,513 characters – the average number of characters in a set of 300 word tokens in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (all books within the OpenITI corpus are divided into chunks of 300 word tokens, each marked by a numbered ‘milestone’ tag). The graph is thus like a great scroll on which the text is written with 1,513 characters per line. The top of the scroll is the graph’s left edge, and its bottom is the right edge. The location of each &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt; that starts with &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; is marked with a blue dot. Uses of the effectively synonymous expressions &lt;em&gt;akhbaranī&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;akhbaranā&lt;/em&gt; are marked with black dots. The red dots, meanwhile, indicate &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;s beginning with the passive-voice phrase &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;, ‘it is reported from’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of phrases that might point to direct transmission, the formula &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; is by far the most common. Al-Tabari does not use the phrase &lt;em&gt;samiʿtu&lt;/em&gt; (‘I heard’), for example, and the phrases &lt;em&gt;akhbarana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;akhbarani&lt;/em&gt; appear only rarely. Al-Tabari’s use of the passive ‘it is reported from’, which does not reveal his direct informant, is concentrated in the final part of the work, a phenomenon discussed in detail elsewhere.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Graph 2: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph 3: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We describe our data and the way we generated it in much more detail in our next blog post, but the following is a summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We went through each work and extracted &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;s that start with the &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula. The formula occurs 32,115 times across the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s are presented in a table entitled ‘Transmission Chains’ in our data set.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The style of writing and citation in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; differs from that in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. Generally speaking, al-Tabari’s more narrative style in the former invokes &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, but often refers back to them in oblique ways. Consequently, &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and other citations appear relatively less frequently in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, as the graphs above show.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;We extracted the names of transmitters from the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and put each in a separate cell in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;’s row. To identify and separate the names, we relied on a list of transmissive terms, first prepared by R. Kevin Jaques, plus a further list of words, such as ‘by him’ (&lt;em&gt;bi-hi&lt;/em&gt;), that appear in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s but are not part of names.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We created a unified list of authorities by normalising variants of each Arabic name to a single Latin-script version and listing the normalised names in a ‘Name Normalisation’ table. We also entered the normalised names into the Transmission Chains table.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We calculated the frequency of the name of each direct informant in each position within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and presented them as a ‘Direct Informants Position Frequencies’ table. This step helped us to diagnose data challenges involving names. Theoretically, these names should only appear in position 1. But that is not the case. For example, cases in which our extraction method failed to distinguish two &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, with the result that the same name occurred in two positions in the putative &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;. Or cases where the same name refers to two different people, only one of whom is a direct informant.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the above table, we created a ‘Direct Informants Overview’ table, which ranks al-Tabari’s direct informants by the frequency of his citation of them. It includes, for each informant, the normalised name, the total number of times the informant’s name appears across al-Tabari’s works, and the number of times it appears in each work. It also contains a cumulative count of citations and the cumulative percentage they represent of the total, which indicates the degree of al-Tabari’s reliance on his top informants. Finally, the table includes the informants’ death dates and the places in which each met al-Tabari according to secondary literature (which is also cited in the table).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we compiled a ‘Texts Name Counts’ table, which shows how many direct informants al-Tabari cites in each of his works and also how many are cited in two or all three of the works. This table is especially important for our final question, concerning the extent to which he relied on a common source base.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We analysed this data alongside text reuse data on overlaps between al-Tabari’s various writings and between his works and other, earlier and later works. Evidence of such alignments was particularly helpful for showing that al-Tabari was working with written materials, sometimes in precise ways but other times quite liberally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project is experimental and unfinished. We are able to obtain a lot of data relatively efficiently, but we know there is further evidence that can be harvested at a later point in time with refinements to our method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;previous-work&quot;&gt;Previous Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data we have examined opens a window on al-Tabari’s participation in a system involving students and teachers, speaking and note-taking, and the storage of material over decades. Our approach aims for the big picture. We want to determine how al-Tabari worked, to get a sense of the scale and likely form of his source base and to judge whether he used a common source base or relied on different direct informants for each of his works. Our overall goal is to expand and add nuance to our current understanding of book history in the third/ninth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ours is a picture of the forest rather than the trees. But our digital effort is part of a long tradition of tracing al-Tabari’s sources (who are often called his ‘teachers’, a blanket term that, we believe, overspecifies the relationship between al-Tabari and many of his direct informants, only some of whom fit the description of this role, whatever respect was owed to them because of their age in al-Tabari’s day). Attempts to identify the people with whom he had direct contact began in the centuries after his death, undertaken, for example, by al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (463/1071), Yaqut al-Hamawi (d. 626/1229), al-Dhahabi (d. 748/1348) and Ibn Hajar al-ʿAsqalani (d. 852/1449). According to Yaqut, al-Tabari wrote about the teachers with whom he studied (&lt;em&gt;samiʿa&lt;/em&gt;) in his &lt;em&gt;Kitab Dhayl al-mudhayyal&lt;/em&gt;. However, this section is not preserved in the ‘skimpy’ selection from the work that survives as &lt;em&gt;Muntakhab min Dhayl al-mudhayyal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The efforts at identification continued into the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, most recently with Ahmad Muhammad Shakir (d. 1958), Franz Rosenthal (d. 2003), Claude Gilliot, ʿAbd Allah b. ʿAbd al-Muhsin al-Turki, Scott Lucas and, most exhaustively, Akram b. Muhammad Athari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would be no forest without trees. We rely especially on Athari’s &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; for our Name Normalisation table. Athari’s work contains 475 numbered entries for names listed first in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. The book runs to more than 800 pages and features entries such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;129. Saʿid b. Numayr. From the tenth [generation]. I did not identify him, nor did I find a biographical entry (&lt;em&gt;tarjama&lt;/em&gt;) on him. Before me, Shaykh [Ahmad Muhammad] Shakir [also] passed over him. In his edition of the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt;, Shaykh [ʿAbdAllah] al-Turki named him, specifying that one of the manuscripts had [the name as] Saʿid b. ʿUmar. But he did not attempt to go further in his entry.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athari includes in his entries, to the best of his ability, the informants’ birth and death dates, the people from and to whom each informant transmitted and information on the informants’ reliability. He also specifies the generation (from the ninth to the eleventh) to which the informant belonged according to a &lt;em&gt;tabaqat&lt;/em&gt; schema, and he cites the sources of his information. It is important to note that he is not claiming to have found 475 &lt;em&gt;shuyukh&lt;/em&gt; for al-Tabari. Rather, his list comprises the ‘surface forms’ of the names that al-Tabari identifies as his sources as they appear in the text, regardless of whether these names can be connected to actual historical persons. The tenor of the above paragraph on Saʿid b. Numayr is common. The last fifty or so of Athari’s entries are on especially problematic surface forms and identities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athari has made considerable efforts to determine the identity of the people named by al-Tabari. Thanks to his investigation, for example, we know that two different names can refer to the same person, or that an apparent reference to a particular individual may in fact denote someone else when the ostensible referent lived before al-Tabari’s time, or that a name appears in the wrong form (such as ‘Yunus b. Sulayman al-Basri’ instead of the correct ‘Yusuf b. Salman al-Basri’). Atharī also notes variations between editions of the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital methods that we currently use cannot identify all of the named persons either, especially in cases in which we know nothing of an individual’s biography. Over these works’ long history, there have been plenty of chances for scribal errors and other changes to obscure identities and mix up the order of names in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a fuller discussion of the data, please read our second blog post, ‘Show Me the Data!’ Otherwise, stay tuned for Post 3, ‘How Many People Did al-Tabari Talk To?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the data set, see https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5533889. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gregor Schoeler, &lt;em&gt;The Genesis of Literature in Islam: From the Aural to the Read&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Shawkat M. Toorawa (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2009), 63. Schoeler’s distinction goes back to his 1985 &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; article, ‘Die Frage der schriftlichen oder mündlichen Überlieferung der Wissenschaften im frühen Islam’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 62 (1985), 201–30. For the phrase ‘actual books’, see his &lt;em&gt;The Oral and the Written in Early Islam&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Uwe Vagelpohl (London: Routledge, 2010). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Letizia Osti and James Weaver, ‘Organizing the Fourth/Tenth Century: Knowledge, Information, Tools’, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Abbasid Studies&lt;/em&gt; 7 (2020), 103–20, at 108. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lindstedt, ‘The Transmission of al-Madāʿinī’s Historical Material to al-Balādhurī and al-Ṭabarī: A Comparison and Analysis of Two &lt;em&gt;Khabar&lt;/em&gt;s’, in Sylvia Akar, Jaakko Hämeen-Anttila and Inka Nokso-Koivisto, eds, &lt;em&gt;Travelling Through Time: Essays in honour of Kaj Öhrnberg&lt;/em&gt; (Helsinki: Finnish Oriental Society, 2013), 41–63 and Lindstedt, ‘Al-Madāʾinī’, &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt;, 3rd ed. In the &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt; article, Lindstedt has also pointed out that in the two surviving works of al-Madāʾinī, ‘every narrative item is preceded by a chain of transmission mentioning his students and his students’ students’. This method of citation ‘arguably signifies that the works were redacted, and perhaps compiled into manuscript form, by students of al-Madāʾinī’. See also Lindstedt, ‘The Life and Deeds of ʿAlī b. Muḥammad al-Madāʾinī’, &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift für Geschichte der arabisch-islamischen Wissenschaften&lt;/em&gt; 20–21 (2012–14), 235–70; Lindstedt, ‘The Role of al-Madāʾinī’s Students in the Transmission of His Material’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 91/2 (2014): 295–340. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Konrad Hirschler, &lt;em&gt;The Written Word in the Medieval Arabic Lands: A Social and Cultural History of Reading Practices&lt;/em&gt; (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2012); Hirschler, &lt;em&gt;A Monument to Medieval Syrian Book Culture: The Library of Ibn ʿAbd al-Hādī&lt;/em&gt; (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2020). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh Baghdad&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, 0463KhatibBaghdadi.TarikhBaghdad.Shamela0000736-ara2.mARkdown, milestone (ms.) 0545. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the more technically minded: To produce this graph we defined regular expression patterns to find the transmissive terms &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;akhbarani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;akhbarana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;. We then searched for the terms in the text of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; to determine the character positions of those terms. We scaled the positions to the x- and y-axes of the graph, which represent the length of the text and the approximate length of the 300–word token chunks, respectively. To identify the beginnings of sections, we searched for the section headers (annotated through OpenITI mARkdown) and marked these with vertical lines. The script for doing this is available at https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5118900. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 89–90. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Akram Athari, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; (Amman and Cairo: n.p., 2005), 258, no. 129. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">In a series of eight blog posts, we share some results of experimental work on citations in three works by Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari (d. 310/923). These are his universal history, Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk; his Quran commentary, Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan (Tafsir) and the Tahdhib al-athar, an incomplete work on traditions, arranged according to the last transmitter of the Hadiths and also according to the Prophet’s Companions. All three are important works in their own fields and contain numerous citation chains (isnads). These isnads provide a fascinating and previously untried opportunity for historians to understand his working methods.1 For the data set, see https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5533889. &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>