<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-20T10:06:35+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">KITAB</title><subtitle>The Website for the KITAB project</subtitle><author><name>KITAB</name></author><entry><title type="html">OpenITI release 2021.2.5</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021-2-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OpenITI release 2021.2.5" /><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021-2-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/OpenITI-release-2021-2-5/">&lt;p&gt;The KITAB team has released a new version (2021.2.5) of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI&quot;&gt;OpenITI&lt;/a&gt; corpus at &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/5550338&quot;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;. The release is open access. It is our fifth release (second release in 2021). You can also access the release through our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release features 10,342 books, including all versions and editions (2,050,063,811 words), of which 6,337 are unique books written by 2,636 authors. In the release, 181 new ids have been added that reflect either new books, including OCRed books, which are assigned a new unique id, or changes to existing ids and corresponding URIs (resulting in new ids). In terms of structural annotation, 120 books have a new status, of which eighty-two are fully available in structural OpenITI mARkdown with a .mARkdown extension. Currently, there are 353 books in mARkdown, which have been reviewed and vetted by the annotation team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To access the major changes to the URIs as well as the statistics on the corpus, please see the release notes and the corresponding csv files at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/5550338&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE/tree/master/release_notes&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cite this version please include the following information (the bibliographical export is available at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3891466&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorenz Nigst, Maxim Romanov, Sarah Bowen Savant, Masoumeh Seydi and Peter Verkinderen, OpenITI: A Machine-Readable Corpus of Islamicate Texts (Version 2021.2.5) [data set] (October 2021), Zenodo, https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5550338.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="release" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="news" /><summary type="html">The KITAB team has released a new version (2021.2.5) of the OpenITI corpus at Zenodo. The release is open access. It is our fifth release (second release in 2021). You can also access the release through our GitHub repository.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/releases.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/releases.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 6: Sources Common to All of al-Tabari’s Works</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-6-Sources-Com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 6: Sources Common to All of al-Tabari’s Works" /><published>2021-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-6--Sources-Com</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-6-Sources-Com/">&lt;p&gt;The argument we are advancing in these blog posts is that when al-Tabari (d. 310/923) created his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt;, he relied on notes that were bound into notebooks of some kind, and we can reconstruct something of their contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We base our argument of the notebooks’ existence on practical evidence: the long interval between the time of writing and the time of his contact with the people he cites, the extensiveness of the citations (which would represent an astonishing feat of memory without written records) and the quick pace at which al-Tabari appears to have worked. There is also more direct evidence. This evidence consists of the citations themselves, including the ways in which they map onto probable notebooks, and of the alignments between all three books revealed by text reuse data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further point that emerges from our data set is the extent to al-Tabari appears to have gone back to the same sets of notes when composing each of his works. Let us look more closely at our data and numbers on this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewing all 849 names on our list of direct informants provides only a weak picture of sources common to the works. This list, as noted in an earlier post, contains many names that occur only once or twice in al-Tabari’s works, and the identities of many of them are uncertain. The list shows that al-Tabari relied on 347 direct informants for the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, 543 for the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and 342 for the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. Cross-checking pairs of these sub-lists shows that the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; have 139 direct informants in common, the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; have 110 in common and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; have 229 in common. All three works share 104 direct informants. These figures seem to suggest that he drew on many different sources and mostly used different sources for each work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the picture becomes more interesting when we focus on the smaller number of people on whom al-Tabari relied intensively. Recall that 51% of all of al-Tabari’s citations in our data set came from just eight people; twenty people accounted for 79% and fifty people for 89% of citations. It is these relatively few direct informants who mattered most to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By focusing on this small subset we get a clearer picture of al-Tabari’s working habits. Of the fifty direct informants cited most frequently, thirty-eight are cited in all three of his works. Of the top twenty, eighteen appear in all three, and each of the top ten is cited in each work. In other words, al-Tabari’s most important direct informants constituted his core source base for all three of his works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among these direct informants, there is a further subset consisting of people cited numerous times in each of the three works. The &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; took years to complete, and in the drawn-out writing process, the notes from these informants were al-Tabari’s go-tos and trusted favourites. In their case it seems especially probable that he had at his disposal stable notes bound together for easy reference and citation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Died&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tabari met in&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total count&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;*Count in *Tahdhib **&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;248/862&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Rayy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2879&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;457&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2126&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;296&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. Bashshar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;252/866&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Basra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1644&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1240&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;370&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Abu Kurayb&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;248/862&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kufa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1609&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;69&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1033&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;507&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. al-Muthanna&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;250/864&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Basra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1081&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;649&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;385&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: Four direct informants on whom al-Tabari relied heavily and whose material was likely preserved in well-organised notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among al-Tabari’s informants, Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862), Muhammad b. Bashshar (d. 252/866), Ab Kurayb (d. 248/862) and Muhammad b. al-Muthanna (d. 250/864) stand out. It is not hard to see why al-Tabari saw these individuals’ works as particularly worthy of careful collation and frequent citation. Muhammad b. Humayd transmitted Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;, an important source both for history (&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;) and for interpretation of the Qur’an (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;; he is also cited 296 times in the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; within our data set).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other figures are well-known Hadith scholars. Scott Lucas’s work on al-Tabari’s ‘teachers’ has shown that Hadiths from each of these three are cited in all six of the canonical Sunni Hadith collections (i.e. those of al-Bukhari, Muslim, Abu Dawud, al-Tirmidhi, al-Nasaʾi and Ibn Maja).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These numbers are of interest for our understanding of knowledge transmission in the third/ninth and fourth/tenth centuries and beyond. How did an author whose works mattered so much to posterity put together his very large works? Reliable materials mattered. And those that al-Tabari deemed reliable he returned to again and again in his works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our next post, we examine text reuse alignments between al-Tabari’s works, which also suggest a common source base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Scott C. Lucas, &lt;em&gt;Selections from the Comprehensive Exposition of the Interpretations of the Verses of the Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge: Royal Aal Al-Bayt Institute for Islamic Thought and Islamic Texts Society, 2017), esp. ii, 467–82 (‘Appendix B: Ṭabarī’s Teachers’). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">The argument we are advancing in these blog posts is that when al-Tabari (d. 310/923) created his Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk, Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan (Tafsir) and Tahdhib al-athar, he relied on notes that were bound into notebooks of some kind, and we can reconstruct something of their contents.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 5: Reconstructing al-Tabari’s Notebooks</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-5-Reconstruct/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 5: Reconstructing al-Tabari’s Notebooks" /><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-5--Reconstruct</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-5-Reconstruct/">&lt;p&gt;In our previous blog post, we argued that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) had to hand an extensive written collection consisting of sets of well-written notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we demonstrate that the data we have collected helps us begin to visualise the notebooks that served as al-Tabari’s ‘data carriers’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Scholars have often mined al-Tabari’s citations for evidence of earlier works. They have given the lion’s share of their attention to reputed authors such as Mujahid and Sayf b. ʿUmar who lived two or more generations before al-Tabari. By contrast, our starting point is his direct informants and the material they passed on to al-Tabari. In some cases, they combined material from many different sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tree-maps&quot;&gt;Tree Maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visualise al-Tabari’s notebooks using a tree map that was created from a subset of the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s introduced by the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;) – specifically, &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s with at least three transmitters after al-Tabari. The tree map displays each person in an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; as a rectangle; the size of the rectangle is proportional to the number of times the person is cited. Our main tree map contains four layers of rectangles: al-Tabari himself (dark pink), his direct informants (dark orange), their informants (light orange) and the latters’ informants (yellow). For example, in the first notebook, Bishr b. Muʿadh’s (d. 245/859–60) main source is Yazid b. Zariʿ (d. 182/798-9?). All but twenty of the 2,387 chains that contain three persons after al-Tabari run thus: Bishr b. Muʿadh &amp;lt; Yazid b. Zariʿ &amp;lt; Saʿid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to stress that our tree maps do not represent the entirety of the data set, only the subset that fits their parameters. A tree map focused on &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s containing three transmitters will exclude all &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that are shorter than three transmitters. Similarly, a tree map visualising &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s of at least five transmitters will exclude &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s with fewer than five, resulting in a smaller subset and a different tree map. Historians interested in the earliest layers of transmission may find the longer &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; tree maps particularly interesting, as they highlight chunks of material that seem to have passed through multiple generations to al-Tabari’s direct informants and on to him. But they should remember that the data set was created to prioritise al-Tabari’s direct informants, not transmitters five generations removed from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The images included here are excerpts from a larger set of tree maps that we will publish with our data set in a forthcoming print publication. Bibliographical information is collated from publications by Gilliot, Athari and Lucas,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as well as from Ibn Nadim’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; and the relevant &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt; articles. We have also consulted other sources.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;six-sets-of-notes&quot;&gt;Six Sets of Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is a series of visualisations of six possible – even likely – collections of notes used by al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 1: Bishr b. Muʿadh&lt;/strong&gt; (d. 245/859–60), cited 2,418 times, filtered to 2,387 chains of at least three transmitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 1: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes on his lessons with Bishr b. Muʿadh in Basra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari relies on Bishr b. Muʿadh chiefly for reports going back to an authority he calls Saʿid, transmitted via Yazid b. Zariʿ. Ibn al-Nadim mentions in his bio-bibliographical &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;em&gt;Kitab Saʿid b. Bashir ʿan Qatada&lt;/em&gt; within a list of compilations of Quran commentary (&lt;em&gt;tasmiyat al-kutub al-musannafa fi tafsir al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt;). Qatada b. Diʿama (d. ca. 117/735) was a ‘successor’, that is, he belonged to the generation of Muslims after the Prophet’s death. He was famed for his memory and his knowledge of genealogies, lexicography, historical traditions, Quranic exegesis, variant Quran readings (&lt;em&gt;qiraʾāt&lt;/em&gt;) and Hadith. As for Saʿid, Muhammad b. Saʿd (d. 230/845) has an entry for Abu ʿAbd al-Rahman Saʿid b. Bashir al-Azdi, who, he says, died in 170 (786 or 787 CE), at the start of Harun al-Rashid’s caliphate; he also mentions that Saʿid b. Bashir was from Basra but settled in Damascus. He quotes several reports from Qatada through Saʿid b. Bashir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that continue after Saʿid, we indeed find that nearly all go back to Qatada. But can we be sure that the Saʿīd who passed on material from Qatada was it Saʿid b. Bashir? We cannot. Al-Tabari received reports from Qatada through several routes, including via a transmitter he names explicitly as Saʿīd b. Bashīr and another he calls Saʿīd b. Abī ʿUrūba, who may or may not be the same person. It is perhaps significant that when he refers specifically to Saʿid b. Bashir as a source for Qatada, his direct informant was not Bishr b. Muʿadh but rather a variety of other people (as many as nine). This means that we cannot be certain that there is only one Saʿīd who reported from Qatada or that al-Tabari received material from Saʿid b. Bashir through Bishr b. Muʿadh .&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is where further work on named entities would be particularly useful. We can say, however, that whatever the origin of its contents, al-Tabari’s Bishr b. Muʿadh notebook contained a lot of material from Qatada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari used this notebook mainly for the &lt;em&gt;Jāmiʿ al-bayān&lt;/em&gt;, but he also picked it up for the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and a few times for the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. The citations from it in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; all occur early in the book, with the last (at milestone 984) being found in al-Tabari’s reporting on the sixth year of the hijra. The sixth year is when the Prophet attempted to return to Mecca to make the lesser pilgrimage (&lt;em&gt;ʿumra&lt;/em&gt;) and ended up concluding the accord of al-Hudaybiyya (March 628). Al-Tabari cites Bishr as one of several sources on the events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 2: Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi&lt;/strong&gt; (d. 248/862), cited 2,879 times, filtered to 2,312 chains of at least three transmitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 2: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes on his lessons with Muhammad b. Humayd in Rayy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the frequency of citation, the notes al-Tabari obtained from Muhammad b. Humayd were by far the most important for the former’s works. Given the large number of quotations from these notes, they may have occupied numerous books or booklets. In biographical literature, Muhammad b. Humayd is well-known as a transmitter of Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; through the intermediary Salama b. al-Fadl, and it is likely that the material he transmitted from Ibn Ishaq was bound together. In this case, the difference between such notebooks versus a ‘book’ obtained through an &lt;em&gt;ijāza&lt;/em&gt; may have been slight. The data rightly challenges us to think harder not just about ‘actual books’ but also about the concept of notes and notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In writing the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, our data would say that al-Tabari relied almost exclusively on the notes from Muhammad b. Humayd for Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But for his other works he drew also on other notebooks containing material from the &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;, especially those of Abu Kurayb (d. 248/862), Yaʿqub b. Ibrāhim al-Dawraqi (d. 252/866), and Sufyan b. Wakiʿ (d. 247/861), as well as at least seven others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the large number of citations represented in this tree map, we might imagine that the material al-Tabari obtained from Jarir b. ʿAbd al-Hamid, Mihran b. Abi ʿUmar and Abu Tamila Yahya b. Saʿid would likewise have been bound. But how these notebooks would have been stored within al-Tabari’s own shelving system is another question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all material transmitted by Mihran from ‘Sufyan’ is quoted in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; from Sura 41 (‘Fussilat’) onwards; this is most likely a collection of the exegetical opinions of Sufyan al-Thawri (d. 161/778). Al-Tabari also cites other direct informants for Sufyan al-Thawri’s opinions, including Yunus b. ʿAbd al-Aʿla (d. 264/877), Abu Kurayb (d. 248/862), and al-Harith b. Muhammad (d. 282/895), as well as the chains Muhammad b. Humayd &amp;lt; Salama b. al-Fadl &amp;lt; Sufyan and Muhammad b. Humayd &amp;lt; Harun &amp;lt; Sufyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be worthwhile to compare the fragmentary Quran commentary attributed to Sufyan&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;. We have not done this. But we do have a machine-readable &lt;em&gt;tafsir&lt;/em&gt; text attributed to Sufyan al-Thawri in the OpenITI corpus (under identifier Shia002462; 29,140 words),&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which has twelve short alignments with al-Tabari’s text; the longest of these measures sixty-one words.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 3: Al-Muthanna b. Ibrahim al-Amuli&lt;/strong&gt; (d. unknown), cited 2,259 times, filtered to 1,973 chains of at least three people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 3: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes from his lessons with al-Muthanna in Rayy (possibly Amul also).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notes that al-Tabari assembled from al-Muthanna b. Ibrahim al-Amuli are quite diverse, with the largest pieces deriving from transmitters named Ishaq b. al-Hajjaj and Abu Salih ʿAbd Allah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter appears in Ibn al-Nadim’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; as Abu Salih ʿAbd Allah b. Muhammad b. Yazdad b. Suwayd (d. 223/837-8). Ibn al-Nadim calls him an eloquent scribe (&lt;em&gt;ahad al-kuttab al-bulaghaʾ&lt;/em&gt;) and attributes to him a &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and a book of epistles (&lt;em&gt;Kitab rasaʾilihi&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari refers to him in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; as ‘the scribe of al-Layth’ (&lt;em&gt;katib al-Layth&lt;/em&gt;); al-Layth appears within the tree map, too. This seems to refer to the famous traditionist and &lt;em&gt;faqih&lt;/em&gt; al-Layth b. Saʿd (d. 175/791).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Abu Salih ʿAbd Allah also transmitted from Muʿawiya b. Salih. In our &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, Muʿawiya’s reporting goes back to Ibn ʿAbbas through ʿAli b. Abi Talha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Zychowicz-Coghill has recently collected witnesses to a &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; by al-Layth on the basis of a recension by Yunus b. Bukayr that is quoted in five other texts. He argues that al-Tabari did not draw on al-Layth’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, our data reveals additional evidence in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; that contradicts his contention. Al-Layth is in fact cited in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, but through other &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s (and not, according to our data, through Yunus b. Bukayr).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Layth’s situation is complex, and readers will be forgiven if they find it a bit hard to follow. For us, the most important feature of it is that it allows us to discern how works that Ibn al-Nadim may have recognised as written works were broken down before al-Tabari’s lifetime, absorbed into subsequent writings, and then reabsorbed into al-Tabari’s book. This process seems to have carried memories of earlier works and their conservators (e.g. the reference to &lt;em&gt;katib al-Layth&lt;/em&gt;) but without either citing the works themselves or making an effort to keep them intact. That is why reconstructions are so tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of al-Tabari and, indeed, text reuse data in general, confirm what Beatrice Gruendler has recently argued, which is that in the third/ninth century (as well as beyond) the authorial agency of scholars such as al-Tabari was often exerted through acts of ‘memorizing, collecting, arranging, commenting, and transmitting of pre-existing sources’. As she writes, ‘This dealing with extant text made a scholar no less of an author in the eyes of his contemporaries, as he provided a repository of the knowledge that they needed.’ Gruendler distinguishes between different types of authorial agency. In poetry, authorship was recognised in the creation of a text, and a ‘basic difference already existed between a “ripped off” verbatim formulation and a borrowed reformulated motif’. In the case of poetry, ‘word-by-word’ copying was frowned on, though ‘a degree of reformulation changed the discourse from ownership to literary inspiration’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we step back, we can understand these two forms of agency as part of a wider epistemology, which attributed greater prestige to adaptation than to simple, perfect reproduction. The reproduction of a work – as a &lt;em&gt;katib&lt;/em&gt; – did not initiate one into the genealogy of a master, whereas a student’s transmission of a teacher’s work (as a &lt;em&gt;rawi&lt;/em&gt; or otherwise) incorporated the student’s persona into the text’s lineage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hierarchy of prestige can be detected in al-Tabari’s citations. Consider the following examples, which indicate al-Tabari’s efforts to track specific pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebooks 4 and 5:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ismaʿil b. ʿAbd al-Rahman al-Suddi&lt;/strong&gt; (d. ca. 127/745) via &lt;strong&gt;Musa b. Harun al-Hamdani&lt;/strong&gt; (d. unknown) and &lt;strong&gt;Muhammad b. al-Husayn&lt;/strong&gt; (d. 261/874), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 4: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes from his lessons with Musa b. Harun al-Hamdani (d. unknown) and Muhammad b. al-Husayn (d. 261/874).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The direct informants here are the obscure Musa b. Harun and Muhammad b. al-Husayn al-Baghdadi, a Hadith scholar from Nisa in modern-day Turkmenistan). Both transmit through different intermediaries (ʿAmr vs. Ahmad) from Asbat b. Nasr al-Hamdani, who in turn transmits from al-Suddi, a &lt;em&gt;mawla&lt;/em&gt; who was a popular preacher in Kufa. In both cases, al-Suddi’s ‘box’ (that is, the material he provided) is neatly nested inside Asbat’s. However, the material from al-Suddī accounts for less than half of the three-person &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s from either Musa b. Harun (who starts a total of 508 chains) and or Muhammad b. al-Husayn (who starts 528).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examining these citations, G. H. A. Juynbol questioned the degree to which the material attributed to al-Suddi could be used to understand his views: ‘In al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, countless exegetical remarks ascribed to al-&lt;em&gt;Suddi&lt;/em&gt; can be found and could conceivably be brought together in a volume. Whether such a compilation would allow conclusions as to a certain bias or predilection on his part, if any, has as yet to be established.’ Ibn al-Nadīm does indeed mention a &lt;em&gt;Kitab Tafsir al-Suddi&lt;/em&gt; within the section, mentioned above, that lists compilations of Quranic commentary (&lt;em&gt;tasmiyat al-kutub al-musannafat fi tafsir al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notebook 6: ʿAbd Allah b. al-ʿAbbas&lt;/strong&gt; (d. ca. 68/687–8) via Muhammad b. Saʿd (d. 276/889).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 5: The possible structure of al-Tabari’s notes on information received through a family &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; from Muhammad b. Saʿd (d. 276/889) in Baghdad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari met Muhammad b. Saʿd b. Muhammad b. al-Hasan b. ʿAtiyya b. Saʿd b. Junada al-ʿAwfi in Baghdad. The information he received from the latter originates with ʿAbd Allah b. al-ʿAbbas (d. ca. 68/687–8), a member of the first generation of Muslims who is frequently called the father of Quranic exegesis. The full chain, in which the description of family relations reflects the respective quoted speaker’s perspective, runs as follows: Muhammad b. Saʿd &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;abi&lt;/em&gt; [‘my father’] &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;ʿammi&lt;/em&gt; [‘my paternal uncle’, i.e. Muhammad b. Saʿd’s great-uncle] &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;abihi&lt;/em&gt; [‘his father’, i.e. the great-uncle’s father] &amp;lt; Ibn ʿAbbas. Franz Rosenthal described al-Tabari’s material from Muhammad b. Saʿd as an ‘unpublished’ book and ‘the heirloom of a particular family’ and noted that ‘a family &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; as complete as this is most remarkable’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that although generating our data was challenging, once generated it is relatively easy to read. Filtering the data in the Transmission Chains table to order the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s alphabetically by the name in position 5, for example, reveals numerous identical &lt;em&gt;isnads&lt;/em&gt; running back to Ibn ʿAbbas. The interpretation of these &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s will, of course, remain a subject of debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Limits of Our Argument&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholars such as Lawrence Conrad, Andrew Rippin, Ella Landau-Tasseron and Arietta Papaconstantinou have rightly raised questions about efforts to reconstruct lost sources.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There is an understandable concern in the field about the risks associated with mining later sources for evidence of earlier ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work is a comparatively modest effort. Our primary focus is on what al-Tabari had to hand, not on whether any given chunk of material can in fact be traced back to Umayyad times. We make no judgement, for example, about whether the Ibn ʿAbbas notebook actually goes back to the man himself. Indeed, we are sceptical that the notebooks can be reconstructed. Instead, they can be described, given that we possess only extracts from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the earlier layers, we are also generally sceptical about the possibility of reconstructing ‘actual books’ from earlier time periods on the basis of quotations and citations found in works that survive today. Our scepticism arises from the fact that authors treated their notes as reusable materials. Now that technology can aid us in new ways, further work on assessing alignments will be worthwhile, but we should be searching for more nuanced ways to describe what we find. What was the nature of these earlier works? Corpora of quotations can be collected and described and sketches of the early written tradition developed on the basis of this evidence, as Kevin Jaques is doing for Ibn Ishaq and as Zychowicz-Coghill has done for al-Layth b. Saʿd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our main bone of contention with efforts at reconstruction that mine later sources for earlier works is that they often give little or no attention or agency to the persons we call al-Tabari’s direct informants. Al-Tabari drew on a material reality that had its own form and organisation. Broadly speaking, our work reflects the field’s rising attention to the materiality of texts, although we do not work with manuscripts. Rather, we direct our attention to where the material has vanished but direct citations of it remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our next post, we compare al-Tabari’s books and investigate how different notebooks fed into different works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Beatrice Gruendler, &lt;em&gt;The Rise of the Arabic Book&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2020), 67. Maxim Romanov has made this argument for al-Dhahabi’s (d. 748/1348) &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-Islam&lt;/em&gt;; see e.g. Romanov, ‘Observations of a Medieval Quantitative Historian?’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 94/2 (2017), 462–95, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1515/islam-2017-0028&quot;&gt;[https://doi.org/10.1515/islam-2017-0028]{.ul}&lt;/a&gt;, at 482ff. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Claude Gilliot, ‘La formation intellectuelle de Tabari (224/5–310/839–923)’, &lt;em&gt;Journal asiatique&lt;/em&gt; 276 (1988), 203–44; Akram Atharī, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyūkh al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt; (Amman and Cairo: n.p., 2005); and Scott C. Lucas, &lt;em&gt;Selections from the Comprehensive Exposition of the Interpretations of the Verses of the Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge: Royal Aal Al-Bayt Institute for Islamic Thought and Islamic Texts Society, 2017), esp. ii, 467–82 (‘Appendix B: Ṭabarī’s Teachers’). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;E.g. Muhammad S. H. Hallaq, &lt;em&gt;Rijal Tafsir al-Tabari, jarhan wa-taʿdilan: Min tahqiq Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan li-Ahmad Shakir wa-Mahmud Shakir&lt;/em&gt; (Beirut: Dar Ibn Hazm, 1999). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cf. Athari, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt;, 159. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;R. Kevin Jaques has assembled a list of persons upon whom al-Tabari relied for Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;, plus locations within the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sufyan al-Thawri, &lt;em&gt;Tafsir al-Qurʾan al-karim&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Imtiyaz ʿAli ʿArshi (Rampur: n.p., 1965). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This work was published as &lt;em&gt;Tafsir al-Thawri&lt;/em&gt;, edited by ‘a committee (&lt;em&gt;lajna&lt;/em&gt;) of &lt;em&gt;ʿulamaʾ&lt;/em&gt;’, in 1403 AH [1982–3 CE]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The alignments are available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.kitab-project.org/passim01022021/Shia002462-ara1/Shia002462-ara1_Shamela0007798-ara1.inProgress.csv&quot;&gt;[http://dev.kitab-project.org/passim01022021/Shia002462-ara1/Shia002462-ara1_Shamela0007798-ara1.inProgress.csv]{.ul}&lt;/a&gt; (included in the data set associated to these blogs). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari refers to al-Layth b. Saʿd (also as al-Layth b. Saʿd al-Misri), but in our data set this name never appears in the al-Muthanna &amp;lt; ʿAbd Allah chains, which refer only to ‘al-Layth’. Al-Tabari may well have maintained in his citations the different surface forms of names that he had recorded in his notes. Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (d. 463/1071) describes an ʿAbd Allah b. Saliḥ b. Muhammad b. Muslim Abu Salih as an Egyptian who was the &lt;em&gt;katib al-Layth b. Saʿd&lt;/em&gt; and who accompanied the latter to Baghdad. The names here do not quite match (ʿAbd Allah b. Muhammad versus ʿAbd Allah b. Salih). See al-Khatib al-Baghdadi, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh Baghdad&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, Shamela0000736-ara2.mARkdown, search term: كاتب الليث. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Edward Zychowicz-Coghill, &lt;em&gt;The First Arabic Annals: Fragments of Umayyad History&lt;/em&gt; (Berlin: de Gruyter, 2021), 3. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gruendler, &lt;em&gt;Rise of the Arabic Book&lt;/em&gt;, 60–2. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 6 and 215, n. 337. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lawrence Conrad, ‘Recovering Lost Texts: Some Methodological Issues’, &lt;em&gt;Journal of the American Oriental Society&lt;/em&gt; 113/2 (1993), 258–63; Andrew Rippin, ‘&lt;em&gt;Tafsir Ibn ʿAbbās&lt;/em&gt; and Criteria for Dating Early &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; Texts’&lt;em&gt;, Jerusalem Studies in Arabic and Islam&lt;/em&gt; 18 (1994), 38–83; Ella Landau-Tasseron, ‘On the Reconstruction of Lost Sources’, &lt;em&gt;al-Qanṭara&lt;/em&gt; 25 (2004), 45–91; Arietta Papaconstantinou, review of Robert Hoyland, &lt;em&gt;Theophilus of Edessa’s Chronicle and the Circulation of Historical Knowledge in Late Antiquity and Early Islam&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Le Muséon&lt;/em&gt; 126 (2013), 459–65. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">In our previous blog post, we argued that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) had to hand an extensive written collection consisting of sets of well-written notes.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi5/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 4: The Form of al-Tabari’s Sources: His Probable Notebooks</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-4-The-Form-of/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 4: The Form of al-Tabari’s Sources: His Probable Notebooks" /><published>2021-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-4--The-Form-of</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-4-The-Form-of/">&lt;p&gt;In the preceding posts, we showed that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) used the phrases ‘he told me’ and ‘he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;) in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt; to indicate people from whom he had obtained information directly. He mentions hundreds of people in this manner – but a very small subset of them accounts for the majority of his citations. Al-Tabari’s three works contain a vast amount of material from direct informants, and most of that material came into his possession early in his life, a long time before he composed his books. It is our contention that al-Tabari made use of an extensive written record to preserve and organise his material over the decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-notes&quot;&gt;Why Notes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This contention may be met with scepticism. One might argue that al-Tabari memorised the information he obtained from his informants and could recall it without the need for written aids. Memorisation of reports was a culturally valued skill in his time. However, there are five main reasons to think that he in fact drew on well-written and well-organised notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The long time – as much as half a century – that had elapsed between his contact with the sources and his writing (see the previous post).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The extensiveness of the citations. There are thousands of pieces of information from different informants scattered across thousands of pages of his works. Citation chains featuring direct informants alternate with other citation chains, disappear for hundreds of pages and then reappear. The feats of medieval memory defy our imagination today, and we do well not to underestimate its role and importance. But the rote recall and deft manipulation of purely oral information on such a scale does seem highly unlikely. A model of memory operating like an index is more plausible: al-Tabari had an extensive mental map of his data, which allowed him to locate what he needed in his notes as he created his own works, drawing on, but not merely reproducing, earlier writings with their own forms. All three of his works are highly structured, by chronology (&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;), Quranic chapters (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) or early traditionists (&lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari’s memory feat was to map the contents of these earlier works, with their own forms, into his own.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The efficiency of al-Tabari’s work. Much of the material he incorporated into his own works may already have been systematically arranged along lines similar to the structure of his own works. But his fast writing pace can also be explained by a well-organised collection of written material – that is, notebooks that he had compiled in specific times and contexts during his youth and that he returned to again and again. The most often used notebooks, based on notes collected from only a few persons, a crucial role for al-Tabari. He relied heavily on them as well as on other written sources, including another written source, whose extensive reuse by al-Tabari can be detected in our data (though he does not cite the work).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The regular citation of the same transmission chains pointing back to earlier written works. Al-Tabari relied substantially on information from individuals who lived before him, many of whom are reported to have written books of their own. Although he could not have met these people in person, his most important direct informants provided him with access, possibly only lightly mediated, to these earlier compositions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The three works’ close (though not exact) alignments with other surviving texts, including al-Tabari’s own. When using earlier texts, he appears to have made adjustments to them to fit the thematic interests of his own books.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal already noted al-Tabari’s probable use of notebooks as well as the scarcity of his citations of actual books by others. He concluded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There can be no doubt that the ‘I was told’ and ‘we were told’ at the opening of chains of transmitters have as a rule to be taken literally as indicating direct personal contact or contact within the setting of public lectures and instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosenthal nonetheless discerned a pretence of orality in al-Tabari’s citations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It must also be assumed that he often referred to someone with whom he undoubtedly had some personal contact, but later, he used the source that was transmitted to him by that individual in its written (published) form and quoted from it while pretending all the time to rely upon oral transmission.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our view, it is more reasonable to read al-Tabari’s citations with &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; as explicit acknowledgement of material that he received orally and recorded in his notes and notebooks. By using these distinctive phrases (and differentiating them from phrases such as &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;), he was emphasising that the transmission took place through personal contact, which was considered more prestigious and more authoritative than transmission of written material alone. From al-Tabari’s perspective, he was saying exactly what he was doing; there was no pretence involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregor Schoeler’s depiction of aurality among Muslim writers of the third/ninth century may partly explain al-Tabari’s learning situation. As noted in our first blog post, in his discussion of forms of writing in this period, Schoeler distinguished between essentially private notes and notebooks (&lt;em&gt;hypomnēmata&lt;/em&gt;, sing. &lt;em&gt;hypomnēma&lt;/em&gt;), on the one hand, and ‘actual books, composed and redacted according to the canon of stylistic rules, and intended for publication’ (&lt;em&gt;syngrammata&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;syngramma&lt;/em&gt;), on the other. The Arabic tradition refers to both types as books (&lt;em&gt;kutub&lt;/em&gt;, sing. &lt;em&gt;kitāb&lt;/em&gt;). Before the third/ninth century, the conventions that would later mark a ‘published’ book had not yet crystallised, and accordingly many books written in that period do not survive, while others, such as the &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; of Ibn Ishaq and the &lt;em&gt;Muwaṭṭaʾ&lt;/em&gt; of Malik b. Anas, survive in multiple variant versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book historians have identified the third/ninth century as a turning point at which &lt;em&gt;syngrammata&lt;/em&gt; began to flourish. Most recently, Beatrice Gruendler has painted a detailed picture of this century, in which books appeared as ‘new media’. Al-Tabari’s numerous and extensive writings represent a milestone that ought to be considered in any periodisation of book history. It is hard to imagine them coming into existence fifty years earlier, when he was still a student and the ‘rise of the Arabic book’ was only beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But did scholars such as al-Tabari view the materials at their disposal in strictly binary terms – as either notes/notebooks or ‘actual books’ or, to put it differently, as either ‘published’ or unpublished works? Al-Tabari gives little indication of such binary thinking in his citations. We might look for a distinction in how he cites people (whose information he recorded as notes) versus how he cites redacted books (which he accessed without direct contact with the authors). But he only rarely acknowledges books as his sources. Even when he cites someone known to have authored a relevant book, he usually fails to mention the work in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when citing reports from Sayf b. ʿUmar (d. during the reign of al-Rashid, r. 170–93/786–809), al-Tabari repeatedly uses phrasing that suggests he accessed Sayf’s work in the form of written material acquired by al-Sari, who himself relied on Shuʿayb (&lt;em&gt;wa-amma al-Sari, fa-innahu qala fi kitabihi ilayya&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;haddathana Shuʿayb ʿan Sayf&lt;/em&gt; …).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Modern scholars, mostly basing their discussions on al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, have speculated about the nature of Sayf’s work, which no longer survives, primarily for the purpose of assessing its reliability (or lack thereof) as a source for the events it relates.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The title &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Futuh al-kabir wa-l-ridda&lt;/em&gt; as the name of Sayf’s lost work does not appear in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;; its widespread use and attribution today appear to derive from Ibn al-Nadim’s (d. 385/995) &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that what is required for a more nuanced understanding of al-Tabari’s work and the literary culture of his time is deeper probing of the variety of written forms that existed and were likely to be used by people such as al-Tabari. What forms might notes have taken? What sorts of ways of binding material together can we imagine? It may have been conventional within &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s to mention individuals and not their works, but what does this convention tell us about how authors such as al-Tabari thought about the works at their disposal and what they could expect in terms of the treatment of their own works afterwards?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line of enquiry requires an openness to the many ways in which al-Tabari and his peers might have constructed and conceived of their own works. It could have the effect of demoting ‘actual books’ as the main, privileged carriers of information in the third/ninth and fourth/tenth centuries and beyond.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Therefore, we would do well to broaden our understanding of authorship to include many forms of writing and writerly culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aligning-al-tabaris-books&quot;&gt;Aligning al-Tabari’s Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence of text reuse in al-Tabari’s works indicates that he drew repeatedly on the same written sources in his writings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 1. An excerpt from a longer alignment (displayed furthest to the right, with the excerpt circled in red) between passages based on Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (on the right; OpenITI, Shamela0009783, milestones 596–604) and in his &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (on the left; OpenITI, Shamela0007798, milestones 9635–41). Text found only in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; is highlighted in green; text found only in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; is highlighted in blue. The long green block comes from Hisham b. Muhammad al-Kalbi. Alignment generated with Ryan Muther’s adaptation of David Smith’s passim software and fed into the OpenITI Diff viewer application (created by Peter Verkinderen, who also designed the way to visualise the location of the excerpt within the whole).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alignment shown on the far right side of Image 1 covers ten consecutive pages in the Leiden edition of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and almost the same in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is one of the longest alignments between the two works. Looking at it gives the impression that one is seeing the seams that run between and link the works. The passages overlap very closely, but they have slight wording differences that could reflect al-Tabari’s own different readings of the text that he received from Muhammad b. Humayd in Rayy while in his teens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closeness of the two texts is evident in the very first sentences in the alignment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;: He [Ibn Ishaq] said: Abraha then built al-Qalis (or al-Qullays) in Sanʿaʾ. He built a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) unlike any seen on earth in its time. Afterwards, he wrote to the Negus, the king of the Abyssinians, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;O king! I have built for you a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) the like of which has never been built for any king before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;: He [Salama b. al-Fadl] said: Ibn Ishaq told us (&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;) that Abraha built a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) in Sanʿaʾ. He was Christian and called it (&lt;em&gt;sammaha&lt;/em&gt;) al-Qalis (or al-Qullays). It was unlike any seen on earth in its time. He wrote to the Negus, the king of the Abyssinians, saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;O king! I have built for you a church (&lt;em&gt;kanisa&lt;/em&gt;) the like of which has never been built for any king before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For al-Tabari, the account of the building of the church in Sanʿaʾ may have been a familiar story, one that he taught regularly in his afternoon teaching sessions in Baghdad. When he sat down to compose the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, the text of this story was well known to him; it was alive in his memory. Writing it down may have been akin to singing for him, insofar as he had internalised the text down to the level of the words and so could improvise when addressing his audience. In the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, he seems to have added the clarification that Abraha was a Christian and that the church he built was called al-Qalis (or al-Qullays). The beginning of the story is thus similar but not identical in the two texts, but when quoting the Negus’s letter al-Tabari appears to have returned to his notes to ensure verbatim accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both reports rely on a transmission chain that ran from his direct informant, Muhammad b. Humayd (d. 248/862), through Salama b. al-Fadl (d. after 190/805-6) to Ibn Ishaq (d.c. 151/768), though the chain is cited explicitly in connection with this story only in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, al-Tabari gives the chain earlier in the text, at the beginning of the overall narrative, without repeating it thereafter). It is likely that the clarification in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; was added by al-Tabari himself, though we cannot know for sure without access to the notes themselves. It is also possible that the clarification was already present in al-Tabari’s notes, or that both texts differ slightly from the text recorded in the notes. Or that a copyist or copyists were involved along the way. We do not, at present, have an earlier, independent text of Ibn Ishaq’s work against which to compare al-Tabari’s version, but a cursory look at text reuse data for this passage in works written after al-Tabari’s lifetime suggests that the version in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; aligns more closely with other transmissions of Ibn Ishaq’s text than does the version in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of al-Tabari’s notes would have been thoroughly familiar to him, but others he would have known less well, perhaps because he never taught from them, even if he drew on them for his works. Infrequently recalled material – like a melody one has heard only once or twice long ago, to continue the singing metaphor – would not lend itself so easily to improvisation or expansion. It is possible that the many much shorter and often very precise alignments between al-Tabari’s works reflect instances in which he reproduced such less familiar material from his notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of his long and illustrious career, al-Tabari was extraordinarily productive in several different fields, including Quran commentary, history and law (in his catalogue of authors, Ibn al-Nadim places him in the chapter on &lt;em&gt;ʿulamaʾ&lt;/em&gt;). We might reasonably speculate that al-Tabari copied parts of his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; into his &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, or vice versa. That would have been efficient. But the text reuse data indicates that that is not how he generally worked. Instead, it seems that he went back to the same sources again and again in the course of composing each of his works. We examine the alignments between his works more closely in a later post, when we consider his reliance on notebooks for his three major works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Discussed in Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 5–6 (citing Yaqut); see also 52-4. Heribert Horst has also argued that al-Ṭabarī’s sources were mostly lecture notes, written down as an aide-mémoire. He examined a large number of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and concluded that al-Tabari relied on only four or five ‘complete books’ (&lt;em&gt;vollständige Bücher&lt;/em&gt;), by ʿAli b. Abi Ṭalha, Mujahid, ʿAbd al-Rahman b. Zayd b. Aslam, Ibn Ishaq and possibly Ibn Saʿd. Horst, ‘Zur Überlieferung im Korankommentar aṭ-Ṭabarīs’, &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift der deutschen morgenländischen Gesellschaft&lt;/em&gt; 103 (1953), 290–307, at 307. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See, for example, al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, Shamela0009783BK1-ara1.completed, ms. 1302. R. Stephen Humphreys translates this phrase as ‘It was transmitted to me in writing by al-Sarī.’ See al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, xv: &lt;em&gt;The Crisis of the Early Caliphate:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Reign of ʿUt̲h̲mān&lt;/em&gt;, trans. R. S. Humphreys (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1990), 47. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a still-useful summary of the scholarly treatment of Sayf, see Ella Landau-Tasseron, ‘Sayf ibn ʿUmar in Medieval and Modern Scholarship’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 67 (1990), 1–26. See also F. M. Donner, ‘Sayf b. ʿUmar’, in &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd ed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ibn al-Nadim, &lt;em&gt;al-Fihrist&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, 0385.Fihrist.Shia003355-ara1.mARkdown, search term: سيف بن عمر. It is also noteworthy that the plural term الفتوح occurs only sixteen times in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a related discussion, see Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘People vs. Books’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, ed. M. J. de Goeje et al., 15 vols in 3 series (Leiden: E. J. Brill, 1879–1901), i, 934–45; al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, v: &lt;em&gt;The Sasanids, the Byzantines, the Lakhmids, and Yemen&lt;/em&gt;, trans. C. E. Bosworth (Leiden: Brill, 1999), 217–35; al-Ṭabarī, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan&lt;/em&gt;, ed. ʿAbd Allah b. ʿAbd al-Muḥsin al-Turki ([N.p.]: [Dar Hijr li-l-Tabaʿa wa-l-Nashr wa-l-Tawaziʿ wa-l-Iʿlan], 2001), xxiv, 636–44. See also al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, v: &lt;em&gt;The Sasanids, the Byzantines, the Lakhmids, and Yemen&lt;/em&gt;, trans. C. E. Bosworth (Leiden: Brill, 1999), 217–35. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">In the preceding posts, we showed that al-Tabari (d. 310/923) used the phrases ‘he told me’ and ‘he told us’ (haddathani/haddathana) in the Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk, the Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan (Tafsir) and the Tahdhib al-athar to indicate people from whom he had obtained information directly. He mentions hundreds of people in this manner – but a very small subset of them accounts for the majority of his citations. Al-Tabari’s three works contain a vast amount of material from direct informants, and most of that material came into his possession early in his life, a long time before he composed his books. It is our contention that al-Tabari made use of an extensive written record to preserve and organise his material over the decades.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi4/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 3: How Many People Did al-Tabari Talk To?</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-3-Post-3-How/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 3: How Many People Did al-Tabari Talk To?" /><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-3--Post-3--How</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-3-Post-3-How/">&lt;p&gt;This is the third in a series of blog posts examining al-Tabari’s (d. 310/923) citations in his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jāmiʿ al-bayān ʿan taʾwīl āy al-Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;), and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-āthār&lt;/em&gt;. In the first and second posts we presented our questions, method and data set. The data set consists of six tables created iteratively using a series of analytical procedures developed by both of us and implemented by Masoumeh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we tackle the size of al-Tabari’s likely source base. In particular, we seek to establish how many people he credits with a major role in providing the information on which he relies. Al-Tabari’s books are full of citations, giving the impression that he drew actively on numerous sources of information. How big was his source base? And how many people gave him significant amounts of information directly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-small-number-of-very-important-direct-informants&quot;&gt;A Small Number of Very Important Direct Informants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to grips with al-Tabari’s source base means wrestling with a long and complicated list of names whose referents countless generations have already struggled to identify. We cannot access these sources directly, unmediated by the efforts of the intervening generations. But using digital methods, we can discern and analyse frequencies and patterns of citation on a scale that is unprecedented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to determine precisely how many people al-Tabari reported from directly using the &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula, but we were able to form a fairly good estimate of that number, and it is surprisingly small. We looked at all 32,115 &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that feature this formula in any of al-Tabari’s three works and counted the number of citations for each direct informant (the first person in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;); these figures are presented in the Direct Informants Overview table, described in our previous post. After listing the informants in the order of the frequency with which they are cited, we calculated the cumulative total number of citations and the percentage of the total that the citations represent at each level – the top informant, the top two informants, the top three and so on down the list. This information is found in the ‘Cumulative count’ and ‘Cumulative percentage’ columns. The table yields the following data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of names&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;% of all citations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;36%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;42%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;56%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;59%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;79%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;84%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;92%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;93%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: The percentage of al-Tabari’s citations accounted for by his most frequently cited direct informants, at different sample sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1 shows the high degree to which al-Tabari relied on a small group of core informants – indeed a very small group, in view of the large size of his works. The numbers are dramatic: more than half (51%) of al-Tabari’s citations go back to a mere eight direct informants, and the vast majority – nearly 80% – of his citations are to just twenty people. This is extraordinary, especially considering that he often names an informant on first mention but not in subsequent references, when his readers know whom he means. Since our method catches only explicit mentions of informants’ names, it is likely to understate the true frequency of references to the most common informants. In reality, then, the degree of concentration is probably even higher than it appears from our figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, 749 names cited by al-Tabari appear as direct informants in only about 7% of his citations across all three works. There are hundreds of names that appear just once, though many of these names may represent variant surface forms of the same name. The total number of people from whom al-Tabari actually harvested information is likely to fall far short of this high figure. More probably it lies in the neighbourhood of 200–300; but within this number, a very small group played an outsized role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-top-ten&quot;&gt;The Top Ten&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that al-Tabari worked efficiently, drawing maximum benefit from a small set of sources. But who were these people? What follows is an annotated list of the ten most often cited informants in order of the frequency of their citation. These ten persons are cited in all three of al-Tabari’s works, and according to our data set they together account for 59% of all references to a direct informant. The list specifies how many times al-Tabari cites each individual (that is, how often the individual’s name begins a paragraph in our machine-readable files) after &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; (‘he told me’) and &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; (‘he told us’), respectively. The biographical information given below has been collated from publications by Gilliot, Athari and Lucas.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We also list the variant surface forms of each name. It is important to note that surface forms can vary for many reasons, including different appellations by which a person was known, the effect of Arabic case endings (which vary depending on the sentence’s syntax), and typological and other errors, both those present in the source texts and those arising from the normalisation of Arabic script in the OpenITI corpus. (As an example, the variation in the dotting of the final yaʾ under Bishr b. Muʿadh below appears already in the source on which the OpenITI file is based.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862). Cited 2,879 times (21 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/2,858 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Rayy, where he stayed for five years after leaving home at the age of 12. Ibn Humayd transmitted a recension of Ibn Ishaq’s biography of the Prophet to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن حميد&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن حميد الرازي&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن حميد&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن حميد الرازي&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In terms of Ibn Ishaq’s biography of the Prophet, it is hard to know precisely what Muhammad b. Humayd had to hand. It may have been the case that al-Tabari worked off of a written version. This was the view of Heribert Horst, who concluded that Ibn Ishaq’s book was one of only four or five ‘complete books’ (&lt;em&gt;vollständige Bücher&lt;/em&gt;) upon which al-Tabari relied.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; R. Kevin Jaques believes it likely that al-Tabari heard a portion of an Ibn Ishaq version from Muhammad b. Humayd, but received permission (in the form of an an &lt;em&gt;ijaza&lt;/em&gt;) to transmit the entirety. As Jaques writes, ‘In al-Tabari’s citation of Ibn Humayd, he would have received an ʿ&lt;em&gt;ijāza&lt;/em&gt; to transmit Ibn Humayd’s ideas as if al-Tabari had heard the entirety of it from Ibn Humayd’s lips. What was accredited for transmission was, in effect, the oeuvre of the author.’&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;While al-Tabari may have worked in this way, the high prevalence of the ‘he told me’ formula represents his access as based on a relationship that ran over time. Yaqut quotes Ibn Kāmil (d. 350/961), a contemporary and early biographer of al-Tabari, as saying that al-Tabari wrote down over 100,000 Hadiths based on reporting from Muhammad b. Humayd (&lt;em&gt;kataba ʿan Ibn Humayd&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The account falls within Ibn Kamil’s description of al-Tabari’s journey in search of knowledge, an account that generally emphasises how much al-Tabari wrote down and stored up for later use (including mention of his rearrangement of his materials). The sense from Yaqut (via Ibn Kamil) would be that al-Tabari heard individual reports from Muhammad b. Humayd, not that he sat down to a written out version of the Prophet’s biography.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Of course, Muhammad b. Humayd passed on more material than the Prophet’s biography. This leaves open the possibility that Ibn Kamil’s account – emphasising bit by bit acquisition – applies to this other material, not the biography by Ibn Ishaq. This is not, however, what Yaqut’s text straight-forwardly says.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bishr b. Muʿadh (d. 245/859–60). Cited 2,418 times (23 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/2,395 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Basra. Al-Tabari relies on him and two intermediaries for a major collection of exegetical opinions from an early traditionist, Qatada (d. ca. 118/736–7).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بشر&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بشر بن معاذ العقدى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بشر بن معاذ العقدي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Al-Muthanna b. Ibrahim al-Amuli (d. unknown). Cited 2,259 times (2,064 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/195 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him either in Amul or in Rayy.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبراهيم&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبراهيم الآملي&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبراهيم الطبري&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;المثنى بن إبرهيم الآملي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Yunus b. ʿAbd al-Aʿla al-Sadafi (d. 264/867). Cited 2,250 times (2,113 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/137 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). A famous early supporter of al-Shafiʿi and a major scholar in Egypt, where al-Tabari met him. For al-Tabari, he is the source of a Quran commentary by ʿAbd al-Rahman b. Zayd.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس بن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس بن عبد الأعلى الصدفى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;يونس بن عبد الأعلى الصدفي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Al-Qasim b. al-Hasan (d. 272/885). Cited 1,699 times (56 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1643 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Baghdad. Gilliot says this is probably Abu Muhammad al-Qasim b. al-Hasan b. Yazid al-Hamdani al-Saʾigh. He is cited in numerous reports in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; as reporting from the Meccan Ibn Jurayj (d. 150/768), who composed a &lt;em&gt;Sunan&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;القاسم&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;القاسم بن الحسن&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. Bashshar, called Bundār (d. 252/866). Cited 1,644 times (16 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,628 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Basra. He was a major Hadith scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن بشار&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;بن بشار&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن بشار&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Abu Kurayb (d. 248/862). Cited 1,609 times (12 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,597 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Kufa. One of the transmitters of Ibn Ishaq from Yunus b. Bukayr (d. 199/815). Gilliot mentions (on the basis of Yaqut’s &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-ʿudabāʾ&lt;/em&gt;) that al-Tabari memorised Abu Kurayb’s reports; the reports also indicate that al-Tabari may have written them down afterwards as notes.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;أبا كريب محمد بن العلاء أبو كريب&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;أبو كريب محمد بن العلاء&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن العلاء&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن العلاء أبو كريب&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن العلاء الهمداني&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sufyan b. Wakiʿ (d. 247/861). Cited 1,443 times (16 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,427 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Kufa.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن وكيع&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;سفيان بن وكيع&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;سفيان بن وكيع بن الجراح&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. ʿAmr al-Bahili (d. 249/869). Cited 1,411 times (1,306 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/105 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). He is a Basran Hadith collector who settled in Baghdad. Mujahid’s (d. 104/722) exegetical opinions passed into the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; partly through him.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عمرو&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عمرو الباهلي&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ibn ʿAbd al-Aʿla (d. 245/859–60). Cited 1,278 times (48 &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/1,239 &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Tabari met him in Basra. Al-Tabari relies on him for Maʿmar’s collection of exegetical opinions from Qatada (a second major source of Qatada’s opinions alongside Bishr b. Muʿadh).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Surface forms of his name:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى الصنعانى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى الصنعاني&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;ابن عبد الأعلى بن واصل&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عبد الأعلى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عبد الأعلى الصنعانى&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;محمد بن عبد الأعلى الصنعاني&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari was born in Amul in 224 or 225/838 or 9. Given the death dates of his top ten sources (whose average year of death was 252/866), he must have been very young – in his teens and twenties – when he gathered reports from most of them. This is consistent with the story biographers tell of al-Tabari’s ‘intellectual formation’ (to use Claude Gilliot’s term). After leaving home at the age of 12 he lived for around five years in Rayy before moving to Baghdad, where he spent about a year. Afterwards, he spent two years or somewhat less in southern Iraq (Wasit, Basra and Kufa) before returning to Baghdad for a further eight years. Then he embarked on what C. E. Bosworth called his ‘major educational and research journey’, which took him to Syria, Palestine and Egypt. He eventually landed back in Baghdad in 256/870, where he flourished as a scholar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His return to Bag̲h̲dād marked the end of his student &lt;em&gt;Wanderjahre&lt;/em&gt;, and he now settled down for the remaining fifty years of his life in order to devote himself to teaching and authorship, producing an amount of high-quality scholarship such as to evoke the admiration, in an age of prolific authors anyway, of both contemporaries and subsequent generations.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari’s biography thus supports the impression that he largely collected his information in the early period of his life. It is further corroborated by the information we can gather on his most frequently cited direct informants beyond the top ten: the average year of death for the top 100 is 256/869–70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the overall data set of 32,115 &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, the terms &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; begin an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; approximately 38% and 62% of the time, respectively. It seems that al-Tabari deliberately distinguished transmission to him, singly, from transmission to him as part of a group, since he made a point of using a specific term – either &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; – nearly exclusively for each direct informant listed above. Still, more work should be done to discern and interpret the patterns in his use of the terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It thus appears that al-Tabari encountered the major sources of the information he relied on in his books when he was young, long before he compiled his works. Such citation of much older persons is, of course, common and reflects the widespread desire to minimise the number of transmitters in an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (on the rationale that information flow is more reliable over fewer people). The terms he uses indicate that his learning occurred in group settings more often than it did in one-on-one situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we explain al-Tabari’s reproduction of this knowledge in books that he wrote as much as a half-century after his first exposure to the source material? How does he manage to quote, for example, nearly 3,000 reports (in our data set) from Muhammad b. Humayd, with whom he studied as a teen, in his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;? In the next blog post we argue that al-Tabari maintained a set of notebooks and put them to efficient and good use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Claude Gilliot, ‘La formation intellectuelle de Tabari (224/5–310/839–923)’, &lt;em&gt;Journal asiatique&lt;/em&gt; 276 (1988), 203–44; Akram Athari, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; (Amman and Cairo: n.p., 2005); and Scott C. Lucas, &lt;em&gt;Selections from the Comprehensive Exposition of the Interpretations of the Verses of the Qurʾān&lt;/em&gt; (Cambridge: Royal Aal Al-Bayt Institute for Islamic Thought and Islamic Texts Society, 2017), esp. ii, 467–82 (‘Appendix B: Ṭabarī’s Teachers’). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The others were compositions by ʿAli b. Abi Talha, Mujahid, ʿAbd al-Rahman b. Zayd b. Aslam, and possibly Ibn Saʿd. Horst, ‘Zur Überlieferung im Korankommentar aṭ-Ṭabarīs’, &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift der deutschen morgenländischen Gesellschaft&lt;/em&gt; 103 (1953), 290–307, at 307. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jaques has spent more than ten years collecting evidence for the transmission of Ibn Ishaq’s &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;. It seems unlikely to Jaques that al-Tabari copied the entirety of the text from Ibn Humayd’s audition. ‘It seems to me more likely that al-Tabari made, or had made, and was given a copy, of the text that Ibn Humayd got from Ibn al-Fadl.’ Personal communication, 4 September 2021. See also Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 6-7. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yaqut, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-ʿudabaʾ&lt;/em&gt;, ed. ʿUmar Faruq al-Tabbaʿ (Beirut: Muʼassasat al-Maʻarif: Dar Ibn Hazm, 1999), i, 520-1. The number should not be taken literally; the same figure is used for reports from Abu Kurayb. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;C. E. Bosworth, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’, &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam,&lt;/em&gt; 2nd ed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">This is the third in a series of blog posts examining al-Tabari’s (d. 310/923) citations in his Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk, Jāmiʿ al-bayān ʿan taʾwīl āy al-Qurʾān (Tafsir), and Tahdhib al-āthār. In the first and second posts we presented our questions, method and data set. The data set consists of six tables created iteratively using a series of analytical procedures developed by both of us and implemented by Masoumeh.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/tabari_dispatches.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 1: Al-Tabari’s Direct Informants: Work on a New Data Set</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-1-Al-Tabari-s/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 1: Al-Tabari’s Direct Informants: Work on a New Data Set" /><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-1--Al-Tabari%E2%80%99s</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-1-Al-Tabari-s/">&lt;p&gt;In a series of eight blog posts, we share some results of experimental work on citations in three works by Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari (d. 310/923). These are his universal history, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;; his Quran commentary, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;) and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt;, an incomplete work on traditions, arranged according to the last transmitter of the Hadiths and also according to the Prophet’s Companions. All three are important works in their own fields and contain numerous citation chains (&lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s). These &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s provide a fascinating and previously untried opportunity for historians to understand his working methods.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-we-want&quot;&gt;What We Want&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the three works, al-Tabari refers repeatedly to people who gave him information directly with the phrase ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;). Our goal was to use these citations to build up a picture of his working methods relevant to Arabic book history. Our specific questions were the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari’s books are full of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and give the general impression of a man on the move, gathering information from many corners. How big was his source base? In particular, how many people gave him information directly on a significant scale (we call these people ‘direct informants’)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What form might the material he obtained from these people have taken? The field generally now accepts the idea that notebooks played a major role in knowledge transmission, especially before al-Tabari’s lifetime. Al-Tabari rarely cites books – that is, works that circulated under specific titles. Do his books provide evidence of the use of notebooks?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To what extent do all three works rely on a common source base? Did al-Tabari reuse his own material, copying, for example, parts of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; into the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, or vice versa?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions address a larger set of issues in book history relating to the idea of the book and the form and evolution of the written Arabic tradition in the third/ninth century and beyond. A major argument running through these posts is that al-Tabari worked efficiently. The total word count of the three works considered here is 4.72 million words. But despite the size of his works and the number of citations in them, he relied heavily on a surprisingly small number of people as his sources. Another major argument is that he relied specifically on notes, collated into notebooks whose structure and content we can imagine in some detail, if not reconstruct precisely. His ability to recall information from these notebooks was critical to his compositional method. He compiled the notebooks in his youth using information he obtained from people with whom he spent significant periods of time. The material that found its way into his writing was (metaphorically) indexed to these people, his experiences with them and the writings that he carried with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book historians working on the third/ninth century struggle to make sense of what can seem a bewildering situation. We find references to works and authors from this period in, among others, the &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; of the bio-bibliographer Ibn al-Nadim (d. 385/995). But when we try to match a book to an author, we often find that the book took its final form only much later – perhaps after decades or more. Or we discover that when Ibn al-Nadīm refers to a person’s writings, he had in mind something smaller, or less permanent, than what we would today recognise as a book. The most frequently encountered situation is that a work mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; no longer survives, at least independently. More perplexingly, we find citations of authors in works that post-date the authors’ lifetimes, but with no references to actual books written by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we as historians describe the working habits of authors in this period, we may feel like the proverbial blind men, each trying to describe an elephant but able only to name a feature or two of it – be it ears, tail or skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than thirty years ago, Gregor Schoeler prompted us to think harder about the meaning of ‘book’, especially in the second/eighth and third/ninth centuries (Schoeler had predecessors, but his impact on the cohort of current historians has been unique). He distinguished an essentially private note set or notebook (&lt;em&gt;hypomnēma&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;hypomnēmata&lt;/em&gt;) from ‘actual books’, purposely crafted for publication to an audience of readers (&lt;em&gt;syngramma&lt;/em&gt;, pl. &lt;em&gt;syngrammata&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This important distinction supplanted the earlier perceived binary between the written and the oral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historians adopted Schoeler’s model and have used it particularly to describe the emergence and development of what for him were ‘actual books’. The third/ninth century is now frequently considered the period that witnessed the ‘rise of the Arabic book’ (as Beatrice Gruendler’s 2020 monograph is titled). Letizia Osti and James Weaver have made the important observation that from the second half of the third/ninth century onwards, books come to possess features that make them ‘increasingly usable for independent reading and study’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Division into topical chapters, hierarchical structuring, the use of section- and chapter-headings, detailed tables of contents within programmatic introductions, and alphabetically ordered lemmata, as well as regular cross-referencing, all enable the autonomous reader to navigate unfamiliar material with greater ease, to some extent perhaps facilitating consultation in addition to linear reading.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the third/ninth century no doubt witnessed changes towards the ‘well-organised book’, we would like to add a further layer of complexity by giving greater consideration to the personal side of writing. We believe that citations and text reuse data reveal that authors’ approaches to their writing were more diverse than we recognise today and that the types of authority that these approaches carried were also more varied than we currently imagine. We can perceive these features by examining al-Tabari’s citations and reading Ibn al-Nadim’s &lt;em&gt;Fihrist&lt;/em&gt; alongside them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are convinced that further questions can productively be asked about the written Arabic tradition. The question we wish to pose is not whether a piece of writing constituted a published, redacted book but rather what forms did writing take, what evidence do we have of these forms in works that do survive and how might ideas about writing itself have contributed to the evolution of the tradition as it survives – including the loss and oblivion of many of its layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari was working with bounteous written materials – including, prominently, Quranic exegesis, historiography and Hadith – and these materials took many different forms. Many of them represented second- and third-generation offshoots of earlier writings, bundled together, as, for example, in the case of al-Tabari’s access to al-Madaʾini’s (d. ca. 224/839 or 228/842–3) historical material, studied by Ilkka Lindstedt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important question concerns the extent to which the situation in al-Tabari’s lifetime resembles that in later eras. Our data points to continuities in practice across the third/ninth century and indeed beyond, with later scholars citing al-Tabari personally, rather than his books, surprisingly often. The Arabic book thus seems to show continued reliance on earlier forms of written transmission, including those supported by aurality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the advancement of the field, we should seek to discern such continuities in writerly practice in later periods, in which writers relied on notes and blends of writing and aurality (as described, for example, by Konrad Hirschler).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This type of blended transmission was clearly critical for Hadith and the disciplines that supported it, but it appears that history writing, and perhaps other genres, too, shared these practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first blog post, we introduce our method; in the second, we present our data. Over the subsequent posts, we then consider each of the above questions as we demonstrate what al-Tabari’s citation practices reveal about the working habits of a major author in the late third/ninth and early fourth/tenth centuries and the shape of the material on which he relied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;method&quot;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari uses several terms to denote transmission of information from other people, but only a few of these terms indicate direct, personal contact. The phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;) at the beginning of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (citation chain) are by far the most common markers of such contact. We are most interested in the name that introduces the &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;, representing the transmitter closest to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd told me (&lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;) that Jarīr said that he was told by Mughira, from al-Musayyib b. Rafiʿ, that Abu Hurayra said: Abraham never lied, except on three occasions…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; with whom al-Tabari implies having had direct contact is Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862). That al-Tabari indeed had direct contact with Muhammad b. Humayd and the other individuals for whom he uses the ‘he told me’ phrases is supported by biographical works that discuss al-Tabari’s life. For example, al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (d. 463/1071) wrote that al-Tabari&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;heard (&lt;em&gt;samiʿa&lt;/em&gt;) Muhammad b. ʿAbd al-Malik b. Abi al-Shawarib, Ishaq b. Abi Israʾil, Ahmad b. Maniʿ al-Baghawi, Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi, Abu Hammam al-Walid b. Shujaʿ, Abu Kurayb Muhammad b. al-ʿAlaʾ, Yaʿqub b. Ibrahim al-Dawraqi, Abu Saʿid al-Ashajja, ʿAmr b. ʿAli, Muhammad b. Bashshar, Muhammad b. al-Muthanna, and a circle comprising many people like them from Iraq, Syria and Egypt.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabari cites all but one (Abu Saʿid al-Ashajja) of these people in his works using the ‘he told me’ phrases. However, although al-Khaṭīb mentioned only ten names, al-Tabari seems to identify hundreds of direct contacts. Further, al-Khatib may well have been relying on the very same evidence as we are for identifying al-Tabari’s direct informants. But even if he was, it would still be noteworthy that he interpreted the ‘he told me’ phrases in the same way as we do – as indicators of direct contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph 1: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; across al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. Graph designed by Peter Verkinderen and Masoumeh Seydi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frequency of this formula can be represented graphically. In Graph 1, the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; has been broken down into chunks of 1,513 characters – the average number of characters in a set of 300 word tokens in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (all books within the OpenITI corpus are divided into chunks of 300 word tokens, each marked by a numbered ‘milestone’ tag). The graph is thus like a great scroll on which the text is written with 1,513 characters per line. The top of the scroll is the graph’s left edge, and its bottom is the right edge. The location of each &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt; that starts with &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; is marked with a blue dot. Uses of the effectively synonymous expressions &lt;em&gt;akhbaranī&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;akhbaranā&lt;/em&gt; are marked with black dots. The red dots, meanwhile, indicate &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;s beginning with the passive-voice phrase &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;, ‘it is reported from’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of phrases that might point to direct transmission, the formula &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; is by far the most common. Al-Tabari does not use the phrase &lt;em&gt;samiʿtu&lt;/em&gt; (‘I heard’), for example, and the phrases &lt;em&gt;akhbarana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;akhbarani&lt;/em&gt; appear only rarely. Al-Tabari’s use of the passive ‘it is reported from’, which does not reveal his direct informant, is concentrated in the final part of the work, a phenomenon discussed in detail elsewhere.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Graph 2: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph 3: The frequency and location of the phrases ‘he told me’/’he told us’ as the first element of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We describe our data and the way we generated it in much more detail in our next blog post, but the following is a summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We went through each work and extracted &lt;em&gt;isnād&lt;/em&gt;s that start with the &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula. The formula occurs 32,115 times across the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s are presented in a table entitled ‘Transmission Chains’ in our data set.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The style of writing and citation in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; differs from that in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. Generally speaking, al-Tabari’s more narrative style in the former invokes &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, but often refers back to them in oblique ways. Consequently, &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and other citations appear relatively less frequently in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, as the graphs above show.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;We extracted the names of transmitters from the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and put each in a separate cell in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;’s row. To identify and separate the names, we relied on a list of transmissive terms, first prepared by R. Kevin Jaques, plus a further list of words, such as ‘by him’ (&lt;em&gt;bi-hi&lt;/em&gt;), that appear in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s but are not part of names.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We created a unified list of authorities by normalising variants of each Arabic name to a single Latin-script version and listing the normalised names in a ‘Name Normalisation’ table. We also entered the normalised names into the Transmission Chains table.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We calculated the frequency of the name of each direct informant in each position within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s and presented them as a ‘Direct Informants Position Frequencies’ table. This step helped us to diagnose data challenges involving names. Theoretically, these names should only appear in position 1. But that is not the case. For example, cases in which our extraction method failed to distinguish two &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, with the result that the same name occurred in two positions in the putative &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;. Or cases where the same name refers to two different people, only one of whom is a direct informant.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Building on the above table, we created a ‘Direct Informants Overview’ table, which ranks al-Tabari’s direct informants by the frequency of his citation of them. It includes, for each informant, the normalised name, the total number of times the informant’s name appears across al-Tabari’s works, and the number of times it appears in each work. It also contains a cumulative count of citations and the cumulative percentage they represent of the total, which indicates the degree of al-Tabari’s reliance on his top informants. Finally, the table includes the informants’ death dates and the places in which each met al-Tabari according to secondary literature (which is also cited in the table).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, we compiled a ‘Texts Name Counts’ table, which shows how many direct informants al-Tabari cites in each of his works and also how many are cited in two or all three of the works. This table is especially important for our final question, concerning the extent to which he relied on a common source base.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We analysed this data alongside text reuse data on overlaps between al-Tabari’s various writings and between his works and other, earlier and later works. Evidence of such alignments was particularly helpful for showing that al-Tabari was working with written materials, sometimes in precise ways but other times quite liberally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project is experimental and unfinished. We are able to obtain a lot of data relatively efficiently, but we know there is further evidence that can be harvested at a later point in time with refinements to our method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;previous-work&quot;&gt;Previous Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data we have examined opens a window on al-Tabari’s participation in a system involving students and teachers, speaking and note-taking, and the storage of material over decades. Our approach aims for the big picture. We want to determine how al-Tabari worked, to get a sense of the scale and likely form of his source base and to judge whether he used a common source base or relied on different direct informants for each of his works. Our overall goal is to expand and add nuance to our current understanding of book history in the third/ninth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ours is a picture of the forest rather than the trees. But our digital effort is part of a long tradition of tracing al-Tabari’s sources (who are often called his ‘teachers’, a blanket term that, we believe, overspecifies the relationship between al-Tabari and many of his direct informants, only some of whom fit the description of this role, whatever respect was owed to them because of their age in al-Tabari’s day). Attempts to identify the people with whom he had direct contact began in the centuries after his death, undertaken, for example, by al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (463/1071), Yaqut al-Hamawi (d. 626/1229), al-Dhahabi (d. 748/1348) and Ibn Hajar al-ʿAsqalani (d. 852/1449). According to Yaqut, al-Tabari wrote about the teachers with whom he studied (&lt;em&gt;samiʿa&lt;/em&gt;) in his &lt;em&gt;Kitab Dhayl al-mudhayyal&lt;/em&gt;. However, this section is not preserved in the ‘skimpy’ selection from the work that survives as &lt;em&gt;Muntakhab min Dhayl al-mudhayyal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The efforts at identification continued into the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, most recently with Ahmad Muhammad Shakir (d. 1958), Franz Rosenthal (d. 2003), Claude Gilliot, ʿAbd Allah b. ʿAbd al-Muhsin al-Turki, Scott Lucas and, most exhaustively, Akram b. Muhammad Athari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would be no forest without trees. We rely especially on Athari’s &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; for our Name Normalisation table. Athari’s work contains 475 numbered entries for names listed first in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. The book runs to more than 800 pages and features entries such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;129. Saʿid b. Numayr. From the tenth [generation]. I did not identify him, nor did I find a biographical entry (&lt;em&gt;tarjama&lt;/em&gt;) on him. Before me, Shaykh [Ahmad Muhammad] Shakir [also] passed over him. In his edition of the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt;, Shaykh [ʿAbdAllah] al-Turki named him, specifying that one of the manuscripts had [the name as] Saʿid b. ʿUmar. But he did not attempt to go further in his entry.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athari includes in his entries, to the best of his ability, the informants’ birth and death dates, the people from and to whom each informant transmitted and information on the informants’ reliability. He also specifies the generation (from the ninth to the eleventh) to which the informant belonged according to a &lt;em&gt;tabaqat&lt;/em&gt; schema, and he cites the sources of his information. It is important to note that he is not claiming to have found 475 &lt;em&gt;shuyukh&lt;/em&gt; for al-Tabari. Rather, his list comprises the ‘surface forms’ of the names that al-Tabari identifies as his sources as they appear in the text, regardless of whether these names can be connected to actual historical persons. The tenor of the above paragraph on Saʿid b. Numayr is common. The last fifty or so of Athari’s entries are on especially problematic surface forms and identities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athari has made considerable efforts to determine the identity of the people named by al-Tabari. Thanks to his investigation, for example, we know that two different names can refer to the same person, or that an apparent reference to a particular individual may in fact denote someone else when the ostensible referent lived before al-Tabari’s time, or that a name appears in the wrong form (such as ‘Yunus b. Sulayman al-Basri’ instead of the correct ‘Yusuf b. Salman al-Basri’). Atharī also notes variations between editions of the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital methods that we currently use cannot identify all of the named persons either, especially in cases in which we know nothing of an individual’s biography. Over these works’ long history, there have been plenty of chances for scribal errors and other changes to obscure identities and mix up the order of names in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a fuller discussion of the data, please read our second blog post, ‘Show Me the Data!’ Otherwise, stay tuned for Post 3, ‘How Many People Did al-Tabari Talk To?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the data set, see https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5533889. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gregor Schoeler, &lt;em&gt;The Genesis of Literature in Islam: From the Aural to the Read&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Shawkat M. Toorawa (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2009), 63. Schoeler’s distinction goes back to his 1985 &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; article, ‘Die Frage der schriftlichen oder mündlichen Überlieferung der Wissenschaften im frühen Islam’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 62 (1985), 201–30. For the phrase ‘actual books’, see his &lt;em&gt;The Oral and the Written in Early Islam&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Uwe Vagelpohl (London: Routledge, 2010). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Letizia Osti and James Weaver, ‘Organizing the Fourth/Tenth Century: Knowledge, Information, Tools’, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Abbasid Studies&lt;/em&gt; 7 (2020), 103–20, at 108. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lindstedt, ‘The Transmission of al-Madāʿinī’s Historical Material to al-Balādhurī and al-Ṭabarī: A Comparison and Analysis of Two &lt;em&gt;Khabar&lt;/em&gt;s’, in Sylvia Akar, Jaakko Hämeen-Anttila and Inka Nokso-Koivisto, eds, &lt;em&gt;Travelling Through Time: Essays in honour of Kaj Öhrnberg&lt;/em&gt; (Helsinki: Finnish Oriental Society, 2013), 41–63 and Lindstedt, ‘Al-Madāʾinī’, &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt;, 3rd ed. In the &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia of Islam&lt;/em&gt; article, Lindstedt has also pointed out that in the two surviving works of al-Madāʾinī, ‘every narrative item is preceded by a chain of transmission mentioning his students and his students’ students’. This method of citation ‘arguably signifies that the works were redacted, and perhaps compiled into manuscript form, by students of al-Madāʾinī’. See also Lindstedt, ‘The Life and Deeds of ʿAlī b. Muḥammad al-Madāʾinī’, &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift für Geschichte der arabisch-islamischen Wissenschaften&lt;/em&gt; 20–21 (2012–14), 235–70; Lindstedt, ‘The Role of al-Madāʾinī’s Students in the Transmission of His Material’, &lt;em&gt;Der Islam&lt;/em&gt; 91/2 (2014): 295–340. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Konrad Hirschler, &lt;em&gt;The Written Word in the Medieval Arabic Lands: A Social and Cultural History of Reading Practices&lt;/em&gt; (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2012); Hirschler, &lt;em&gt;A Monument to Medieval Syrian Book Culture: The Library of Ibn ʿAbd al-Hādī&lt;/em&gt; (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2020). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh Baghdad&lt;/em&gt;, OpenITI, 0463KhatibBaghdadi.TarikhBaghdad.Shamela0000736-ara2.mARkdown, milestone (ms.) 0545. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the more technically minded: To produce this graph we defined regular expression patterns to find the transmissive terms &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;akhbarani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;akhbarana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;. We then searched for the terms in the text of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; to determine the character positions of those terms. We scaled the positions to the x- and y-axes of the graph, which represent the length of the text and the approximate length of the 300–word token chunks, respectively. To identify the beginnings of sections, we searched for the section headers (annotated through OpenITI mARkdown) and marked these with vertical lines. The script for doing this is available at https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5118900. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franz Rosenthal, general introduction to al-Tabari, &lt;em&gt;The History of al-Ṭabarī&lt;/em&gt;, i: &lt;em&gt;General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Franz Rosenthal (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), 89–90. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Akram Athari, &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam shuyukh al-Tabari&lt;/em&gt; (Amman and Cairo: n.p., 2005), 258, no. 129. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">In a series of eight blog posts, we share some results of experimental work on citations in three works by Muhammad b. Jarir al-Tabari (d. 310/923). These are his universal history, Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk; his Quran commentary, Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan (Tafsir) and the Tahdhib al-athar, an incomplete work on traditions, arranged according to the last transmitter of the Hadiths and also according to the Prophet’s Companions. All three are important works in their own fields and contain numerous citation chains (isnads). These isnads provide a fascinating and previously untried opportunity for historians to understand his working methods.1 For the data set, see https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5533889. &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi1/media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispatches from al-Tabari 2: Show Me the Data!</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-2-Show-Me-the/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispatches from al-Tabari 2: Show Me the Data!" /><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-2--Show-Me-the</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Dispatches-from-al-Tabari-2-Show-Me-the/">&lt;p&gt;You have now entered the weeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past months, we have been asking ourselves what we would need to tell the story of how al-Tabari (d. 310/923) worked. Our first blog post summarised the procedure that we used to generate our data set. This post describes the data in greater detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our data set is based on al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-rusul wa-l-muluk&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jamiʿ al-bayan ʿan taʾwil ay al-Qurʾan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib al-athar&lt;/em&gt;, included in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/4513723&quot;&gt;[2021.1.4 release]{.ul}&lt;/a&gt; of our data via Zenodo under the identifiers Shamela0009783BK1, Shamela0007798 and JK008250Vols, respectively. The books have been annotated with tags belonging to the OpenITI mARkdown scheme to identify certain structural and content features. The present study made use of these tags. We have used the structural tagging in the above release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-tables&quot;&gt;Data Tables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We produced five tables that display the data gleaned from al-Tabari’s three books. We did not set out to create these five; rather, they emerged in the course of the work. What follows is an account of research in progress. We expect to improve on our method in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-transmission-chains&quot;&gt;1. Transmission Chains&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collected all &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s from the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; that start a paragraph with either &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; (‘he told me’) or &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; (‘he told us’); we included also related phrases, such as &lt;em&gt;wa-qad haddathani&lt;/em&gt;. These phrases occur a total of 32,115 times in the three books – 2,065 times in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, 26,234 in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and 3,816 in the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;. The largest number of such citations is thus found in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;, which is also the longest of the three works, containing 2.91 million word tokens to the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;’s 1.46 million and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;’s roughly 346,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We put each &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; into a row in a CSV file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi2/media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021-10-05/sarah_savant_masoumeh_seydi2/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image 1: A section of al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, tagged with OpenITI mARkdown encoding (implemented in EditPad Pro), with a transmission chain featuring Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi (d. 248/862) transmitting to al-Tabari from Jarīr b. ʿAbd al-Hamid (d. 188/804). Muhammad b. Humayd also transmitted material from Muhammad b. Ishaq’s (d. 150/767) &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt; to al-Tabari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted in our previous post, the style of al-Tabari’s writing and citation in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; differs from that in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;, as al-Tabari invokes &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s less frequently in the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;. Furthermore, in the latter parts of the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; formula is extremely rare (as evident from Graph 1, in Post 1). Instead, beginning with his account of the founding of Baghdad, al-Tabari typically uses the passive voice to attribute information (&lt;em&gt;dhukira ʿan&lt;/em&gt;, ‘It is reported from’ so-and-so that …).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We relied on machine-readable files of al-Tabari’s books in the OpenITI corpus, annotated and vetted by KITAB team members Maxim Romanov, Hamid Reza Hakimi and Masoumeh Seydi. In these files, the beginning of each paragraph is indicated with a #, which enabled us to write our search pattern (‘regular expression’) to detect instances of &lt;em&gt;haddathani&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;haddathana&lt;/em&gt; specifically at the start of a paragraph (regular expressions are a formalised way of constructing search patterns that is used in many computer languages and text-editing softwares). The reason we excluded non-paragraph-beginning uses of the formula from our search is that when the phrase appears within a transmission chain, it generally introduces not al-Tabari’s direct informant but some earlier authority cited by an intermediate source. In a small number of cases (fewer than twenty), our subsequent review revealed that the machine-readable files required editing, as the # marks had not been placed appropriately (e.g., an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; containing our formula had been erroneously split between two paragraphs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also excluded some data because its structure would have complicated our analysis. The biggest such exclusion concerned &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that feature two or more names in the same node – that is, a piece of information was attributed equally to two different sources. This could occur anywhere within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;, but it was most problematic when the two sources were named as al-Tabari’s direct informants, as in this case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;حدثنا أبو كريب محمد بن العلاء ومحمد بن يزيد الرفاعي قالا حدثنا حسين بن علي عن فضيل بن عياض عن الأعمش …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abu Kurayb Muhammad b. al-ʿAlaʾ [and]{.ul} Muhammad b. Yazid al-Rifaʿi told us: Husayn b. ʿAli told us from Fudayl, from al-ʿAmash …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 32,115 &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s with which we began, we omitted from our analysis 550 (1.7%) that contained two direct informants. However, this exclusion is not significant and has little or no effect on our general findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Transmission Chains table, each &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; has its own row, and each transmitter is placed in a separate cell. The data set also contains a list of transmissive terms prepared by Kevin Jaques as well as a list of other words that appear in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s but do not belong to the names. We used these lists to ensure that only the transmitters’ names were included in the table and that separate names were correctly demarcated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Milestone id&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isnad text&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in pos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in pos 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in pos 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in pos 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in pos 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in pos 6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of names&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ms0185&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;حدثني ابن حميد قال حدثنا جرير عن مغيرة عن المسيب بن رافع عن أبي هريرة قال ما كذب ابراهيم ع غير ثلاث كذبات&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ابن حميد&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;جرير&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;مغيرة&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;المسيب بن رافع&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبي هريرة&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ما كذب ابراهيم ع غير ثلاث كذبات&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: Sample transmission chain from al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, milestone 185. The original passage containing the names is preserved in the table as ‘isnad text’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we are only able to deal with relatively simple &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. We eliminate rows where in position 1 two names occur, as mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-name-normalisation&quot;&gt;2. Name Normalisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we created an authorities list that reduced (normalised) variants of a name to a single Latin-script version, without diacritics. The table also provides biographical information, when available, for direct informants. In its present form, the table contains 4,920 individual names in their ‘surface form’, that is, the form in which they appear in the text, found in any position in an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; in any of al-Tabari’s works. Some of these surface forms in fact refer to the same individual, as in the following example, which demonstrates the need for name normalisation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surface form (in Arabic)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Normalisation (transliteration)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appears in position 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appears in position 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appears in position 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appears only in position 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;إبراهيم بن عبد الله العبسي&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibrahim b. 'AbdAllah b. Muhammad&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;إبراهيم بن عبد الله بن محمد العبسي&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibrahim b. 'Abd Allah b. Muhammad&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;إبراهيم بن عبد الله بن مسلم&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibrahim b. 'Abd Allah b. Muslim&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;إبراهيم بن عبد الله بن مسلم أبو مسلم&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibrahim b. 'Abd Allah b. Muslim&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 2: Sample name normalisations, also indicating the position(s) in which the name appears within al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; positions in which particular names appear help us assess whether two surface forms could refer to a single person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then updated the Transmission Chains table with the normalised names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Milestone id&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isnad text&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in position 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in position 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in position 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in position 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in position 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of names&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ms0185&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;حدثني ابن حميد قال حدثنا جرير عن مغيرة عن المسيب بن رافع عن أبي هريرة قال ما كذب ابراهيم ع غير ثلاث كذبات&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jarir&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mughira&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;al-Musayyib b. Rafi'&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Abu Hurayra&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1b: Sample normalised transmission chain. The normalised names of transmitters have been inserted and cells without names (in this case ‘Name in position 6’; cf. Table 1) have been omitted. However, the ‘Number of names’ column retains the original values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-direct-informants-position-frequencies&quot;&gt;3. Direct Informants Position Frequencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the third table, we calculated the frequency with which each normalised name of a direct informant appears in each position within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s (pos 1 = direct informant). Theoretically, the direct informants should only appear at position 1, but for a variety of reasons the names repeat at later positions (see below ‘Data Challenges’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 7&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in pos 10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2879&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bishr b. Mu'adh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2418&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;al-Muthanna&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2259&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Yunus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2250&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;162&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;al-Qasim&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1699&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 3: Example of direct informants position frequencies, showing the five names al-Tabari cites most frequently in position 1 (i.e. as direct informants).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table allows us to identify the names of direct informats cited most frequently in each position (as well as the less commonly cited names). It also helps us tackle some of the data challenges involving names discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-direct-informants-overview&quot;&gt;4. Direct Informants Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We extend the Direct Informants Position Frequencies table. It includes the names of al-Tabari’s direct informants and the number of times he cites them (‘count’) in position 1. The table also records the works in which they are cited as well as a cumulative total of the citations and the percentage they represent of all citations (revealing, for example, the portion of all citations accounted for by the top five or ten direct informants).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name in position 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cumulative count&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cumulative percentage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in &lt;em&gt;Jāmiʿ al-bayān&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count in &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2879&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2879&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.11855066&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;457&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2126&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;296&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bishr b. Mu'adh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2418&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5297&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16.776993&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2383&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;al-Muthanna&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2259&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7556&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;23.9318405&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2233&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Yunus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2250&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9806&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31.05818262&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2075&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;149&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;al-Qasim&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1699&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11505&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;36.43936275&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1667&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 4: Example of direct informants overview, showing al-Tabari’s top five direct informants. The most frequently cited informant is Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi, who is cited in all three of the works under study and whose name begins 9 percent of all &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s in our data set. Muhammad b. Humayd al-Razi and Bishr b. Mu'adh together appear as the direct informant in sixteen percent of all &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s in our data set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be clear that we take these numbers as relative, not absolute, indicators of frequency, having been forced to make our textual data conform to a data model that is not always perfectly suited. We lose some information, such as the omitted &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that contain two or more names in position 1. Furthermore, al-Tabari relies on his top direct informants even more heavily than these numbers indicate. Our data accounts only for cases in which an informant is named at the beginning of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;, but al-Tabari also refers back to already named sources in ways that are too oblique to be picked up by our search (e.g., ‘he said’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Texts Name Counts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we counted how many direct informants al-Tabari cites in each of his works and how many of these informants are cited not just in one but in two or three of the works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Count of names in position 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; (total)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;347&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; (total)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;543&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt; (total)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;342&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;139&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;229&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;104&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 5: Count of direct informants who appear in each work, in specific pairs of works and in all three works. We also have comparable data on transmitters cited in positions 2 and 3 (not included in this table).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text Reuse and Other Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides this data, we relied on text reuse alignments generated in February 2021, when we ran the books included in the corresponding OpenITI corpus release (version &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/4513723&quot;&gt;[2021.1.4]{.ul}&lt;/a&gt;) through passim software. The most important alignments that we discovered were between two works of al-Tabari, rather than between al-Tabari’s writings and those of another author. We also drew on alignments found between the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; in October 2020; this run used a variation of the passim algorithm that is more useful for uncovering long alignments. We considered all of these alignments within the wider context of the text reuse patterns discovered in the February 2021 data set. Finally, we also relied on data generated by searches across the corpus using regular expressions, especially citations of al-Tabari within &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s in works that post-date his lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to stress that we focused our energies on the disambiguation of direct informants – not on the identification of names further down in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. Many names that appear in later positions have not been normalised and may thus still refer to the same person. The questions we wished to pose to our data – about al-Tabari’s working methods and source base – did not require us to put the same effort into pinning down the identities of these later persons as they did into identifying reliably al-Tabari’s direct informants. Our scripts, furthermore, are not currently very good at detecting the ends of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. Our present work in progress is oriented towards a specific set of questions, but once we publish it, subsequent researchers will be able to build on our data set, pursue their own questions and improve on our methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we cannot yet rely on Natural Language Processing tools (which would have speeded up the extraction of names from the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s). Ryan Muther is working on word-embedding methods for name extraction, and these will also help address the problems identified here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Isolating Single Names&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first major problem we faced was that after we had divided the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s into single-name cells in the Transmission Chains table, some cells still contained non-Latinised names or non-name words. That was because we built the list of names gradually and because the transmissive terms list was not comprehensive. There were a lot of names; we did not originally plan to Latinise as many as we did. Also, many &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s contained further details that needed to be excluded, such as the location where a piece of information was transmitted. In response, whenever we came across a non-Latinised name, we added it to the Name Normalisation table. And when we found non-name words, we added these to a growing list of words to be purged from the table (we kept this list for further study).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of omissions, as already noted we deleted from our data set &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; rows that featured two or more names in the first position, though we saved these rows in a spreadsheet for future study. At subsequent positions within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, we removed cells that contained two or more names, as well as cells that marked the beginning of a second (branching) &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; with the word &lt;em&gt;wa&lt;/em&gt; (‘and’) prefacing the parallel chain. Our data extraction method erroneously treated these branches as a single &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (with the result that in the Names Position Frequency table, a direct informant would appear in two positions). We did not remove all such rows and cells since identifying them was time consuming. We also removed within the cells some words (including transmissive terms) to better isolate the names. In general, we focused on removals (of either rows or cells) where a direct informant was cited at least five times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever we removed a name cell for either of the above reasons, we also removed all further cells to the right of it, as the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; was effectively broken from that point onwards. This procedure preserved the information on al-Tabari’s direct informant but lost the information on that informant’s sources. This occurred with 1,787 rows in this way (marking each omission with ##### in the data set). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Matching Names to People&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Direct Informants Position Frequencies table allowed us to address two different but related problems. We can call them the one name/multiple persons problem and the multiple names/one person problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the first problem, we have not yet come up with a way to encode a single name to point to two different persons depending on, for example, the name’s position within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;. The name Yunus in the Transmission Chains table illustrates the dilemma. When al-Tabari mentions a Yunus in position 1, he means Yunus b. ʿAbd al-Aʿla al-Sadafi (d. 264/877–8), an Egyptian scholar of Quran and Hadith, but when Yunus appears in position 2, it refers to Yunus b. Bukayr (d. 199/815), who transmitted material from Ibn Ishaq’s biography of the Prophet. We could not automatically normalise instances of Yunus in position 2 to Yunus b. Bukayr without the normalisation’s applying also to Yunus b. ʿAbd al-Aʿla al-Sadafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of Muhammad b. Saʿd, who appears in both position 1 and position 2 in al-Tabari’s &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, is similar. In the first position, al-Tabari uses the name for Muhammad b. Saʿd b. Muhammad b. al-Hasan b. ʿAtiyya b. Saʿd b. Junada al-ʿAwfi (d. 276/889), who transmitted information through a family &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; that goes back to Ibn ʿAbbas (d. c. 68/687–8). Al-Tabari cites him and this particular family &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; many times. In the second position, however, ‘Muhammad b. Saʿd’ refers to the author of &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Tabaqat al-kabir&lt;/em&gt; (d. 235/830).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one name/multiple persons problem results in undercounting of people, particularly when we look across the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. Counts of individuals in a single position within the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s (e.g. direct informants) rather than across positions are generally more accurate. The problem might be addressed with a word-embedding method: the computer ‘learns’ the sequences of names that occur in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s across al-Tabari’s books and can then predict which Yunus or Muhammad b. Saʿd is meant on the basis of the position in which the name appears. However, the programme would need to be able to handle transmitters who genuinely occupy different positions in different &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, reflecting the varying routes through which al-Tabari acquired information conveyed by such transmitters. Ryan Muther is now working on developing such word-embedding methods with the project team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we cannot yet resolve this disambiguation problem, we were able to deal with the much more frequent problem of one person’s being referred to in multiple ways. The problem is less severe in al-Tabari’s texts than it is in many later works (especially Ibn ʿAsakir’s &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;). But it is a problem nonetheless and had to be addressed to avoid the artificial inflation of our direct informant count through counting the same informant multiple times under different names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, we selected standard Latin-script names for al-Tabari’s informants and then assigned all the relevant surface-form names to them. We identified the individuals behind apparently different names by observing patterns in the sequences of names preceding and following them in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s: slightly varying names that typically appeared between the same pair of names could be assumed to refer to the same person. Again, we prioritised reconciliation of al-Tabari’s direct informants and made only passing efforts to unify surface forms of names appearing in other positions in the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We normalised the names of al-Tabari’s direct informants even when the normalisation resulted in some ambiguity. For example, ‘al-Qasim’ and ‘al-Qasim b. al-Hasan’ are both cited as direct informants (i.e. in position 1). The &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that follow these names contain the same transmitters, indicating that the two names refer to the same person. We thus normalised both as ‘al-Qasim’ in the Name Normalisation table to facilitate accurate counting of al-Tabari’s direct informants. However, a (possibly different) al-Qasim further down in an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (say, in position 2) now has the same normalised name as al-Qasim b. Muhammad in position 1, and the two individuals cannot be distinguished from one another. We have accepted this ambiguity as preferable to the error that would follow from differentiating the two names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat similarly, the word &lt;em&gt;abi&lt;/em&gt; (‘my father’) appears frequently in &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, when transmitters report having received information from their fathers without naming the latter. We let the word stand in each case, rather than identifying the father in question. Although this means that the normalised ‘name’ Abi now represents multiple people, retaining it has the benefit of preserving information on family relationships among the transmitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found many cases of names that occurred only once or twice but closely resembled other names that appeared frequently in the same positions. For example, al-Tabari cites al-Husayn b. ʿAmr b. Muhammad al-ʿAnqazi several times in the &lt;em&gt;Tafsir&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Tahdhib&lt;/em&gt;, but once he cites al-Husayn b. Muhammad al-ʿAnqazi, indicating that this al-Husayn was a son rather than a grandson of Muhammad al-ʿAnqazī. The transmission chains that the two al-Husayns start contain the same names further down the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;abi&lt;/em&gt; – Asbat – al-Suddi). Although it is true that the omission of an element in a genealogy is not uncommon, for now we chose not to unify these names. When analysing our data, we looked at the frequency of names, especially in the first position, and generally disregarded names that occur infrequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach was to avoid normalisation when in doubt. For example, while filtering the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s we discovered that two of our most commonly cited direct informants (al-Muthanna and ʿAlī b. Dāwūd, the latter normalised to ‘Ali) had many common nodes in their citation chains. They may well be the same person, but since none of our secondary sources, either medieval or modern, seem to have equated them, we did not do so either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data is our starting point and subject to further consideration. The methods we are developing should be discussed and debated. The iterative processes can be improved. But the following posts go on to investigate what the data can show now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Discussed in Sarah Bowen Savant, ‘Al-Ṭabarī’s Unacknowledged Debt to Ibn Abī Ṭāhir Ṭayfūr’ (forthcoming). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Pos = position. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">You have now entered the weeds.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/dispatches2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/thumbs/dispatches2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Arabic Pasts 2021 Programme</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Arabic-pasts-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arabic Pasts 2021 Programme" /><published>2021-10-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Arabic-pasts-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/Arabic-pasts-2021/">&lt;p&gt;Arabic Pasts 2021 is happening from 7th - 9th of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This annual exploratory and informal workshop co-hosted with SOAS University and the University of Oxford offers the opportunity to reflect on history writing in Arabic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please download a pdf of our programme &lt;a href=&quot;/documents/Arabic_Pasts_Schedule_2021.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or find it detailed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;https://aku-edu.zoom.us/meeting/register/tJMsduChpj0sHtXn5T4Y8lDlnBr2847B1V1r&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you would like to register to join us online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;day-one-online&quot;&gt;Day One (Online)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday, 7 October 2021&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome and Introduction (1:00 – 1:30 pm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-1-idealised-pasts-130--330-pm&quot;&gt;Session 1: Idealised Pasts (1:30 – 3:30 pm)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chair, Leif Stenberg, AKU-ISMC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Didactic Disputes: A History of Ashʿarism from 8th/14th-century Tunis&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Caitlyn Olson, New York University Abu Dhabi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructing a Historical Narrative of Sunni Theology: Ibn al-Mibrad’s (d. 909/1503) Genealogy of Ḥanbalī &lt;em&gt;Uṣūl al-Dīn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Arjan Post, KU Leuven&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unravelling the “Postclassical”: Characterising Philosophical Theology After Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī (d. 606/1210))&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Tariq Mir, SOAS, University of London&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the Future upon the Ruins of an Exalted Past. The Islamic Golden Age Topos in the Writings of the Nahḍa Intellectuals&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mouttalib Sophia, ENS de Lyon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coffee Break
3:30 – 3:45 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-2-lost-texts-and-other-recoveries-345--515-pm&quot;&gt;Session 2: Lost Texts and Other Recoveries (3:45 – 5:15 pm)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Chair, James McDougall, University of Oxford **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recovering Lost Texts and Authenticity: Textual Traditions as Living Institution&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Kevin Jaques, University of Indiana and KITAB Project&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergence of Arabic Annals in the 2nd Hijrī Century&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Edward Zychowicz-Coghill, University of Cambridge and King’s College&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transmission of Middle-Persian Texts to Early Arabic Historiography – the Case of Bahrām Čūbīn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Joonas Maristo, University of Helsinki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End of Day One&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;day-two-aga-khan-centre-london--online&quot;&gt;Day Two (Aga Khan Centre, London, &amp;amp; Online)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friday, 8 October 2021&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-1-what-texts-do-930--1100-am&quot;&gt;Session 1: What Texts Do (9:30 – 11:00 am)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chair, Hugh Kennedy, SOAS, University of London&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stories of Justice: Judges and Courts in Ottoman-Arabic Historiography&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;James Baldwin, Royal Holloway&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructing Image and Competing for Legacy of an Early Islamic Renunciant: Ibn al-Jawzī’s &lt;em&gt;Manāqib Maʿrūf al-Karkhī&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Zhicheng Ye, SOAS, University of London&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coffee Break
11:00 – 11:15 am&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-2-memory-text-community-1-1115--1245-pm&quot;&gt;Session 2: Memory, Text, Community-1 (11:15 – 12:45 pm)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chair, Sarah Bowen Savant, AKU-ISMC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory and Textual Communities: An Analysis of Saḥnūn’s &lt;em&gt;Mudawwana&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aslisho Qurboniev, KITAB Project, AKU-ISMC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Life and the Reader: Studying Manuscript Circulation and Text Reuse of the Biographies of Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gowaart Van Den Bossche, KITAB Project, AKU-ISMC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Case Study: Iranian Localization of the Memory of Zindīqs in the Early Abbasid Period&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Yuko Tanaka, SOAS, University of London&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch Break
12:45 – 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-3-memory-text-community-2-200--330-pm&quot;&gt;Session 3: Memory, Text, Community-2 (2:00 – 3:30 pm)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chair, Fozia Bora, University of Leeds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arabic Memory, Syriac Writing: Did Muslim Legends Inspire Christian Arab Martyrdoms?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Simon Pierre, Sorbonne Université&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructed Narratives of Apostasy in Medieval Arabic Historiography&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Salimeh Maghsodulou, Institute of Islamic Studies - McGill University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing the Reincarnated: Druze Textualities and Political Time&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aamer Ibraheem, Columbia University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coffee Break
3:30 – 3:45 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-4-early-arabic-pasts-345--445-pm&quot;&gt;Session 4: Early Arabic Pasts (3:45 – 4:45 pm)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chair, Karen Bauer, The Institute of Ismaili Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shape of History in the Qurʾan&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mohsen Goudarzi, Department of Classical &amp;amp; Near Eastern Studies, Religious Studies Program&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Theory of Paganism in the Syriac Cave of Treasures and its Deployment in Ibn al-Kalbī’s Kitāb al-Aṣnām&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Asad Uz Zaman, The Ohio State University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End of Day Two&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;day-three-online&quot;&gt;Day Three (Online)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 9 October 2021&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-1-raising-the-profile-of-a-historian-145---245-pm&quot;&gt;Session 1: Raising the Profile of a Historian (1:45 - 2:45 pm)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chair, Arezou Azad, University of Oxford&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uthmān ibn Sanad (d. 1828) for Understanding the History of the Gulf During the Turn of the Nineteenth Century&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Saleh Alkhulaifi, SOAS, University of London&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indian Historian’s Arabic Craft: ʿAbd al-Ḥayy al-Ḥasanī’s (d. 1923) History of Islam in India&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mohsin Ali, UCLA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coffee Break
2:45 – 3:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;session-2-historical-subjects-and-modes-of-expression-300--500-pm&quot;&gt;Session 2: Historical Subjects and Modes of Expression (3:00 – 5:00 pm)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chair, Letizia Osti, University of Milan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ibn Khaldūn in His Subjective Lexicon - The Emotional Constellation of an Intellectual in Transition&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Laila M. Jreis Navarro, Fondecyt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Kurdish about an Arabic Fatwā? Two Centuries of Kurdish Jurisprudence in ‘Abdulkarim al-Mudarris’s &lt;em&gt;Jawāhir al-Fatāwā&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Andrew Bush, Harvard Law School&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Study of Zayn al-Dīn al-Makhdūm’s &lt;em&gt;al-Ajwiba al-ʿAjība ʿan al-Asʾila al-Gharība&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Noorudeen Pattasseri, Hamad Bin Khalifa University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agenda Setting in Modern Coptic Death Memorials: Histories of the Deceased as Vehicles for Political Expression&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Weston Bland, University of Pennsylvania&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End of Workshop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>KITAB</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html">Arabic Pasts 2021 is happening from 7th - 9th of October.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Token Frequency Counter For OpenITI Texts</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Token Frequency Counter For OpenITI Texts" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts/">&lt;p&gt;One of the participants in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2020/07/24/call-for-participation/&quot;&gt;KITAB user group&lt;/a&gt; asked for an easy way to find out which are the most frequently used words in a text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are quite a lot of online tools that allow you to upload a file (or provide a link to a web page) and will produce a nice table with word counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this specific user group participant works with the largest text in the KITAB corpus, Ibn al-ʿAsakir’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenITI/0575AH/master/data/0571IbnCasakir/0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq/0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq.JK000916-ara1.mARkdown&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which weighs in at about 75 MB in the OpenITI version, and none of the sites I tried out was willing to accept such a large file. Others failed to produce a frequency list even with smaller books, probably because they don’t deal well with Arabic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of other options to create frequency lists from a text, but most involve using a programming language such as Python or R. Since most of our user group participants do not have any background in programming, we thought about using this question as an opportunity to show the user group how to install Python or R and run a simple script to create the frequency list (for example, using the fantastic R stylo library).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even demonstrating something simple like this to people who do not have Python or R installed and are working on different platforms always takes quite some time, time we didn’t have during our user group meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, after getting frustrated with a number of websites that promise to convert a text into a frequency list, I decided to build such an online tool for OpenITI myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was quite straightforward because I could build on work we have done for our &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/openiti/&quot;&gt;OpenITI Python library&lt;/a&gt; and other subprojects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://openiti.github.io/tokenFrequency/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, you upload a text and get a table with token frequency counts in return. You can browse through the table online or download it as a csv file (by clicking ‘Download table as csv file’ at the top of the table) that you can import into a spreadsheet program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An additional advantage of building such a tool yourself is that you can customise it to your own wishes. I added a number of options I would personally find useful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a minimum limit for the number of times a token needs to be in the text for it to be included in the table&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a list of ‘stop words’ – that is, tokens to be excluded from the count&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an option to define what the tool must consider a token. By default, it considers any sequence of Arabic-script characters a token (see below for a full list of these characters). You can also provide your own definition of what characters should be considered a token by providing a regular expression of your own. (Note for those who know about this type of stuff: Javascript’s regular-expression engine is used for the tokenisation, so &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MARKDOWN_HASHa9611d04392ad1acb0cd7642a0e405dfMARKDOWN_HASH&lt;/code&gt; refers only to ASCII word characters.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an option to split off a metadata header, so that words that are not really part of the text are not counted in. By default, the OpenITI metadata header is split off from the main body of the text, but you can also provide a regular expression of your own to split off headers that are delimited in another way.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a really quick build; if you would find more options useful, don’t hesitate to contact me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A cautionary note about tokens&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool extracts ‘tokens’ from the text and counts them. The word ‘token’ is frequently used as a synonym for ‘word’, but they are not exactly the same. A token is nothing more than a sequence of characters, in our case defined by default as an unbroken sequence of Arabic-script characters, bounded on either side by characters that do not belong to that list of characters (there are other ways to define tokens as well). The tool does not try to analyse this sequence of characters as a word with a specific meaning, a specific form of a specific verb or the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the token &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ولكتابه&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;em&gt;wa-li-kitabi-hi&lt;/em&gt;, ‘and for his book’) could be considered four separate words, but the tool considers it one token. The opposite is also true: the name ʿAbd Allah is written in Arabic using two separate tokens (in our definition), ʿAbd and Allah, and both are thus counted separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the plural of &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتاب&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;kitab&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;kutub&lt;/em&gt;, and both are considered (and counted as) separate tokens by the tool, although they are arguably the same word. This problem is compounded with verbs, since Arabic expresses their number, gender, tense and so on using prefixes and suffixes. Each form of the same verb is thus considered a separate token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that if you’re interested in how many times an author used a specific ‘word’ in the text, you may have to sum up a large number of different versions of the word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if we want to know how many times Ibn ʿAsakir uses the word &lt;em&gt;kitab&lt;/em&gt; in his &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt;, we could try to sum up the counts for these tokens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;count&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;token&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3560&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2585&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1805&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1320&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1204&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1111&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;492&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;278&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;276&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;263&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;196&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابيهما&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;108&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;103&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;96&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;91&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;87&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;81&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;47&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بالكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبنا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ولكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابهما&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;للكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;للكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتبه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابة&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبهما&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أفبكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتبهن&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتابان&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابان&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وبكتابه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;قرأالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابها&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابهم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتبكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتباه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بكتابكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بالكتابين&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابى&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وكتبك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتبات&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;قرأكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;الكتابان&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أقرألكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ككتابكم&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;تصنيفكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;والكتبا&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;بهذاالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتابنه&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;واكتابي&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;فقرأكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ولكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;وإنماالكتاب&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;لكتابك&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even that approach is not always successful. For example, the word &lt;em&gt;kataba&lt;/em&gt; (‘he wrote’) and the word &lt;em&gt;kutub&lt;/em&gt; (‘books’) are clearly separate words, but they are written in exactly the same way in unvocalised Arabic (&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt;) and are thus considered to be one token, and counted as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to know from the frequency list how often the token &lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;كتب&lt;/span&gt; refers to a book and how often to the act of writing. By way of illustration, I have marked in bold the cases in the table where there is uncertainty over whether the verb or the noun is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example also shows another use case for such frequency lists: it shows a number of tokens that are clearly errors in the text, often due to the omission of a space (marked in bold and italics in the table); these all appear only once or twice in the text. Combining such frequency information for all texts in the corpus could give us an idea of what tokens in our texts are likely to be errors and should be flagged as such. We are currently experimenting with the use of such frequency lists of single tokens (and of token bigrams – combinations of two adjacent tokens) extracted from the entire OpenITI corpus for identifying possible OCR mistakes in texts produced by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@openiti/openiti-aocp-9802865a6586&quot;&gt;OCR&lt;/a&gt; pipeline we are setting up to get additional texts into the corpus. More about this in a later blog post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix: list of Unicode characters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the tool considers any sequence of the following unicode characters a token:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ء&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER HAMZA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;آ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH MADDA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;أ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH HAMZA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ؤ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER WAW WITH HAMZA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;إ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH HAMZA BELOW&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ئ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER YEH WITH HAMZA ABOVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ا&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ب&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER BEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ة&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TEH MARBUTA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ت&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ث&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER THEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ج&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER JEEM&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ح&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER HAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;خ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER KHAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;د&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER DAL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ذ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER THAL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ر&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER REH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ز&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ZAIN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;س&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SEEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ش&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SHEEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ص&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SAD&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ض&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER DAD&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ط&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ظ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ZAH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ع&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER AIN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;غ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER GHAIN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ف&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER FEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ق&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER QAF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ك&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER KAF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ل&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER LAM&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;م&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER MEEM&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ن&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER NOON&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ه&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER HEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;و&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER WAW&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ى&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER ALEF MAKSURA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ي&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER YEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ً&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC FATHATAN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٌ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC DAMMATAN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٍ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC KASRATAN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;َ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC FATHA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ُ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC DAMMA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ِ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC KASRA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ّ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC SHADDA&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ْ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC SUKUN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٰ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER SUPERSCRIPT ALEF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ـ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC TATWEEL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٠&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ZERO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;١&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ONE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٢&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT TWO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٣&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT THREE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٤&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FOUR&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٥&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FIVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٦&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SIX&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٧&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٨&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;٩&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT NINE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٮ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER DOTLESS BEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ٹ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TTEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;پ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER PEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;چ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER TCHEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ژ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER JEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ک&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER KEHEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;گ&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER GAF&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ی&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER FARSI YEH&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;ے&lt;/span&gt; ARABIC LETTER YEH BARREE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۱&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ONE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۲&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT TWO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۳&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT THREE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۴&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FOUR&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۵&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT FIVE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۶&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SIX&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۷&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۸&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۹&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT NINE&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;۰&lt;/span&gt; EXTENDED ARABIC-INDIC DIGIT ZERO&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Verkinderen</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="viz" /><summary type="html">One of the participants in our KITAB user group asked for an easy way to find out which are the most frequently used words in a text.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-A-Token-Frequency-Counter-For-OpenITI-Texts//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Using the Many to Spot the Few</title><link href="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/d/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using the Many to Spot the Few" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://kitab-project-org.github.io/d</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/d/">&lt;p&gt;At present, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-corpus-metadata.azurewebsites.net/&quot;&gt;OpenITI/KITAB corpus&lt;/a&gt; comprises 10,243 text files, 6,268 of which are unique titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a large, and growing, number of texts makes quality control challenging. But at the same time, it is precisely this large number of texts that can be the basis for quantitative methods of quality control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I would like to briefly explore how we can make use of a large number of annotated lines of poetry for a simple quality check of such lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the texts in the OpenITI/KITAB corpus contain poetic verses. Many of these verses are found in texts that carry the word &lt;em&gt;diwan&lt;/em&gt; in the title; others are not. Some of these verses are annotated and tagged as verses; others are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of where verses are found, if they are annotated according to the OpenITI mARkdown system used by OpenITI/KITAB, the tag %~% is inserted either between two of the hemistichs of a verse or before or after a verse in case there are not two hemistichs (see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://alraqmiyyat.github.io/mARkdown/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; under ‘Verses of poetry’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many instances, the tag is inserted manually in the course of the annotation work carried out by KITAB team members. In the vast majority of cases, however, the tag is inserted automatically by KITAB when new text files are converted to the OpenITI mARkdown format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However the tag %~% has been inserted, the number of lines containing it is substantial, and if we search our corpus for lines containing %~%, we get tens of thousands of results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give a sense of the scale, for the following exploration, I have limited myself to texts attributed to authors whose date of death falls between the years 1 and 799 of the Hijri calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we limit ourselves to texts from within the said chronological window, there are far more than 300,000 lines that contain the tag %~%!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a large number should tell us something rather solid about lines of poetry in our corpus. Not least, it should tell us pretty accurately how long they typically are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The length of each string tagged as a line of poetry in our corpus can easily be determined computationally, and the resulting hundreds of thousands of values indeed give us a relatively good idea of what to expect from verses in terms of length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, outliers are of considerable interest when it comes to flagging strings that seem to be either too long or too short. The many can be used to spot the few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of these outliers are problematic, but the chance that they actually are is more than just a remote one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worthwhile plotting the relevant data to get a better sense and overview of how the lengths of strings which contain the tag %~% are distributed across the OpenITI/KITAB corpus (as has been said, for this exploration, the texts used fall within the chronological window 0001–0799 AH). The following figure shows a distribution in which the x-axis shows the AH death dates and the y-axis the lengths of the strings containing the tag %~%:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two facts are readily palpable: First, the bulk of the strings in our corpus which have been tagged as poetic verses are somewhere between thirty and eighty characters long (which in this exploration also includes non-Arabic characters). Second, not only are there outliers, but many of these outliers seem to accumulate around a few text files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we zoom in on strings whose length is between 80 and 300 characters, this can be seen more clearly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For example, the values eye-catchingly stacked at 0283 AH all belong to the text file containing Ibn al-Rumi’s &lt;em&gt;diwan&lt;/em&gt;. The highest character count value here is 278, which is considerably longer than expected from a line of poetry. Indeed, if we go into the text file and check up on this particular string, there are issues with the text file (see the image below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The reasons some of the strings that contain the tag %~% are too long differ. At the end of the day, it will be up to a human annotator to make a judgement call and fix what caused the problem (should there be any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, already at this point, the data that we can generate from our corpus allows us to identify files with ‘odd’ lines of poetry and directs us to the affected text files relatively efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, from the more than 300,000 lines that contain the tag %~%, fewer than 1,000 are longer than eighty characters, and fewer than 300 exceed 100 characters. The latter are scattered across only about thirty-five texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KITAB will automatically flag these cases in our yml version metadata files.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lorenz Nigst</name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="corpus" /><category term="viz" /><summary type="html">At present, the OpenITI/KITAB corpus comprises 10,243 text files, 6,268 of which are unique titles.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://kitab-project-org.github.io/images/old_blogs/2021-07-13-2//media/image1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>